window.quizData = [
  {
    question: "When was the modern state of Punjab formed?",
    options: [
      "1st November 1966",
      "1st November 1956",
      "15th August 1947",
      "15th August 1950",
    ],
    answer: "1st November 1966",
  },
  {
    question: "When did Pepsu merge with Punjab?",
    options: [
      "1st November 1956",
      "1st November 1966",
      "15th August 1947",
      "1st January 1955",
    ],
    answer: "1st November 1956",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which regions were included in Punjab, Haryana, and Chandigarh on 1st November 1966?",
    options: [
      "Punjab, Haryana, Chandigarh UT, Himachal UT",
      "Punjab, Haryana, Chandigarh, Jammu & Kashmir",
      "Punjab, Haryana, Delhi, Himachal Pradesh",
      "Punjab, Haryana, Chandigarh, Rajasthan",
    ],
    answer: "Punjab, Haryana, Chandigarh UT, Himachal UT",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who is known as the 'Father of Modern Punjabi Politics' and the first Chief Minister of Punjab?",
    options: [
      "Pratap Singh Kairon",
      "Beant Singh",
      "Surjit Singh Barnala",
      "Parkash Singh Badal",
    ],
    answer: "Pratap Singh Kairon",
  },
  {
    question: "Which party did Pratap Singh Kairon belong to?",
    options: ["Congress", "Akali Dal", "BJP", "Indian National Congress"],
    answer: "Congress",
  },
  {
    question: "Who was the first Sikh Chief Minister of Punjab?",
    options: [
      "Pratap Singh Kairon",
      "Beant Singh",
      "Surjit Singh Barnala",
      "Parkash Singh Badal",
    ],
    answer: "Pratap Singh Kairon",
  },
  {
    question: "When was the Green Revolution initiated in Punjab?",
    options: [
      "During the tenure of Pratap Singh Kairon",
      "During the tenure of Beant Singh",
      "In the 1990s under Parkash Singh Badal",
      "In 1980s under Surjit Singh Barnala",
    ],
    answer: "During the tenure of Pratap Singh Kairon",
  },
  {
    question: "In which year was Pratap Singh Kairon murdered?",
    options: ["1965", "1966", "1970", "1980"],
    answer: "1965",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which Chief Minister of Punjab was murdered in August 1995 in Chandigarh?",
    options: [
      "Beant Singh",
      "Surjit Singh Barnala",
      "Parkash Singh Badal",
      "Pratap Singh Kairon",
    ],
    answer: "Beant Singh",
  },
  {
    question: "When did Beant Singh serve as the Chief Minister of Punjab?",
    options: ["1992-1995", "1985-1990", "1990-1992", "2000-2005"],
    answer: "1992-1995",
  },
  {
    question: "Where was Beant Singh born?",
    options: ["Ludhiana", "Amritsar", "Patiala", "Jalandhar"],
    answer: "Ludhiana",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which President of India de-established the PEPSU Legislative Assembly?",
    options: [
      "Dr. Rajendra Prasad",
      "Dr. Sarvepalli Radhakrishnan",
      "Dr. Zakir Husain",
      "Dr. A.P.J. Abdul Kalam",
    ],
    answer: "Dr. Rajendra Prasad",
  },
  {
    question: "When was the PEPSU state established and de-established?",
    options: [
      "Established on 15th July 1948, de-established on 31st October 1956",
      "Established on 1st January 1947, de-established on 31st December 1955",
      "Established on 1st November 1950, de-established on 15th August 1960",
      "Established on 15th August 1947, de-established on 15th August 1955",
    ],
    answer:
      "Established on 15th July 1948, de-established on 31st October 1956",
  },
  {
    question: "Who was the first governor of PEPSU?",
    options: [
      "Yadavindra Singh",
      "Baba Kesar Singh",
      "Giani Gurmukh Singh",
      "Bhagat Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Yadavindra Singh",
  },
  {
    question: "Who was the first deputy governor of PEPSU?",
    options: [
      "Jagatjit Singh",
      "Raghbir Singh",
      "Brish Bhan",
      "Gian Singh Rarewala",
    ],
    answer: "Jagatjit Singh",
  },
  {
    question: "Who was the first Chief Minister of PEPSU?",
    options: [
      "Gian Singh Rarewala",
      "Raghbir Singh",
      "Brish Bhan",
      "Sardar Darbara Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Gian Singh Rarewala",
  },
  {
    question: "Who was the second Chief Minister of PEPSU?",
    options: [
      "Raghbir Singh",
      "Brish Bhan",
      "Gian Singh Rarewala",
      "Rupinder Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Raghbir Singh",
  },
  {
    question: "Who was the third and last Chief Minister of PEPSU?",
    options: [
      "Brish Bhan",
      "Gian Singh Rarewala",
      "Raghbir Singh",
      "Yadavindra Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Brish Bhan",
  },
  {
    question: "How many members were there in the PEPSU Legislative Assembly?",
    options: ["60", "50", "70", "80"],
    answer: "60",
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following was a six salute state in PEPSU?",
    options: ["Patiala", "Nalagarh", "Kalsia", "Jind"],
    answer: "Patiala",
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following was NOT a six salute state in PEPSU?",
    options: ["Kapurthala", "Jind", "Faridkot", "Nalagarh"],
    answer: "Nalagarh",
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following was a non-salute state in PEPSU?",
    options: ["Nalagarh", "Patiala", "Kapurthala", "Faridkot"],
    answer: "Nalagarh",
  },
  {
    question: "Which states were part of the PEPSU state?",
    options: [
      "Patiala, Jind, Kapurthala, Nabha, Faridkot, Malerkotla",
      "Patiala, Jind, Bhatinda, Gurdaspur, Amritsar",
      "Hoshiarpur, Firozpur, Kapurthala, Nawan Shahr",
      "Ludhiana, Jalandhar, Bathinda, Gurdaspur",
    ],
    answer: "Patiala, Jind, Kapurthala, Nabha, Faridkot, Malerkotla",
  },
  {
    question: "Who were the signatories of the Rajiv-Longowal Pact of 1985?",
    options: [
      "Rajiv Gandhi and Harchand Singh Longowal",
      "Rajiv Gandhi and Amarinder Singh",
      "Harchand Singh Longowal and Manmohan Singh",
      "Surjit Singh Barnala and Rajiv Gandhi",
    ],
    answer: "Rajiv Gandhi and Harchand Singh Longowal",
  },
  {
    question: "On which date was the Rajiv-Longowal Pact signed?",
    options: [
      "24th July 1985",
      "15th August 1985",
      "1st October 1985",
      "10th July 1984",
    ],
    answer: "24th July 1985",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who was the president of Akali Dal during the Rajiv-Longowal Pact?",
    options: [
      "Harchand Singh Longowal",
      "Prakash Singh Badal",
      "Surjit Singh Barnala",
      "Amarinder Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Harchand Singh Longowal",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following was a provision of the Rajiv-Longowal Pact of 1985?",
    options: [
      "Compensation to families, Army recruitment, Enquiry into 1984 killings",
      "Free education for all children, Farmers' loan waivers, Protection of river waters",
      "Promotion of English language, Protection of minorities, Reconciliation of all religious communities",
      "Distribution of land to farmers, Reduction of taxes, Increase in employment opportunities",
    ],
    answer:
      "Compensation to families, Army recruitment, Enquiry into 1984 killings",
  },
  {
    question: "Which act was passed in 1983 in Punjab for the armed forces?",
    options: [
      "Armed Forces (Punjab and Chandigarh) Special Powers Act (AFSPA)",
      "National Security Act",
      "Terrorist and Disruptive Activities (Prevention) Act (TADA)",
      "Public Safety Act",
    ],
    answer: "Armed Forces (Punjab and Chandigarh) Special Powers Act (AFSPA)",
  },
  {
    question:
      "When was the Armed Forces (Punjab and Chandigarh) Special Powers Act (AFSPA) withdrawn?",
    options: ["1997", "2000", "1987", "1995"],
    answer: "1997",
  },
  {
    question:
      "When did the Disturbed Areas Act remain in force in Chandigarh until it was struck down by the High Court?",
    options: ["2012", "2005", "2000", "1998"],
    answer: "2012",
  },
  {
    question: "Which princely state of Punjab became part of Haryana?",
    options: ["Loharu State", "Patiala State", "Faridkot State", "Nabha State"],
    answer: "Loharu State",
  },
  {
    question: "When was the Punjab Reorganisation Act passed?",
    options: ["1966", "1956", "1971", "1947"],
    answer: "1966",
  },
  {
    question: "Which divisions became part of Pakistan in 1947?",
    options: [
      "Multan, Rawalpindi, Lahore",
      "Jalandhar, Delhi, Lahore",
      "Patiala, Ludhiana, Ambala",
      "Sialkot, Ferozepur, Jalandhar",
    ],
    answer: "Multan, Rawalpindi, Lahore",
  },
  {
    question: "Which division is NOT a part of Punjab?",
    options: ["Ambala", "Rawalpindi", "Lahore", "Jalandhar"],
    answer: "Rawalpindi",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who was the Chief Minister of Punjab who laid the foundation of the Green Revolution?",
    options: [
      "Partap Singh Kairon",
      "Bikram Singh Majithia",
      "Parkash Singh Badal",
      "Giani Zail Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Partap Singh Kairon",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is known as the Father of the Green Revolution?",
    options: [
      "Norman Borlaug",
      "MS Swaminathan",
      "Har Gobind Khorana",
      "Amartya Sen",
    ],
    answer: "Norman Borlaug",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is known as the Father of the Green Revolution in India?",
    options: [
      "MS Swaminathan",
      "Dr. Verghese Kurien",
      "Dr. Arun Krishnan",
      "Vishal Tewari",
    ],
    answer: "MS Swaminathan",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who is known as the Father of the White Revolution (milk production)?",
    options: [
      "Dr. Verghese Kurien",
      "Norman Borlaug",
      "MS Swaminathan",
      "Dr. Arun Krishnan",
    ],
    answer: "Dr. Verghese Kurien",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who is known as the Father of the Blue Revolution (aquaculture and fisheries) in India?",
    options: [
      "Dr. Arun Krishnan",
      "Dr. Verghese Kurien",
      "Norman Borlaug",
      "Sam Pitroda",
    ],
    answer: "Dr. Arun Krishnan",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who is known as the Father of the Yellow Revolution (oilseeds) in India?",
    options: [
      "Sam Pitroda",
      "Dr. Arun Krishnan",
      "Vishal Tewari",
      "Nirpakh Tutej",
    ],
    answer: "Sam Pitroda",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who is known as the Father of the Golden Revolution (horticulture) in India?",
    options: [
      "Nirpakh Tutej",
      "Vishal Tewari",
      "Durgesh Patel",
      "Dr. Verghese Kurien",
    ],
    answer: "Nirpakh Tutej",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who is known as the Father of the Pink Revolution (meat production) in India?",
    options: [
      "Durgesh Patel",
      "Vishal Tewari",
      "Dr. Arun Krishnan",
      "Dr. Verghese Kurien",
    ],
    answer: "Durgesh Patel",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who is known as the Father of the Red Revolution (tomatoes and meat) in India?",
    options: ["Vishal Tewari", "Durgesh Patel", "Sam Pitroda", "Nirpakh Tutej"],
    answer: "Vishal Tewari",
  },
  {
    question: "What is the boundary line between Pakistan and Punjab known as?",
    options: [
      "Radcliffe Line",
      "Durand Line",
      "McMahon Line",
      "Line of Control",
    ],
    answer: "Radcliffe Line",
  },
  {
    question: "Which boundary line is the border between India and China?",
    options: [
      "McMahon Line",
      "Durand Line",
      "Radcliffe Line",
      "Line of Control",
    ],
    answer: "McMahon Line",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is the boundary line between India and Afghanistan known as?",
    options: [
      "Durand Line",
      "Radcliffe Line",
      "McMahon Line",
      "Line of Control",
    ],
    answer: "Durand Line",
  },
  {
    question: "Who was the chairman of the Punjab Boundary Commission in 1947?",
    options: [
      "Cyril Radcliffe",
      "Mehr Chand Mahajan",
      "Teja Singh",
      "Din Mohamed",
    ],
    answer: "Cyril Radcliffe",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who were the members of the Punjab Boundary Commission in 1947? (Select all that apply)",
    options: [
      "Cyril Radcliffe",
      "Mehr Chand Mahajan",
      "Teja Singh",
      "Din Mohamed",
      "Muhammad Munir",
      "Jagdev Singh Talwandi",
    ],
    answer:
      "Cyril Radcliffe, Mehr Chand Mahajan, Teja Singh, Din Mohamed, Muhammad Munir",
  },
  {
    question: "Who was the chief minister of Punjab after partition in 1966?",
    options: [
      "Giani Gurmukh Singh Musafir",
      "Gopi Chand Bhargava",
      "Bhim Sen Sachar",
      "Partap Singh Kairon",
    ],
    answer: "Giani Gurmukh Singh Musafir",
  },
  {
    question: "Who was the Chief Minister of Punjab in 1947?",
    options: [
      "Gopi Chand Bhargava",
      "Giani Gurmukh Singh Musafir",
      "Bhim Sen Sachar",
      "Partap Singh Kairon",
    ],
    answer: "Gopi Chand Bhargava",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who served as the Chief Minister of Punjab after Gopi Chand Bhargava?",
    options: [
      "Bhim Sen Sachar",
      "Partap Singh Kairon",
      "Ram Kishan",
      "Giani Gurmukh Singh Musafir",
    ],
    answer: "Bhim Sen Sachar",
  },
  {
    question: "Which political party did Jagdev Singh Talwandi belong to?",
    options: [
      "Shiromani Akali Dal",
      "Indian National Congress",
      "Bharatiya Janata Party",
      "Communist Party of India",
    ],
    answer: "Shiromani Akali Dal",
  },
  {
    question: "Who was the second Chief Minister of Punjab after Partition?",
    options: [
      "Bhim Sen Sachar",
      "Partap Singh Kairon",
      "Ram Kishan",
      "Gopi Chand Bhargava",
    ],
    answer: "Bhim Sen Sachar",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who was the Chief Minister of Punjab after Giani Gurmukh Singh Musafir?",
    options: [
      "Gurnam Singh",
      "Lachhman Singh Gill",
      "Parkash Singh Badal",
      "Zail Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Gurnam Singh",
  },
  {
    question: "Who served as the Chief Minister of Punjab after Gurnam Singh?",
    options: [
      "Lachhman Singh Gill",
      "Parkash Singh Badal",
      "Zail Singh",
      "Darbara Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Lachhman Singh Gill",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following served as the Chief Minister of Punjab the most number of times?",
    options: [
      "Parkash Singh Badal",
      "Beant Singh",
      "Surjit Singh Barnala",
      "Amarinder Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Parkash Singh Badal",
  },
  {
    question: "Who was the Chief Minister of Punjab in 1978?",
    options: [
      "Zail Singh",
      "Darbara Singh",
      "Surjit Singh Barnala",
      "Parkash Singh Badal",
    ],
    answer: "Zail Singh",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who was the Chief Minister of Punjab immediately before Surjit Singh Barnala?",
    options: [
      "Darbara Singh",
      "Beant Singh",
      "Harcharan Singh Brar",
      "Rajinder Kaur Bhattal",
    ],
    answer: "Darbara Singh",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who was the first woman to serve as the Chief Minister of Punjab?",
    options: [
      "Rajinder Kaur Bhattal",
      "Amarinder Singh",
      "Charanjit Singh Channi",
      "Beant Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Rajinder Kaur Bhattal",
  },
  {
    question: "Who was the Chief Minister of Punjab before Beant Singh?",
    options: [
      "Surjit Singh Barnala",
      "Harcharan Singh Brar",
      "Parkash Singh Badal",
      "Amarinder Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Surjit Singh Barnala",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following was a Chief Minister of Punjab after 2000?",
    options: [
      "Amarinder Singh",
      "Charanjit Singh Channi",
      "Bhagwant Mann",
      "Rajinder Kaur Bhattal",
    ],
    answer: "Amarinder Singh",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who succeeded Charanjit Singh Channi as the Chief Minister of Punjab?",
    options: [
      "Bhagwant Mann",
      "Parkash Singh Badal",
      "Harcharan Singh Brar",
      "Beant Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Bhagwant Mann",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who was the President of the Board of Administration formed after the unification of Punjab in 1849?",
    options: [
      "Henry Montgomery Lawrence",
      "John Lawrence",
      "Charles Mansel",
      "Justice JC Shah",
    ],
    answer: "Henry Montgomery Lawrence",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following positions did John Lawrence hold in the Board of Administration formed in 1849?",
    options: ["Military", "Finance", "Judicial", "President"],
    answer: "Finance",
  },
  {
    question: "Who were the members of the Punjab Boundary Commission in 1966?",
    options: [
      "S. Dutt, M. M. Philips, Justice J. C. Shah",
      "Henry Montgomery Lawrence, Charles Mansel, John Lawrence",
      "Gurnam Singh, Lachhman Singh Gill, Parkash Singh Badal",
      "S. Dutt, Gurnam Singh, Harcharan Singh Brar",
    ],
    answer: "S. Dutt, M. M. Philips, Justice J. C. Shah",
  },
  {
    question: "Who was the first Lokpal of Punjab?",
    options: [
      "S. S. Sodhi",
      "Justice Vinod Kumar Sharma",
      "Justice J. C. Shah",
      "Rajinder Kaur Bhattal",
    ],
    answer: "S. S. Sodhi",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the current Lokpal of Punjab?",
    options: [
      "Justice Vinod Kumar Sharma",
      "S. S. Sodhi",
      "Justice J. C. Shah",
      "Gurnam Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Justice Vinod Kumar Sharma",
  },
  {
    question: "Under which Act was the Punjab Lokayukta formed?",
    options: [
      "Punjab Lokpal Act 1996",
      "Punjab Lokayukta Act 1997",
      "Punjab Justice Act 2000",
      "Punjab Anti-Corruption Act 1985",
    ],
    answer: "Punjab Lokpal Act 1996",
  },
  {
    question: "How many Lok Sabha seats does Punjab have?",
    options: ["13", "11", "15", "18"],
    answer: "13",
  },
  {
    question: "How many Rajya Sabha seats are allocated to Punjab?",
    options: ["7", "6", "8", "5"],
    answer: "7",
  },
  {
    question: "How many seats are there in the Punjab Vidhan Sabha?",
    options: ["117", "120", "125", "100"],
    answer: "117",
  },
  {
    question:
      "How many Scheduled Caste (SC) seats are there in the Punjab Vidhan Sabha?",
    options: ["34", "30", "28", "25"],
    answer: "34",
  },
  {
    question: "When was the Sikh Gurudwara Act passed?",
    options: ["1925", "1930", "1940", "1950"],
    answer: "1925",
  },
  {
    question: "When was the Sikh Gurudwara Act passed?",
    options: ["1925", "1920", "1930", "1940"],
    answer: "1925",
  },
  {
    question:
      "When was the Shiromani Gurudwara Prabandhak Committee (SGPC) formed?",
    options: [
      "16 November 1920",
      "1 January 1921",
      "15 August 1922",
      "12 December 1925",
    ],
    answer: "16 November 1920",
  },
  {
    question: "Who was the first president of the SGPC?",
    options: [
      "Sundar Singh Mahjithia",
      "Kharak Singh",
      "Gurcharan Singh Tohra",
      "Gopal Singh Qaumi",
    ],
    answer: "Sundar Singh Mahjithia",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following was the longest-serving president of the SGPC?",
    options: [
      "Gurcharan Singh Tohra",
      "Kharak Singh",
      "Bibi Jagir Kaur",
      "Gopal Singh Qaumi",
    ],
    answer: "Gurcharan Singh Tohra",
  },
  {
    question: "Who served as the shortest-serving president of the SGPC?",
    options: [
      "Gopal Singh Qaumi",
      "Kharak Singh",
      "Bibi Jagir Kaur",
      "Harjinder Singh Dhami",
    ],
    answer: "Gopal Singh Qaumi",
  },
  {
    question: "Who was the first woman president of the SGPC?",
    options: [
      "Bibi Jagir Kaur",
      "Bibi Amrit Kaur",
      "Rajinder Kaur Bhattal",
      "Sukhbir Kaur",
    ],
    answer: "Bibi Jagir Kaur",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the current president of the SGPC?",
    options: [
      "Harjinder Singh Dhami",
      "Gurcharan Singh Tohra",
      "Sundar Singh Mahjithia",
      "Kharak Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Harjinder Singh Dhami",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which monument is associated with the Jallianwala Bagh massacre?",
    options: [
      "Flame of Liberty",
      "Statue of Unity",
      "Independence Memorial",
      "Martyrs' Memorial",
    ],
    answer: "Flame of Liberty",
  },
  {
    question: "On which date did the Jallianwala Bagh massacre occur?",
    options: [
      "13 April 1919",
      "15 August 1947",
      "25 December 1918",
      "23 March 1919",
    ],
    answer: "13 April 1919",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who was the Lieutenant Governor of Punjab during the Jallianwala Bagh massacre?",
    options: [
      "Michael O'Dwyer",
      "Reginald Dyer",
      "Lord Chelmsford",
      "Lord Hardinge",
    ],
    answer: "Michael O'Dwyer",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who was the English officer responsible for the Jallianwala Bagh massacre?",
    options: [
      "General Reginald Dyer",
      "General Charles Napier",
      "Lieutenant General John Nixon",
      "General Lord Kitchener",
    ],
    answer: "General Reginald Dyer",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who chaired the Hunter Commission investigating the Jallianwala Bagh massacre?",
    options: [
      "Lord Hunter",
      "Lord Curzon",
      "Lord Mountbatten",
      "Lord Lansdowne",
    ],
    answer: "Lord Hunter",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following was an Indian member of the Hunter Commission?",
    options: [
      "Chimanlal Harilal Setalvad",
      "Pandit Jawaharlal Nehru",
      "Sardar Patel",
      "Subhas Chandra Bose",
    ],
    answer: "Chimanlal Harilal Setalvad",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which person resigned from the Viceroy's Executive Council after the Jallianwala Bagh massacre?",
    options: [
      "Shankar Narayana",
      "Lala Lajpat Rai",
      "C.R. Das",
      "Mahatma Gandhi",
    ],
    answer: "Shankar Narayana",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who returned his knighthood in protest of the Jallianwala Bagh massacre?",
    options: [
      "Rabindranath Tagore",
      "Mahatma Gandhi",
      "Sarojini Naidu",
      "Subhas Chandra Bose",
    ],
    answer: "Rabindranath Tagore",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who returned the title ‘Kesar-i-Hind’ in protest against the Jallianwala Bagh massacre?",
    options: [
      "Mahatma Gandhi",
      "Jawaharlal Nehru",
      "Lala Lajpat Rai",
      "Sardar Vallabhbhai Patel",
    ],
    answer: "Mahatma Gandhi",
  },
  {
    question: "Where was the first session of the Sikh League held?",
    options: ["Amritsar", "Lahore", "Chandigarh", "Patiala"],
    answer: "Amritsar",
  },
  {
    question: "On which date was the Sikh League founded?",
    options: [
      "19 December 1919",
      "15 August 1920",
      "1 January 1921",
      "30 November 1920",
    ],
    answer: "19 December 1919",
  },
  {
    question: "Who was the first president of the Sikh League?",
    options: [
      "Gajjan Singh",
      "Gurcharan Singh Tohra",
      "Sundar Singh Majithia",
      "Kharak Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Gajjan Singh",
  },
  {
    question: "When was the Penal Code introduced in Punjab?",
    options: ["1860", "1857", "1871", "1900"],
    answer: "1860",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which commission was appointed by the Government of India in 1953 for state reorganization?",
    options: [
      "State Reorganization Commission",
      "Simon Commission",
      "Sub-Committee of States",
      "Indian Constitution Commission",
    ],
    answer: "State Reorganization Commission",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who were the members of the State Reorganization Commission appointed in 1953?",
    options: [
      "Justice Fazal Ali, KM Panikkar, HN Kunzru",
      "Jawaharlal Nehru, Sardar Patel, Rajendra Prasad",
      "B.R. Ambedkar, Jawaharlal Nehru, Maulana Azad",
      "Indira Gandhi, Lal Bahadur Shastri, Rajiv Gandhi",
    ],
    answer: "Justice Fazal Ali, KM Panikkar, HN Kunzru",
  },
  {
    question:
      "When was the report of the State Reorganization Commission submitted?",
    options: ["1955", "1956", "1954", "1957"],
    answer: "1955",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which Act was recommended by the State Reorganization Commission in 1955?",
    options: [
      "States Reorganisation Act",
      "Indian Independence Act",
      "The Constitution of India",
      "Panchayati Raj Act",
    ],
    answer: "States Reorganisation Act",
  },
  {
    question: "When did the States Reorganisation Act come into effect?",
    options: [
      "1 November 1956",
      "15 August 1950",
      "26 January 1950",
      "1 January 1957",
    ],
    answer: "1 November 1956",
  },
  {
    question:
      "How many states and centrally administered territories were formed after the States Reorganisation Act?",
    options: [
      "14 states and 6 centrally administered territories",
      "12 states and 8 centrally administered territories",
      "16 states and 4 centrally administered territories",
      "18 states and 5 centrally administered territories",
    ],
    answer: "14 states and 6 centrally administered territories",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who was the first Asian to be elected as the chairman of the Commonwealth Parliamentarian Executive Forum?",
    options: [
      "Dr. Balram Jakhar",
      "Dr. Manmohan Singh",
      "Indira Gandhi",
      "Atal Bihari Vajpayee",
    ],
    answer: "Dr. Balram Jakhar",
  },
  {
    question: "Dr. Balram Jakhar was from which place in Punjab?",
    options: ["Abohar (Fazilka)", "Patiala", "Amritsar", "Ludhiana"],
    answer: "Abohar (Fazilka)",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which place in Punjab is referred to as the 'California of Punjab' due to its fruit production?",
    options: ["Abohar", "Amritsar", "Ludhiana", "Fazilka"],
    answer: "Abohar",
  },
  {
    question: "Which animal is found in the Abohar Wildlife Sanctuary?",
    options: ["Blackbuck", "Tiger", "Lion", "Elephant"],
    answer: "Blackbuck",
  },
  {
    question: "Who had the longest tenure as the Speaker of the Lok Sabha?",
    options: [
      "Dr. Balram Jakhar",
      "Meira Kumar",
      "Somnath Chatterjee",
      "Somsundaram Pillai",
    ],
    answer: "Dr. Balram Jakhar",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the Member of Parliament from Fatehgarh Sahib?",
    options: [
      "Amrinder Singh Brar (Raja Warring)",
      "Charanjit Singh Channi",
      "Amar Singh",
      "Dr. Dharamvir Gandhi",
    ],
    answer: "Amar Singh",
  },
  {
    question: "Which MP represents the constituency of Ludhiana?",
    options: [
      "Amritpal Singh",
      "Charanjit Singh Channi",
      "Amrinder Singh Brar (Raja Warring)",
      "Dr. Dharamvir Gandhi",
    ],
    answer: "Amrinder Singh Brar (Raja Warring)",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the MP for Khadoor Sahib?",
    options: [
      "Amritpal Singh",
      "Dr. Dharamvir Gandhi",
      "Charanjit Singh Channi",
      "Amar Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Amritpal Singh",
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following MPs represents Jalandhar?",
    options: [
      "Dr. Dharamvir Gandhi",
      "Amritpal Singh",
      "Charanjit Singh Channi",
      "Amar Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Charanjit Singh Channi",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the MP from Patiala?",
    options: [
      "Dr. Dharamvir Gandhi",
      "Charanjit Singh Channi",
      "Amrinder Singh Brar (Raja Warring)",
      "Amritpal Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Dr. Dharamvir Gandhi",
  },
  {
    question: "Which MP represents the constituency of Hoshiarpur?",
    options: [
      "Dr. Raj Kumar Chabbewal",
      "Gurmeet Singh Meet Hayer",
      "Harsimrat Kaur Badal",
      "Sarabjeet Singh Khalsa",
    ],
    answer: "Dr. Raj Kumar Chabbewal",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the Member of Parliament for Amritsar?",
    options: [
      "Gurjeet Singh Aujla",
      "Dr. Raj Kumar Chabbewal",
      "Sukhvinder Singh Randhawa",
      "Sher Singh Ghubaya",
    ],
    answer: "Gurjeet Singh Aujla",
  },
  {
    question: "Which MP represents the constituency of Sangrur?",
    options: [
      "Sarvjit Singh Kang",
      "Gurmeet Singh Meet Hayer",
      "Malvinder Singh Kang",
      "Harsimrat Kaur Badal",
    ],
    answer: "Gurmeet Singh Meet Hayer",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the Member of Parliament for Bhatinda?",
    options: [
      "Harsimrat Kaur Badal",
      "Malvinder Singh Kang",
      "Sukhvinder Singh Randhawa",
      "Sher Singh Ghubaya",
    ],
    answer: "Harsimrat Kaur Badal",
  },
  {
    question: "Who represents the constituency of Anandpur Sahib?",
    options: [
      "Malvinder Singh Kang",
      "Sarvjit Singh Khalsa",
      "Sukhvinder Singh Randhawa",
      "Sher Singh Ghubaya",
    ],
    answer: "Malvinder Singh Kang",
  },
  {
    question: "Which MP represents Faridkot?",
    options: [
      "Sarvjit Singh Khalsa",
      "Sukhvinder Singh Randhawa",
      "Gurmeet Singh Meet Hayer",
      "Harsimrat Kaur Badal",
    ],
    answer: "Sarvjit Singh Khalsa",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the Member of Parliament from Ferozpur?",
    options: [
      "Sher Singh Ghubaya",
      "Sukhvinder Singh Randhawa",
      "Charanjit Singh Channi",
      "Amritpal Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Sher Singh Ghubaya",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the MP from Gurdaspur?",
    options: [
      "Sukhvinder Singh Randhawa",
      "Sher Singh Ghubaya",
      "Dr. Dharamvir Gandhi",
      "Gurmeet Singh Meet Hayer",
    ],
    answer: "Sukhvinder Singh Randhawa",
  },
  {
    question: "Who was the first Chief Minister of Punjab?",
    options: [
      "Gopi Chand Bhargava",
      "Parkash Singh Badal",
      "Beant Singh",
      "Harcharan Singh Brar",
    ],
    answer: "Gopi Chand Bhargava",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the current Governor of Punjab?",
    options: [
      "Banwarilal Purohit",
      "Dharma Vira",
      "Gulab Chand Kataria",
      "Bhairab Dutt Pande",
    ],
    answer: "Gulab Chand Kataria",
  },
  {
    question: "Who was the first Sikh Governor of Punjab?",
    options: [
      "Ujjal Singh",
      "Chandulal Madhavlal Trivedi",
      "Chandeshwar Prasad Narayan Singh",
      "Bhairab Dutt Pande",
    ],
    answer: "Ujjal Singh",
  },
  {
    question: "Which Governor of Punjab had the longest tenure?",
    options: [
      "Dadappa Chintappa Pavate",
      "Dharma Vira",
      "Banwarilal Purohit",
      "Chandulal Madhavlal Trivedi",
    ],
    answer: "Dadappa Chintappa Pavate",
  },
  {
    question: "Who was the Governor of Punjab during Operation Blue Star?",
    options: [
      "Bhairab Dutt Pande",
      "Dharma Vira",
      "Ujjal Singh",
      "Banwarilal Purohit",
    ],
    answer: "Bhairab Dutt Pande",
  },
  {
    question: "Who was the Governor of Punjab when PEPSU was merged?",
    options: [
      "Chandeshwar Prasad Narayan Singh",
      "Chandulal Madhavlal Trivedi",
      "Ujjal Singh",
      "Bhairab Dutt Pande",
    ],
    answer: "Chandeshwar Prasad Narayan Singh",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which Governor of Punjab served after the formation of the state of Punjab in 1966?",
    options: [
      "Banwarilal Purohit",
      "Gulab Chand Kataria",
      "Ujjal Singh",
      "Dharma Vira",
    ],
    answer: "Ujjal Singh",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following governors served between 1966 and the present in Punjab?",
    options: [
      "Gulab Chand Kataria",
      "Banwarilal Purohit",
      "Chandulal Madhavlal Trivedi",
      "Dadappa Chintappa Pavate",
    ],
    answer: "Gulab Chand Kataria",
  },
  {
    question: "Who was the Governor of Punjab before Gulab Chand Kataria?",
    options: [
      "Banwarilal Purohit",
      "Bhairab Dutt Pande",
      "Ujjal Singh",
      "Dharma Vira",
    ],
    answer: "Banwarilal Purohit",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who was the first Governor of Punjab after the state reorganization in 1966?",
    options: [
      "Dharma Vira",
      "Dadappa Chintappa Pavate",
      "Chandulal Madhavlal Trivedi",
      "Ujjal Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Dharma Vira",
  },
  {
    question: "Who was the president of Punjab Riyasti Praja Mandal?",
    options: [
      "Sewa Singh Thikrivala",
      "Bhagwan Singh",
      "Maharaja Bhupinder Singh",
      "Kultar Singh Sandhwan",
    ],
    answer: "Sewa Singh Thikrivala",
  },
  {
    question: "When was the Punjab Riyasti Praja Mandal formed?",
    options: [
      "17 June 1928",
      "15 August 1947",
      "26 March 1952",
      "1 January 1940",
    ],
    answer: "17 June 1928",
  },
  {
    question: "Who was the secretary of the Punjab Riyasti Praja Mandal?",
    options: [
      "Bhagwan Singh",
      "Sewa Singh Thikrivala",
      "Maharaja Bhupinder Singh",
      "Gurcharan Singh Tohra",
    ],
    answer: "Bhagwan Singh",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following was the main opposition of the Punjab Riyasti Praja Mandal?",
    options: [
      "Maharaja Bhupinder Singh of Patiala",
      "Maharaja Hari Singh of Jammu and Kashmir",
      "Maharaja of Amritsar",
      "Maharaja of Kapurthala",
    ],
    answer: "Maharaja Bhupinder Singh of Patiala",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Where did the first session of the Punjab Riyasti Praja Mandal take place?",
    options: ["Lahore", "Amritsar", "Ludhiana", "Mansa"],
    answer: "Lahore",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Where did the second session of the Punjab Riyasti Praja Mandal take place?",
    options: ["Ludhiana", "Lahore", "Patiala", "Mansa"],
    answer: "Ludhiana",
  },
  {
    question: "When was the first election of Punjab held?",
    options: [
      "26 March 1952",
      "15 August 1947",
      "1 January 1950",
      "17 June 1928",
    ],
    answer: "26 March 1952",
  },
  {
    question: "In which year was the Punjab Legislative Council removed?",
    options: ["1970", "1966", "1952", "1980"],
    answer: "1970",
  },
  {
    question: "How many districts are there in Punjab?",
    options: ["23", "22", "24", "21"],
    answer: "23",
  },
  {
    question: "Which district was the 21st district of Punjab formed from?",
    options: ["Gurdaspur", "Firozpur", "Sangrur", "Hoshiarpur"],
    answer: "Gurdaspur",
  },
  {
    question: "Which district was the 22nd district of Punjab formed from?",
    options: ["Firozpur", "Gurdaspur", "Sangrur", "Patiala"],
    answer: "Firozpur",
  },
  {
    question: "Which district was the 23rd district of Punjab formed from?",
    options: ["Sangrur", "Mansa", "Patiala", "Firozpur"],
    answer: "Sangrur",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the current Speaker of the Punjab Vidhan Sabha?",
    options: [
      "Kultar Singh Sandhwan",
      "Charanjit Singh Channi",
      "Sukhdev Singh Dhindsa",
      "Rupinder Kaur Rubi",
    ],
    answer: "Kultar Singh Sandhwan",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which constituency does the current Speaker of Punjab Vidhan Sabha, Kultar Singh Sandhwan, represent?",
    options: ["Kotkapura", "Jalandhar", "Faridkot", "Patiala"],
    answer: "Kotkapura",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who was the first speaker of the Punjab Vidhan Sabha after independence?",
    options: [
      "Kapur Singh",
      "Shahab-ud-din Virk",
      "Harbans Lal Gupta",
      "Satya Prakash Singha",
    ],
    answer: "Kapur Singh",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which political party did Shahab-ud-din Virk belong to, the first pre-independence Speaker of the Punjab Vidhan Sabha?",
    options: [
      "Unionist Party",
      "Indian National Congress",
      "Shiromani Akali Dal",
      "BJP",
    ],
    answer: "Unionist Party",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who was the second pre-independence Speaker of the Punjab Vidhan Sabha?",
    options: [
      "Satya Prakash Singha",
      "Shahab-ud-din Virk",
      "Harbans Lal Gupta",
      "Kapur Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Satya Prakash Singha",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who served as the Speaker of the Punjab Vidhan Sabha from 1964 to 1967?",
    options: [
      "Harbans Lal Gupta",
      "Kultar Singh Sandhwan",
      "Kapur Singh",
      "Satya Prakash Singha",
    ],
    answer: "Harbans Lal Gupta",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the current Speaker of the Punjab Vidhan Sabha?",
    options: [
      "Kultar Singh Sandhwan",
      "Harbans Lal Gupta",
      "Kapur Singh",
      "Shahab-ud-din Virk",
    ],
    answer: "Kultar Singh Sandhwan",
  },
  {
    question: "How many parliamentary constituencies are there in Punjab?",
    options: ["13", "15", "20", "23"],
    answer: "13",
  },
  {
    question: "How many parliament seats does Punjab have?",
    options: ["20", "18", "25", "22"],
    answer: "20",
  },
  {
    question: "When was the first time President's Rule imposed in Punjab?",
    options: [
      "20 June 1951 to 17 April 1952 (302 days)",
      "5 July 1966 to 1 November 1966 (119 days)",
      "23 August 1968 to 17 February 1969 (178 days)",
      "14 June 1971 to 17 March 1972 (277 days)",
    ],
    answer: "20 June 1951 to 17 April 1952 (302 days)",
  },
  {
    question: "When was the second time President's Rule imposed in Punjab?",
    options: [
      "23 August 1968 to 17 February 1969 (178 days)",
      "14 June 1971 to 17 March 1972 (277 days)",
      "5 July 1966 to 1 November 1966 (119 days)",
      "17 February 1980 to 6 June 1980 (110 days)",
    ],
    answer: "5 July 1966 to 1 November 1966 (119 days)",
  },
  {
    question: "When was the third time President's Rule imposed in Punjab?",
    options: [
      "23 August 1968 to 17 February 1969 (178 days)",
      "5 July 1966 to 1 November 1966 (119 days)",
      "14 June 1971 to 17 March 1972 (277 days)",
      "20 June 1951 to 17 April 1952 (302 days)",
    ],
    answer: "23 August 1968 to 17 February 1969 (178 days)",
  },
  {
    question: "When was the fourth time President's Rule imposed in Punjab?",
    options: [
      "14 June 1971 to 17 March 1972 (277 days)",
      "17 February 1980 to 6 June 1980 (110 days)",
      "10 October 1983 to 29 September 1985 (1 year 354 days)",
      "11 May 1987 to 25 February 1992 (4 years 259 days)",
    ],
    answer: "14 June 1971 to 17 March 1972 (277 days)",
  },
  {
    question: "When was the fifth time President's Rule imposed in Punjab?",
    options: [
      "30 April 1977 to 20 June 1977 (51 days)",
      "17 February 1980 to 6 June 1980 (110 days)",
      "10 October 1983 to 29 September 1985 (1 year 354 days)",
      "23 August 1968 to 17 February 1969 (178 days)",
    ],
    answer: "30 April 1977 to 20 June 1977 (51 days)",
  },
  {
    question: "When was the sixth time President's Rule imposed in Punjab?",
    options: [
      "17 February 1980 to 6 June 1980 (110 days)",
      "11 May 1987 to 25 February 1992 (4 years 259 days)",
      "10 October 1983 to 29 September 1985 (1 year 354 days)",
      "5 July 1966 to 1 November 1966 (119 days)",
    ],
    answer: "17 February 1980 to 6 June 1980 (110 days)",
  },
  {
    question: "When was the seventh time President's Rule imposed in Punjab?",
    options: [
      "10 October 1983 to 29 September 1985 (1 year 354 days)",
      "23 August 1968 to 17 February 1969 (178 days)",
      "11 May 1987 to 25 February 1992 (4 years 259 days)",
      "14 June 1971 to 17 March 1972 (277 days)",
    ],
    answer: "10 October 1983 to 29 September 1985 (1 year 354 days)",
  },
  {
    question: "When was the eighth time President's Rule imposed in Punjab?",
    options: [
      "11 May 1987 to 25 February 1992 (4 years 259 days)",
      "5 July 1966 to 1 November 1966 (119 days)",
      "20 June 1951 to 17 April 1952 (302 days)",
      "30 April 1977 to 20 June 1977 (51 days)",
    ],
    answer: "11 May 1987 to 25 February 1992 (4 years 259 days)",
  },
  {
    question: "Who was the Governor of Punjab with the shortest tenure?",
    options: [
      "Hokishe Sema",
      "Chandulal Madhavlal Trivedi",
      "Chandeshwar Prasad Narayan Singh",
      "Dharma Vira",
    ],
    answer: "Hokishe Sema",
  },
  {
    question: "Where was the headquarters of the Hindustan Ghadar Party?",
    options: ["San Francisco", "Amritsar", "Lahore", "Karachi"],
    answer: "San Francisco",
  },
  {
    question: "When was the Hindustan Ghadar Party founded?",
    options: [
      "15 July 1913",
      "1 August 1914",
      "25 December 1912",
      "10 November 1915",
    ],
    answer: "15 July 1913",
  },
  {
    question: "Who were the founders of the Hindustan Ghadar Party?",
    options: [
      "Lala Hardial and Sohan Singh Bhakna",
      "Bhagat Singh and Chandra Shekhar Azad",
      "Mahatma Gandhi and Jawaharlal Nehru",
      "Subhas Chandra Bose and Rajguru",
    ],
    answer: "Lala Hardial and Sohan Singh Bhakna",
  },
  {
    question: "What was the initial name of the Hindustan Ghadar Party?",
    options: [
      "Pacific Coast Hindustan Association",
      "Indian National Congress",
      "Indian Revolutionary League",
      "All India Muslim League",
    ],
    answer: "Pacific Coast Hindustan Association",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What was the name of the newspaper published by the Hindustan Ghadar Party?",
    options: [
      "Ghadar (Urdu)",
      "Punjab Kesari",
      "The Hindustan Times",
      "Kesari",
    ],
    answer: "Ghadar (Urdu)",
  },
  {
    question: "Where was the headquarters of the Hindustan Ghadar Party?",
    options: [
      "Yuhantar Ashram",
      "Gurudwara Rakab Ganj",
      "Central Sikh League Office",
      "Nanak Shah Fakir Shrine",
    ],
    answer: "Yuhantar Ashram",
  },
  {
    question: "When did the Hindustan Ghadar Party dissolve?",
    options: ["1948", "1952", "1935", "1942"],
    answer: "1948",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What was the name of the committee formed in 1919 to look into events that occurred after the Jallianwala Bagh massacre?",
    options: [
      "Hunter Committee",
      "Hunter Commission",
      "Minto-Morley Commission",
      "Shimla Deputation",
    ],
    answer: "Hunter Committee",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who headed the Congress committee formed in 1919 to investigate the events of the Jallianwala Bagh massacre?",
    options: [
      "Madan Mohan Malviya",
      "Jawaharlal Nehru",
      "Subhas Chandra Bose",
      "Sardar Vallabhbhai Patel",
    ],
    answer: "Madan Mohan Malviya",
  },
  {
    question: "When was the Naujawan Bharat Sabha formed by Bhagat Singh?",
    options: ["1926", "1930", "1928", "1920"],
    answer: "1926",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Where was the Hindustan Socialist Republican Association (HSRA) formed by Bhagat Singh and other members?",
    options: [
      "Firoz Shah Kotla Ground, Delhi",
      "Jallianwala Bagh, Amritsar",
      "Lahore, Punjab",
      "Chandigarh",
    ],
    answer: "Firoz Shah Kotla Ground, Delhi",
  },
  {
    question: "Who commanded Operation Bluestar?",
    options: [
      "Major General Kuldeep Singh Brar",
      "General Reginald Dyer",
      "General Zorawar Singh",
      "Major General Bhagat Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Major General Kuldeep Singh Brar",
  },
  {
    question: "Who assassinated Michael O'Dwyer?",
    options: [
      "Sardar Udham Singh",
      "Bhagat Singh",
      "Lala Hardyal",
      "Ram Prasad Bismil",
    ],
    answer: "Sardar Udham Singh",
  },
  {
    question: "What was the other name of Sardar Udham Singh?",
    options: [
      "Ram Mohammad Singh Azad",
      "Sher Singh Azad",
      "Bikram Singh",
      "Singh Dilwar",
    ],
    answer: "Ram Mohammad Singh Azad",
  },
  {
    question: "When and where did Sardar Udham Singh shoot Michael O'Dwyer?",
    options: [
      "13 March 1940, Caxton Hall, London",
      "31 July 1940, Pentonville Prison, London",
      "1 November 1940, Lahore",
      "10 March 1940, Amritsar",
    ],
    answer: "13 March 1940, Caxton Hall, London",
  },
  {
    question: "What was the name of the Singh Sabha changed to in 1883?",
    options: [
      "Khalsa Diwan",
      "Nanak Sabha",
      "Sikh Darbar",
      "Singh Sabha Federation",
    ],
    answer: "Khalsa Diwan",
  },
  {
    question: "Who founded the Nirankari movement?",
    options: [
      "Baba Dyal Das",
      "Baba Ram Singh",
      "Baba Harbhajan Singh",
      "Baba Dhan Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Baba Dyal Das",
  },
  {
    question:
      "When and where did Baba Dyal start the movement in North-West Punjab?",
    options: [
      "1851, North-West Punjab",
      "1870, Amritsar",
      "1860, Lahore",
      "1895, Patiala",
    ],
    answer: "1851, North-West Punjab",
  },
  {
    question: "What is the key difference between Namdharis and other Sikhs?",
    options: [
      "Namdharis have only the five marks of Sikhism without the Kirpan",
      "Namdharis use a different type of turban",
      "Namdharis do not wear the five Ks",
      "Namdharis only use the Guru Granth Sahib",
    ],
    answer: "Namdharis have only the five marks of Sikhism without the Kirpan",
  },
  {
    question: "When was the Namdhari Kuka movement formed?",
    options: ["April 1812", "January 1810", "March 1820", "July 1850"],
    answer: "April 1812",
  },
  {
    question: "Who was the founder of the Namdhari Kuka movement?",
    options: [
      "Guru Balak Singh",
      "Guru Gobind Singh Ji",
      "Baba Ram Singh",
      "Baba Sohan Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Guru Balak Singh",
  },
  {
    question: "Where was the Namdhari Kuka movement founded?",
    options: [
      "Bank of the Haron River, Hazro, Punjab",
      "Gurdwara Harmandir Sahib, Amritsar",
      "Gurdwara Bangla Sahib, Delhi",
      "Gurdwara Patna Sahib, Patna",
    ],
    answer: "Bank of the Haron River, Hazro, Punjab",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Where is the headquarters of the Namdhari Kuka movement located?",
    options: [
      "Bhaini Sahib, Ludhiana",
      "Amritsar, Punjab",
      "Patiala, Punjab",
      "Chandigarh",
    ],
    answer: "Bhaini Sahib, Ludhiana",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the current Guru of the Namdhari Kuka movement?",
    options: [
      "Guru Uday Singh",
      "Guru Har Rai Singh",
      "Guru Balak Singh",
      "Guru Ram Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Guru Uday Singh",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following is a publication associated with the Namdhari Kuka movement?",
    options: [
      "Nwan Hindustan, Satyug, Sacha Marg",
      "Kesari, Harbinger",
      "Punjab Kesari, Navjeevan",
      "Ghadar, Kaurav",
    ],
    answer: "Nwan Hindustan, Satyug, Sacha Marg",
  },
  {
    question: "When was the Sri Guru Singh Sabha Amritsar formed?",
    options: ["1873", "1880", "1900", "1855"],
    answer: "1873",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Where did the first meeting of Sri Guru Singh Sabha Amritsar take place?",
    options: [
      "Akal Takht, Amritsar",
      "Golden Temple, Amritsar",
      "Nankana Sahib, Lahore",
      "Gurdwara Baba Atal, Amritsar",
    ],
    answer: "Akal Takht, Amritsar",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who was the chairman of the first meeting of Sri Guru Singh Sabha Amritsar?",
    options: [
      "Thakur Singh Sandhwalia",
      "Gian Singh",
      "Bhai Kahn Singh Nabha",
      "Bhai Vir Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Thakur Singh Sandhwalia",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who was the secretary of the first meeting of Sri Guru Singh Sabha Amritsar?",
    options: [
      "Gian Singh",
      "Bhai Puran Singh",
      "Bhai Harbans Singh",
      "Bhai Kesar Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Gian Singh",
  },
  {
    question:
      "On which date was Indira Gandhi shot by her two Sikh security guards?",
    options: [
      "31 October 1984",
      "1 November 1984",
      "15 August 1984",
      "20 October 1984",
    ],
    answer: "31 October 1984",
  },
  {
    question: "Who founded the Namdhari movement?",
    options: [
      "Ram Singh",
      "Guru Balak Singh",
      "Baba Sohan Singh",
      "Baba Dyal Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Ram Singh",
  },
  {
    question: "When was the Namdhari movement founded?",
    options: ["1857", "1860", "1870", "1880"],
    answer: "1857",
  },
  {
    question: "Where was the Namdhari movement founded?",
    options: ["Bhaini Sahib", "Amritsar", "Ludhiana", "Patiala"],
    answer: "Bhaini Sahib",
  },
  {
    question: "Which movement was the first to start the Swadeshi Movement?",
    options: [
      "Namdhari Movement",
      "Ghadar Movement",
      "Indian National Congress",
      "Arya Samaj",
    ],
    answer: "Namdhari Movement",
  },
  {
    question: "The Komagata Maru was rented by which individual?",
    options: [
      "Gurdit Singh",
      "Baba Sohan Singh",
      "Lala Lajpat Rai",
      "Sardar Udham Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Gurdit Singh",
  },
  {
    question: "From where did the Komagata Maru sail to Vancouver, Canada?",
    options: ["British Hong Kong", "Singapore", "Shanghai", "Calcutta"],
    answer: "British Hong Kong",
  },
  {
    question:
      "When did the Komagata Maru reach Calcutta after its return to India?",
    options: [
      "29 September 1914",
      "1 October 1914",
      "25 September 1914",
      "15 October 1914",
    ],
    answer: "29 September 1914",
  },
  {
    question: "When did Guru Gobind Singh fight his first battle at Bhangani?",
    options: ["1688", "1699", "1675", "1704"],
    answer: "1688",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Against whom did Guru Gobind Singh fight his first battle at Bhangani?",
    options: [
      "Raja Bheem Chand",
      "Raja Shamsher Singh",
      "Raja Surjit Singh",
      "Raja Dal Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Raja Bheem Chand",
  },
  {
    question: "When was the Khalsa Panth established?",
    options: ["1699", "1688", "1704", "1675"],
    answer: "1699",
  },
  {
    question: "Who founded the Ghadar Party in 1913?",
    options: [
      "Lala Hardayal & Sohan Singh Bhakna",
      "Bhagat Singh & Chandra Shekhar Azad",
      "Lala Lajpat Rai & Bal Gangadhar Tilak",
      "Mahatma Gandhi & Jawaharlal Nehru",
    ],
    answer: "Lala Hardayal & Sohan Singh Bhakna",
  },
  {
    question: "In which year did the East India Company annex Punjab?",
    options: ["1849", "1857", "1818", "1850"],
    answer: "1849",
  },
  {
    question: "Where did Guru Nanak Dev Ji found Kartarpur?",
    options: ["Kartarpur", "Amritsar", "Patiala", "Nankana Sahib"],
    answer: "Kartarpur",
  },
  {
    question: "Which place was founded by Guru Arjan Dev Ji?",
    options: [
      "Tarn Taran, Kartarpur (Jalandhar), Hargobindpura",
      "Amritsar, Goindwal, Kiratpur",
      "Anandpur Sahib, Khadur Sahib",
      "Goindwal, Hargobindpura, Ponta Sahib",
    ],
    answer: "Tarn Taran, Kartarpur (Jalandhar), Hargobindpura",
  },
  {
    question: "Where did Guru Amar Das Ji found Goindwal?",
    options: ["Goindwal", "Amritsar", "Anandpur Sahib", "Khadur Sahib"],
    answer: "Goindwal",
  },
  {
    question: "Where did Guru Gobind Singh Ji found Ponta Sahib?",
    options: ["Ponta Sahib", "Kiratpur Sahib", "Amritsar", "Anandpur Sahib"],
    answer: "Ponta Sahib",
  },
  {
    question: "Where did Guru Angad Dev Ji found Khadur Sahib?",
    options: ["Khadur Sahib", "Goindwal", "Amritsar", "Tarn Taran"],
    answer: "Khadur Sahib",
  },
  {
    question: "Where did Guru Ram Das Ji found Amritsar?",
    options: [
      "Amritsar (Guru ka Chakk, Ramdaspur)",
      "Goindwal",
      "Tarn Taran",
      "Kiratpur",
    ],
    answer: "Amritsar (Guru ka Chakk, Ramdaspur)",
  },
  {
    question: "Where did Guru Hargobind Ji found Kiratpur?",
    options: ["Kiratpur", "Ponta Sahib", "Amritsar", "Goindwal"],
    answer: "Kiratpur",
  },
  {
    question: "Which place was founded by Guru Tegh Bahadur Ji?",
    options: [
      "Chakk Nanki (Anandpur Sahib)",
      "Kiratpur",
      "Goindwal",
      "Amritsar",
    ],
    answer: "Chakk Nanki (Anandpur Sahib)",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following territories was conquered by Maharaja Ranjit Singh?",
    options: [
      "Kasur, Kangra, Kashmir, Peshawar",
      "Amritsar, Lahore, Peshawar, Kashmir",
      "Delhi, Lahore, Amritsar, Kangra",
      "Delhi, Kashmir, Kasur, Lahore",
    ],
    answer: "Kasur, Kangra, Kashmir, Peshawar",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who was the ruler of Kasur when Maharaja Ranjit Singh conquered it?",
    options: [
      "Qutub-ud-Din",
      "Azim Khan",
      "Raja Sansar Chand Katoch",
      "Zaffar Khan",
    ],
    answer: "Qutub-ud-Din",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who was the ruler of Kangra when it was conquered by Maharaja Ranjit Singh?",
    options: [
      "Raja Sansar Chand Katoch",
      "Zaffar Khan",
      "Qutub-ud-Din",
      "Azim Khan",
    ],
    answer: "Raja Sansar Chand Katoch",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who was the ruler of Kashmir when Maharaja Ranjit Singh conquered it?",
    options: [
      "Zaffar Khan",
      "Azim Khan",
      "Raja Sansar Chand Katoch",
      "Qutub-ud-Din",
    ],
    answer: "Zaffar Khan",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who was the ruler of Peshawar when it was conquered by Maharaja Ranjit Singh?",
    options: [
      "Azim Khan",
      "Raja Sansar Chand Katoch",
      "Zaffar Khan",
      "Qutub-ud-Din",
    ],
    answer: "Azim Khan",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who founded the non-profit organization 'Servants of the People Society'?",
    options: [
      "Lala Lajpat Rai",
      "Bhagat Singh",
      "Mahatma Gandhi",
      "Jawaharlal Nehru",
    ],
    answer: "Lala Lajpat Rai",
  },
  {
    question: "Who constructed the Sheesh Mahal in Patiala?",
    options: [
      "Maharaja Narinder Singh",
      "Maharaja Ranjit Singh",
      "Maharaja Bhupinder Singh",
      "Maharaja Kesar Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Maharaja Narinder Singh",
  },
  {
    question: "Which ruler helped the Britishers during the 1857 revolt?",
    options: [
      "Maharaja Narinder Singh",
      "Maharaja Ranjit Singh",
      "Maharaja Bhupinder Singh",
      "Maharaja Kesar Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Maharaja Narinder Singh",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who was present at the ceremony of Maharaja Narinder Singh in Patiala?",
    options: [
      "Lord Canning",
      "Lord Mountbatten",
      "Lord Dalhousie",
      "Lord Curzon",
    ],
    answer: "Lord Canning",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which two structures were formed by Maharaja Narinder Singh in Patiala?",
    options: [
      "Sheesh Mahal and Ajaib Ghar",
      "Moti Bagh Palace and Sheesh Mahal",
      "Maharaja Palace and Ajaib Ghar",
      "Ajaib Ghar and Panta Sahib",
    ],
    answer: "Sheesh Mahal and Ajaib Ghar",
  },
  {
    question: "Who built the Moti Bagh Palace in Patiala?",
    options: [
      "Maharaja Narinder Singh",
      "Maharaja Bhupinder Singh",
      "Maharaja Ranjit Singh",
      "Maharaja Kesar Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Maharaja Narinder Singh",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is located at the Moti Bagh Palace after India's independence?",
    options: [
      "Netaji Subhash National Institute of Sports",
      "Punjab Vidhan Sabha",
      "Punjab University",
      "Indian National Army Museum",
    ],
    answer: "Netaji Subhash National Institute of Sports",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who was sent to negotiate with Bhindranwale during Operation Blue Star?",
    options: [
      "Gurcharan Singh Tohra",
      "Jarnail Singh Bhindranwale",
      "Indira Gandhi",
      "Jagjit Singh Chauhan",
    ],
    answer: "Gurcharan Singh Tohra",
  },
  {
    question:
      "In which year was Guru Ke Mahal established by Guru Ramdas in Amritsar?",
    options: ["1573", "1600", "1640", "1582"],
    answer: "1573",
  },
  {
    question: "Who founded the Radha Soami movement?",
    options: [
      "Shiv Dayal",
      "Jaimal Singh",
      "Sardar Bahadur Maharaja Jagat Singh",
      "Maharaja Charan Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Shiv Dayal",
  },
  {
    question: "On which day was the Radha Soami movement founded?",
    options: [
      "Basant Panchami",
      "Diwali",
      "Guru Nanak Jayanti",
      "Makar Sankranti",
    ],
    answer: "Basant Panchami",
  },
  {
    question: "In which year was the Radha Soami movement founded?",
    options: ["1861", "1880", "1891", "1900"],
    answer: "1861",
  },
  {
    question: "Where was the Radha Soami movement founded?",
    options: ["Agra", "Amritsar", "Delhi", "Lahore"],
    answer: "Agra",
  },
  {
    question: "Who founded the RSS Beas lineage of the Radha Soami movement?",
    options: [
      "Jaimal Singh",
      "Shiv Dayal",
      "Maharaja Charan Singh",
      "Gurinder Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Jaimal Singh",
  },
  {
    question: "Who was the second leader of the RSS Beas lineage?",
    options: [
      "Swan Singh",
      "Maharaja Charan Singh",
      "Sardar Bahadur Maharaja Jagat Singh",
      "Gurinder Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Swan Singh",
  },
  {
    question: "Who was the third leader of the RSS Beas lineage?",
    options: [
      "Sardar Bahadur Maharaja Jagat Singh",
      "Maharaja Charan Singh",
      "Swan Singh",
      "Jaimal Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Sardar Bahadur Maharaja Jagat Singh",
  },
  {
    question: "Who was the fourth leader of the RSS Beas lineage?",
    options: [
      "Maharaja Charan Singh",
      "Gurinder Singh",
      "Sardar Bahadur Maharaja Jagat Singh",
      "Swan Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Maharaja Charan Singh",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the current leader of the RSS Beas lineage?",
    options: [
      "Gurinder Singh",
      "Maharaja Charan Singh",
      "Sardar Bahadur Maharaja Jagat Singh",
      "Swan Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Gurinder Singh",
  },
  {
    question: "Who was associated with the Ghadar Movement and Kisan Sabha?",
    options: [
      "Sohan Singh Bhakna",
      "Lala Hardayal",
      "Baba Deep Singh",
      "Ajit Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Sohan Singh Bhakna",
  },
  {
    question:
      "In which year was the Ghadar Party's Hindustan Association of Pacific Coast formed?",
    options: ["1913", "1920", "1900", "1915"],
    answer: "1913",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who was the first president of the Hindustan Association of Pacific Coast (Ghadar Party)?",
    options: [
      "Sohan Singh Bhakna",
      "Lala Hardayal",
      "Sardar Ajit Singh",
      "Rash Behari Bose",
    ],
    answer: "Sohan Singh Bhakna",
  },
  {
    question: "Where was the first Punjabi printing press established?",
    options: ["Ludhiana", "Amritsar", "Delhi", "Jalandhar"],
    answer: "Ludhiana",
  },
  {
    question: "Who built the Akal Takht?",
    options: [
      "Guru Hargobind",
      "Guru Nanak Dev",
      "Guru Gobind Singh",
      "Guru Arjan Dev",
    ],
    answer: "Guru Hargobind",
  },
  {
    question: "What is the original name of Akal Takht?",
    options: ["Akal Bunga", "Akal Mahal", "Akal Gurdwara", "Takht Sahib"],
    answer: "Akal Bunga",
  },
  {
    question: "Where is Akal Takht located?",
    options: [
      "Darbar Sahib (Golden Temple), Amritsar",
      "Kesgarh Sahib, Anandpur Sahib",
      "Hazur Sahib, Nanded",
      "Damdama Sahib, Talwandi Sabo",
    ],
    answer: "Darbar Sahib (Golden Temple), Amritsar",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following is NOT one of the 5 Takhts established by Sikh Gurus?",
    options: ["Patna Sahib", "Kesgarh Sahib", "Hazur Sahib", "Durgiana Sahib"],
    answer: "Durgiana Sahib",
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following Takhts is located in Bihar?",
    options: ["Patna Sahib", "Kesgarh Sahib", "Hazur Sahib", "Damdama Sahib"],
    answer: "Patna Sahib",
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following Takhts is located in Maharashtra?",
    options: ["Hazur Sahib", "Kesgarh Sahib", "Damdama Sahib", "Patna Sahib"],
    answer: "Hazur Sahib",
  },
  {
    question: "What was the ancient name of Bathinda?",
    options: ["Vikramgarh", "Tabar-i-Hind", "Bhatinda", "Kaniskhapur"],
    answer: "Vikramgarh",
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following thermal plants are located in Bathinda?",
    options: [
      "Guru Nanak Dev Thermal Plant, Guru Hargobind Thermal Plant",
      "Guru Gobind Singh Thermal Plant, Guru Nanak Singh Thermal Plant",
      "Guru Arjan Dev Thermal Plant, Guru Teg Bahadur Thermal Plant",
      "None of the above",
    ],
    answer: "Guru Nanak Dev Thermal Plant, Guru Hargobind Thermal Plant",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which fort in Bathinda is believed to have been built by Raja Dhab and Samrat Kanishka?",
    options: [
      "Qila Mubarak Fort",
      "Qila Andheri Fort",
      "Qila Patiala Fort",
      "Qila Guru Nanak Fort",
    ],
    answer: "Qila Mubarak Fort",
  },
  {
    question:
      "In which year was Bathinda conquered by Maharaja Ala Singh, the Maharaja of Patiala?",
    options: ["1754", "1600", "1800", "1500"],
    answer: "1754",
  },
  {
    question: "What was the name given to Punjab by the Greeks?",
    options: ["Pantapotamia", "Punjabistan", "Saptapathak", "Sapta Sindhu"],
    answer: "Pantapotamia",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following was the ancient name of Punjab according to the Rigveda?",
    options: ["Sapta Sindhu", "Panchananda", "Trigarta", "Tak Desh"],
    answer: "Sapta Sindhu",
  },
  {
    question: "What name was given to Punjab in the Mahabharat?",
    options: [
      "Panchananda, Tak Desh, Trigarta",
      "Sapta Sindhu, Punjab, Bharta",
      "Tak Desh, Gandhara, Kamboja",
      "Kuru Desh, Aryavarta, Punjab",
    ],
    answer: "Panchananda, Tak Desh, Trigarta",
  },
  {
    question: "What was the Persian name for Punjab?",
    options: ["Punjab", "Indus Valley", "Shindh", "Sapt Sindhu"],
    answer: "Punjab",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who started the Manji Partha to spread the message of Guru Nanak Dev Ji?",
    options: [
      "Guru Amar Das Ji",
      "Guru Angad Dev Ji",
      "Guru Nanak Dev Ji",
      "Guru Gobind Singh Ji",
    ],
    answer: "Guru Amar Das Ji",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following practices were introduced by Guru Nanak Dev Ji?",
    options: ["Langar Pratha", "Daswand", "Mall Akhara", "Masand Pratha"],
    answer: "Langar Pratha",
  },
  {
    question: "Who introduced the Mall Akhara practice?",
    options: [
      "Guru Angad Dev Ji",
      "Guru Nanak Dev Ji",
      "Guru Ram Das Ji",
      "Guru Gobind Singh Ji",
    ],
    answer: "Guru Angad Dev Ji",
  },
  {
    question: "Who introduced the Masand Pratha?",
    options: [
      "Guru Ram Das Ji",
      "Guru Arjan Dev Ji",
      "Guru Gobind Singh Ji",
      "Guru Amar Das Ji",
    ],
    answer: "Guru Ram Das Ji",
  },
  {
    question: "Who ended the Masand Pratha?",
    options: [
      "Guru Gobind Singh Ji",
      "Guru Ram Das Ji",
      "Guru Arjan Dev Ji",
      "Guru Amar Das Ji",
    ],
    answer: "Guru Gobind Singh Ji",
  },
  {
    question: "Who composed the Lavan?",
    options: [
      "Guru Ram Das Ji",
      "Guru Arjan Dev Ji",
      "Guru Nanak Dev Ji",
      "Guru Gobind Singh Ji",
    ],
    answer: "Guru Ram Das Ji",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who completed the construction of the Sarowars Santokhsar and Ramsar?",
    options: [
      "Guru Arjan Dev Ji",
      "Guru Amar Das Ji",
      "Guru Gobind Singh Ji",
      "Guru Hargobind Ji",
    ],
    answer: "Guru Arjan Dev Ji",
  },
  {
    question: "Who composed the Pothi Sahib?",
    options: [
      "Guru Arjan Dev Ji",
      "Guru Ram Das Ji",
      "Guru Gobind Singh Ji",
      "Guru Amar Das Ji",
    ],
    answer: "Guru Arjan Dev Ji",
  },
  {
    question: "Where was the first Parkash of the Adi Granth performed?",
    options: [
      "Harmandir Sahib, Amritsar",
      "Takht Sri Patna Sahib",
      "Sri Hazur Sahib, Nanded",
      "Sri Anandpur Sahib",
    ],
    answer: "Harmandir Sahib, Amritsar",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who renamed Ruhela village as Hargobindpur after its reconstruction?",
    options: [
      "Guru Arjan Dev Ji",
      "Guru Hargobind Ji",
      "Guru Gobind Singh Ji",
      "Guru Nanak Dev Ji",
    ],
    answer: "Guru Arjan Dev Ji",
  },
  {
    question: "Who built the Lohgarh Fort at Amritsar?",
    options: [
      "Guru Hargobind Ji",
      "Guru Arjan Dev Ji",
      "Guru Gobind Singh Ji",
      "Guru Amar Das Ji",
    ],
    answer: "Guru Hargobind Ji",
  },
  {
    question: "What was the original name of Guru Angad Dev Ji?",
    options: ["Bhai Lehna", "Bhai Nand Lal", "Bhai Gurditta", "Bhai Buddha"],
    answer: "Bhai Lehna",
  },
  {
    question: "Who introduced the Gurmukhi script?",
    options: [
      "Guru Angad Dev Ji",
      "Guru Nanak Dev Ji",
      "Guru Gobind Singh Ji",
      "Guru Amar Das Ji",
    ],
    answer: "Guru Angad Dev Ji",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who sought blessings from Guru Har Rai, the oldest son of Shah Jahan?",
    options: ["Dara Shikoh", "Aurangzeb", "Shah Jahan", "Jahangir"],
    answer: "Dara Shikoh",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which place, founded by Guru Teg Bahadur, later became famous as Anandpur Sahib?",
    options: ["Chakk Nanki", "Patna Sahib", "Amritsar", "Kiratpur Sahib"],
    answer: "Chakk Nanki",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The Battle of Nadaun (1690) was fought between the hill rajas and which of the following commanders?",
    options: ["Alif Khan", "Azim Khan", "Nadir Shah", "Sultan Mahmud"],
    answer: "Alif Khan",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Kalmot was captured by the Sikhs after defeating Raja Bhim Chand in which battle?",
    options: [
      "Battle of Basoli",
      "Battle of Bhangani",
      "Battle of Plassey",
      "Battle of Amritsar",
    ],
    answer: "Battle of Basoli",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Guru ki Kashi is another name for which of the following places?",
    options: [
      "Damdama Sahib (Talwandi Sabo)",
      "Kiratpur Sahib",
      "Patna Sahib",
      "Harmandir Sahib",
    ],
    answer: "Damdama Sahib (Talwandi Sabo)",
  },
  {
    question: "The Dasam Granth was written by which Guru at Damdama Sahib?",
    options: [
      "Guru Gobind Singh Ji",
      "Guru Arjan Dev Ji",
      "Guru Tegh Bahadur Ji",
      "Guru Ram Das Ji",
    ],
    answer: "Guru Gobind Singh Ji",
  },
  {
    question: "Who compiled the Guru Granth Sahib?",
    options: [
      "Guru Gobind Singh Ji",
      "Guru Arjan Dev Ji",
      "Guru Nanak Dev Ji",
      "Guru Amar Das Ji",
    ],
    answer: "Guru Gobind Singh Ji",
  },
  {
    question: "How many pages are in the Guru Granth Sahib?",
    options: ["1430", "1500", "1200", "1600"],
    answer: "1430",
  },
  {
    question:
      "How many hymns of Guru Nanak are there in the Guru Granth Sahib?",
    options: ["974", "1000", "800", "1100"],
    answer: "974",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following Bhagats' hymns are included in the Guru Granth Sahib?",
    options: [
      "Kabir and Farid",
      "Nanak and Gobind",
      "Arjan and Hargobind",
      "Sikh and Bhatt",
    ],
    answer: "Kabir and Farid",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who wrote the hymns in the Guru Granth Sahib from the Guru's bani?",
    options: [
      "Guru Nanak Dev Ji",
      "Guru Arjan Dev Ji",
      "Guru Gobind Singh Ji",
      "Guru Amar Das Ji",
    ],
    answer: "Guru Nanak Dev Ji",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The hymns of Guru Arjan in the Guru Granth Sahib number how many?",
    options: ["2218", "1200", "1500", "900"],
    answer: "2218",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following is the correct total count of hymns of Guru Tegh Bahadur in the Guru Granth Sahib?",
    options: ["116", "200", "50", "300"],
    answer: "116",
  },
  {
    question: "Which is the oldest Takht in Sikhism?",
    options: ["Akal Takht", "Kesgarh Sahib", "Hazur Sahib", "Patna Sahib"],
    answer: "Akal Takht",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Takht Sri Kesgarh Sahib is known for the creation of Khalsa by baptizing whom?",
    options: [
      "Panj Pyaras",
      "Guru Gobind Singh Ji",
      "Baba Banda Singh Bahadur",
      "Guru Nanak Dev Ji",
    ],
    answer: "Panj Pyaras",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who was Bhai Daya Ram, one of the Panj Pyaras who were baptized at Sri Kesgarh Sahib?",
    options: [
      "Khatri from Lahore",
      "Barber from Bidar",
      "Mashki from Jagannath, Orissa",
      "Painter from Dwarka, Gujarat",
    ],
    answer: "Khatri from Lahore",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following was Bhai Dharam Das, one of the Panj Pyaras, by profession?",
    options: [
      "Jaat from Delhi",
      "Barber from Bidar",
      "Mashki from Jagannath, Orissa",
      "Painter from Dwarka, Gujarat",
    ],
    answer: "Jaat from Delhi",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Bhai Himmat Rai, one of the Panj Pyaras, was a mashki from which place?",
    options: [
      "Jagannath, Orissa",
      "Lahore",
      "Dwarka, Gujarat",
      "Bidar, Karnataka",
    ],
    answer: "Jagannath, Orissa",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Bhai Mohkam Chand, one of the Panj Pyaras, was a painter from which place?",
    options: ["Dwarka, Gujarat", "Lahore", "Bidar, Karnataka", "Delhi"],
    answer: "Dwarka, Gujarat",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Bhai Sahib Chand, one of the Panj Pyaras, was a barber from which place?",
    options: [
      "Bidar, Karnataka",
      "Lahore",
      "Jagannath, Orissa",
      "Dwarka, Gujarat",
    ],
    answer: "Bidar, Karnataka",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Hazur Sahib, a significant Sikh shrine, is located on the bank of which river?",
    options: ["Godavari", "Ganga", "Sarasvati", "Indus"],
    answer: "Godavari",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which Takht is regarded as the center for propagating Sikhism in East India?",
    options: [
      "Takht Sri Patna Sahib",
      "Takht Sri Kesgarh Sahib",
      "Takht Sri Hazur Sahib",
      "Takht Sri Damdama Sahib",
    ],
    answer: "Takht Sri Patna Sahib",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who introduced the official seal in the name of Guru Nanak and Guru Gobind Singh?",
    options: [
      "Baba Banda Singh and Maharaja Ranjit Singh",
      "Guru Gobind Singh Ji",
      "Maharaja Ranjit Singh",
      "Guru Arjan Dev Ji",
    ],
    answer: "Baba Banda Singh and Maharaja Ranjit Singh",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who was the Maharaja of the Sikh Empire during the First Anglo-Sikh War?",
    options: [
      "Maharaja Daleep Singh",
      "Maharaja Ranjit Singh",
      "Maharaja Gulab Singh",
      "Maharaja Hari Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Maharaja Daleep Singh",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who was the Governor-General of India during the First Anglo-Sikh War?",
    options: [
      "Lord Harding",
      "Lord Cornwallis",
      "Lord Dalhousie",
      "Lord Wellesley",
    ],
    answer: "Lord Harding",
  },
  {
    question: "Which battle was the first battle of the First Anglo-Sikh War?",
    options: [
      "Battle of Mudki",
      "Battle of Ferozeshah",
      "Battle of Baddowal",
      "Battle of Aliwal",
    ],
    answer: "Battle of Mudki",
  },
  {
    question:
      "When did the Battle of Mudki take place during the First Anglo-Sikh War?",
    options: [
      "18 December 1845",
      "28 January 1846",
      "21 December 1845",
      "10 February 1846",
    ],
    answer: "18 December 1845",
  },
  {
    question: "Who was the Sikh leader in the Battle of Mudki?",
    options: [
      "Laal Singh",
      "Ranjodh Singh Majithia",
      "Teja Singh",
      "Sham Singh Atariwala",
    ],
    answer: "Laal Singh",
  },
  {
    question: "Who was the British commander in the Battle of Mudki?",
    options: ["Hugh Gough", "Henry Smith", "Henry Hardinge", "Sir John Keane"],
    answer: "Hugh Gough",
  },
  {
    question: "Which side won the Battle of Mudki?",
    options: ["British", "Sikh", "Draw", "None of the above"],
    answer: "British",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which battle followed the Battle of Mudki in the First Anglo-Sikh War?",
    options: [
      "Battle of Ferozeshah",
      "Battle of Aliwal",
      "Battle of Sobraon",
      "Battle of Baddowal",
    ],
    answer: "Battle of Ferozeshah",
  },
  {
    question: "When did the Battle of Ferozeshah take place?",
    options: [
      "21 December 1845",
      "28 January 1846",
      "18 December 1845",
      "10 February 1846",
    ],
    answer: "21 December 1845",
  },
  {
    question: "Who were the Sikh leaders in the Battle of Ferozeshah?",
    options: [
      "Laal Singh, Teja Singh",
      "Ranjodh Singh Majithia",
      "Sham Singh Atariwala, Teja Singh",
      "Laal Singh, Ranjodh Singh Majithia",
    ],
    answer: "Laal Singh, Teja Singh",
  },
  {
    question: "Who was the British commander in the Battle of Ferozeshah?",
    options: ["Hugh Gough", "Henry Smith", "Henry Hardinge", "Lord Dalhousie"],
    answer: "Hugh Gough",
  },
  {
    question: "Which side won the Battle of Ferozeshah?",
    options: ["British", "Sikh", "Draw", "None of the above"],
    answer: "British",
  },
  {
    question: "Which battle of the First Anglo-Sikh War was won by the Sikhs?",
    options: [
      "Battle of Baddowal",
      "Battle of Mudki",
      "Battle of Aliwal",
      "Battle of Sobraon",
    ],
    answer: "Battle of Baddowal",
  },
  {
    question: "When did the Battle of Baddowal take place?",
    options: [
      "21 January 1846",
      "18 December 1845",
      "28 January 1846",
      "21 December 1845",
    ],
    answer: "21 January 1846",
  },
  {
    question: "Who was the Sikh leader in the Battle of Baddowal?",
    options: [
      "Ranjodh Singh Majithia",
      "Laal Singh",
      "Teja Singh",
      "Sham Singh Atariwala",
    ],
    answer: "Ranjodh Singh Majithia",
  },
  {
    question: "Who was the British commander in the Battle of Baddowal?",
    options: ["Henry Smith", "Hugh Gough", "Henry Hardinge", "Sir John Keane"],
    answer: "Henry Smith",
  },
  {
    question: "Which side won the Battle of Baddowal?",
    options: ["Sikh", "British", "Draw", "None of the above"],
    answer: "Sikh",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which battle followed the Battle of Baddowal in the First Anglo-Sikh War?",
    options: [
      "Battle of Aliwal",
      "Battle of Sobraon",
      "Battle of Ferozeshah",
      "Battle of Mudki",
    ],
    answer: "Battle of Aliwal",
  },
  {
    question: "When did the Battle of Aliwal take place?",
    options: [
      "28 January 1846",
      "21 December 1845",
      "21 January 1846",
      "18 December 1845",
    ],
    answer: "28 January 1846",
  },
  {
    question: "Who was the Sikh leader in the Battle of Aliwal?",
    options: [
      "Ranjodh Singh Majithia",
      "Laal Singh",
      "Teja Singh",
      "Sham Singh Atariwala",
    ],
    answer: "Ranjodh Singh Majithia",
  },
  {
    question: "Who was the British commander in the Battle of Aliwal?",
    options: ["Henry Smith", "Hugh Gough", "Henry Hardinge", "Lord Dalhousie"],
    answer: "Henry Smith",
  },
  {
    question: "Which side won the Battle of Aliwal?",
    options: ["British", "Sikh", "Draw", "None of the above"],
    answer: "British",
  },
  {
    question: "Which was the final battle of the First Anglo-Sikh War?",
    options: [
      "Battle of Sobraon",
      "Battle of Aliwal",
      "Battle of Ferozeshah",
      "Battle of Baddowal",
    ],
    answer: "Battle of Sobraon",
  },
  {
    question: "When did the Battle of Sobraon take place?",
    options: [
      "10 February 1846",
      "21 December 1845",
      "18 December 1845",
      "28 January 1846",
    ],
    answer: "10 February 1846",
  },
  {
    question: "Who were the Sikh leaders in the Battle of Sobraon?",
    options: [
      "Laal Singh, Teja Singh, Sham Singh Atariwala",
      "Ranjodh Singh Majithia",
      "Sham Singh Atariwala, Laal Singh",
      "Teja Singh, Laal Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Laal Singh, Teja Singh, Sham Singh Atariwala",
  },
  {
    question: "Who were the British commanders in the Battle of Sobraon?",
    options: [
      "Hugh Gough, Henry Hardinge",
      "Henry Smith, Hugh Gough",
      "Henry Hardinge, Lord Dalhousie",
      "Hugh Gough, Sir John Keane",
    ],
    answer: "Hugh Gough, Henry Hardinge",
  },
  {
    question: "Which side won the Battle of Sobraon?",
    options: ["British", "Sikh", "Draw", "None of the above"],
    answer: "British",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who was the Maharaja of the Sikh Empire during the Second Anglo-Sikh War?",
    options: [
      "Maharaja Duleep Singh",
      "Maharaja Ranjit Singh",
      "Maharaja Gulab Singh",
      "Maharaja Hari Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Maharaja Duleep Singh",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who was the Governor-General of India during the Second Anglo-Sikh War?",
    options: [
      "Lord Dalhousie",
      "Lord Harding",
      "Lord Cornwallis",
      "Lord Wellesley",
    ],
    answer: "Lord Dalhousie",
  },
  {
    question: "Which battle was the first battle of the Second Anglo-Sikh War?",
    options: [
      "Battle of Ramnagar",
      "Battle of Multan",
      "Battle of Chillianwala",
      "Battle of Gujrat",
    ],
    answer: "Battle of Ramnagar",
  },
  {
    question:
      "When did the Battle of Ramnagar take place during the Second Anglo-Sikh War?",
    options: [
      "22 November 1848",
      "13 January 1849",
      "22 January 1849",
      "21 February 1849",
    ],
    answer: "22 November 1848",
  },
  {
    question: "Who was the Sikh leader in the Battle of Ramnagar?",
    options: [
      "Sher Singh Attariwala",
      "Chattar Singh",
      "Mulraaj",
      "Teja Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Sher Singh Attariwala",
  },
  {
    question: "Who was the British commander in the Battle of Ramnagar?",
    options: ["Hugh Gough", "Henry Smith", "General Whish", "Henry Hardinge"],
    answer: "Hugh Gough",
  },
  {
    question: "Which side won the Battle of Ramnagar?",
    options: ["Sikh", "British", "Draw", "None of the above"],
    answer: "Sikh",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which battle followed the Battle of Ramnagar in the Second Anglo-Sikh War?",
    options: [
      "Battle of Chillianwala",
      "Battle of Multan",
      "Battle of Gujrat",
      "Battle of Sobraon",
    ],
    answer: "Battle of Chillianwala",
  },
  {
    question: "When did the Battle of Chillianwala take place?",
    options: [
      "13 January 1849",
      "22 November 1848",
      "21 February 1849",
      "22 January 1849",
    ],
    answer: "13 January 1849",
  },
  {
    question: "Who was the Sikh leader in the Battle of Chillianwala?",
    options: [
      "Sher Singh Attariwala",
      "Chattar Singh",
      "Mulraaj",
      "Teja Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Sher Singh Attariwala",
  },
  {
    question: "Who was the British commander in the Battle of Chillianwala?",
    options: [
      "Hugh Gough",
      "General Whish",
      "Henry Hardinge",
      "Lord Dalhousie",
    ],
    answer: "Hugh Gough",
  },
  {
    question: "Which side won the Battle of Chillianwala?",
    options: ["Sikh", "British", "Draw", "None of the above"],
    answer: "Sikh",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which battle followed the Battle of Chillianwala in the Second Anglo-Sikh War?",
    options: [
      "Battle of Multan",
      "Battle of Ramnagar",
      "Battle of Gujrat",
      "Battle of Sobraon",
    ],
    answer: "Battle of Multan",
  },
  {
    question: "When did the Battle of Multan take place?",
    options: [
      "22 January 1849",
      "13 January 1849",
      "22 November 1848",
      "21 February 1849",
    ],
    answer: "22 January 1849",
  },
  {
    question: "Who was the Sikh leader in the Battle of Multan?",
    options: [
      "Mulraaj",
      "Sher Singh Attariwala",
      "Chattar Singh",
      "Ranjodh Singh Majithia",
    ],
    answer: "Mulraaj",
  },
  {
    question: "Who was the British commander in the Battle of Multan?",
    options: [
      "General Whish",
      "Hugh Gough",
      "Henry Hardinge",
      "Lord Dalhousie",
    ],
    answer: "General Whish",
  },
  {
    question: "Which side won the Battle of Multan?",
    options: ["British", "Sikh", "Draw", "None of the above"],
    answer: "British",
  },
  {
    question: "Which was the final battle of the Second Anglo-Sikh War?",
    options: [
      "Battle of Gujrat",
      "Battle of Multan",
      "Battle of Chillianwala",
      "Battle of Ramnagar",
    ],
    answer: "Battle of Gujrat",
  },
  {
    question: "When did the Battle of Gujrat take place?",
    options: [
      "21 February 1849",
      "22 January 1849",
      "13 January 1849",
      "22 November 1848",
    ],
    answer: "21 February 1849",
  },
  {
    question: "Who were the Sikh leaders in the Battle of Gujrat?",
    options: [
      "Sher Singh Attariwala, Chattar Singh",
      "Sher Singh Attariwala",
      "Mulraaj, Chattar Singh",
      "Ranjodh Singh Majithia",
    ],
    answer: "Sher Singh Attariwala, Chattar Singh",
  },
  {
    question: "Who was the British commander in the Battle of Gujrat?",
    options: [
      "Hugh Gough",
      "General Whish",
      "Henry Hardinge",
      "Lord Dalhousie",
    ],
    answer: "Hugh Gough",
  },
  {
    question: "Which side won the Battle of Gujrat?",
    options: ["British", "Sikh", "Draw", "None of the above"],
    answer: "British",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What event does the Kup Rohira Memorial near Malerkotla commemorate?",
    options: [
      "Vadda Ghallughara",
      "Chhota Ghallughara",
      "Battle of Sobraon",
      "Anglo-Sikh War",
    ],
    answer: "Vadda Ghallughara",
  },
  {
    question:
      "When did the Vadda Ghallughara occur, which is commemorated by the Kup Rohira Memorial?",
    options: [
      "5 February 1762",
      "13 January 1849",
      "22 November 1848",
      "21 February 1849",
    ],
    answer: "5 February 1762",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who was the leader behind the Vadda Ghallughara, commemorated at the Kup Rohira Memorial?",
    options: [
      "Ahmad Shah Abdali",
      "Maharaja Ranjit Singh",
      "Lord Dalhousie",
      "Sher Singh Attariwala",
    ],
    answer: "Ahmad Shah Abdali",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The Treaty of Amritsar, signed in 1809, was between Maharaja Ranjit Singh and the British. Who was the British representative at the signing?",
    options: ["Charles Metcalfe", "Lord Hardinge", "Henry Smith", "Hugh Gough"],
    answer: "Charles Metcalfe",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following was the outcome of the Treaty of Amritsar signed in 1809?",
    options: [
      "Sutlej to be the border",
      "Kashmir ceded to the British",
      "Sikh Empire and British East India Company as allies",
      "Jammu and Kashmir to be a part of the British Empire",
    ],
    answer: "Sutlej to be the border",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who was the British Governor-General during the signing of the Treaty of Amritsar in 1809?",
    options: [
      "Lord Minto I",
      "Lord Dalhousie",
      "Lord Hardinge",
      "Lord Wellesley",
    ],
    answer: "Lord Minto I",
  },
  {
    question:
      "When was the second Treaty of Amritsar signed between the British East India Company and Raja Gulab Singh?",
    options: [
      "16 March 1846",
      "22 January 1849",
      "5 February 1762",
      "21 February 1849",
    ],
    answer: "16 March 1846",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who was the British Governor-General during the signing of the Treaty of Amritsar in 1846?",
    options: [
      "Lord Hardinge",
      "Lord Minto I",
      "Lord Dalhousie",
      "Lord Cornwallis",
    ],
    answer: "Lord Hardinge",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who represented the British East India Company during the signing of the Treaty of Amritsar in 1846?",
    options: [
      "British East India Company and Raja Gulab Singh",
      "Charles Metcalfe",
      "Hugh Gough",
      "Lord Dalhousie",
    ],
    answer: "British East India Company and Raja Gulab Singh",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Maharaja Ranjit Singh's kingdom was divided into how many provinces?",
    options: ["4", "5", "3", "2"],
    answer: "4",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following were the provinces of Maharaja Ranjit Singh's kingdom?",
    options: [
      "Lahore, Kashmir, Peshawar, Multan",
      "Amritsar, Jammu, Lahore, Kashmir",
      "Peshawar, Multan, Delhi, Patiala",
      "Lahore, Jammu, Peshawar, Ludhiana",
    ],
    answer: "Lahore, Kashmir, Peshawar, Multan",
  },
  {
    question: "Who were the sons of Maharaja Ranjit Singh?",
    options: [
      "Sher Singh, Tara Singh, Nau Nihal Singh, Dalip Singh",
      "Sher Singh, Raj Singh, Bhuri Singh, Gulab Singh",
      "Dalip Singh, Ram Singh, Tara Singh, Harnam Singh",
      "Nau Nihal Singh, Dalip Singh, Kesar Singh, Harnam Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Sher Singh, Tara Singh, Nau Nihal Singh, Dalip Singh",
  },
  {
    question: "Who led the Sikh forces in the Battle of Mudki?",
    options: [
      "Lala Singh",
      "Sher Singh",
      "Ranjodh Singh Majithia",
      "Laal Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Lala Singh",
  },
  {
    question:
      "In which battle did Sikh forces, led by Ranjodh Singh, defeat the British?",
    options: [
      "Battle of Baddowal",
      "Battle of Ferozeshah",
      "Battle of Aliwal",
      "Battle of Mudki",
    ],
    answer: "Battle of Baddowal",
  },
  {
    question: "Who signed the Treaty of Lahore after the First Anglo-Sikh War?",
    options: [
      "Lord Harding and Maharaja Dalip Singh",
      "Lord Dalhousie and Maharaja Ranjit Singh",
      "Lord Hardinge and Raja Gulab Singh",
      "Lord Minto and Maharaja Ranjit Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Lord Harding and Maharaja Dalip Singh",
  },
  {
    question:
      "When was the Treaty of Lahore signed after the First Anglo-Sikh War?",
    options: [
      "9 March 1846",
      "21 February 1849",
      "22 January 1849",
      "16 March 1846",
    ],
    answer: "9 March 1846",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who were the parties involved in the Treaty of Amritsar (16 March 1846)?",
    options: [
      "British East India Company and Raja Gulab Singh",
      "Maharaja Ranjit Singh and British East India Company",
      "Maharaja Dalip Singh and British East India Company",
      "Raja Gulab Singh and Lord Harding",
    ],
    answer: "British East India Company and Raja Gulab Singh",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who was the British Governor-General during the signing of the Treaty of Amritsar (16 March 1846)?",
    options: [
      "Lord Hardinge",
      "Lord Dalhousie",
      "Lord Minto I",
      "Lord Cornwallis",
    ],
    answer: "Lord Hardinge",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who led the British forces in the Battle of Multan against Moolraj?",
    options: ["General Whish", "Hugh Gough", "Henry Smith", "Lord Harding"],
    answer: "General Whish",
  },
  {
    question: "Who was elected as the president of Punjab Ryasti Praja Mandal?",
    options: [
      "Seva Singh Thikriwala",
      "Master Tara Singh",
      "Sardar Bahadur Singh",
      "Baba Kharak Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Seva Singh Thikriwala",
  },
  {
    question: "Which movement was Master Tara Singh associated with?",
    options: [
      "Punjab Suba Movement",
      "Khalistan Movement",
      "Quit India Movement",
      "Farmers' Protest",
    ],
    answer: "Punjab Suba Movement",
  },
  {
    question: "Who founded Phagwara?",
    options: [
      "Shah Jahan",
      "Guru Hargobind Singh Ji",
      "Maharaja Ranjit Singh",
      "Maharaja Dalip Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Shah Jahan",
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following is NOT located in Phagwara?",
    options: [
      "Shri Hanuman Garhi Temple",
      "Lovely Professional University",
      "Gurudwara Chouda Khuh Sahib",
      "Golden Temple",
    ],
    answer: "Golden Temple",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which river is associated with the proto-historic sites at Harappa?",
    options: ["Ravi River", "Indus River", "Ganges River", "Jhelum River"],
    answer: "Ravi River",
  },
  {
    question: "Who first excavated the proto-historic sites at Harappa?",
    options: [
      "Daya Ram Sahni",
      "Rai Bahadur Bawa",
      "Alexander Cunningham",
      "John Marshall",
    ],
    answer: "Daya Ram Sahni",
  },
  {
    question: "Which district is Phagwara part of?",
    options: ["Kapurthala", "Jalandhar", "Hoshiarpur", "Amritsar"],
    answer: "Kapurthala",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following is the biggest city of the Indus Valley Civilization (IVC)?",
    options: ["Rakhigarhi", "Mohenjo-Daro", "Harappa", "Lothal"],
    answer: "Rakhigarhi",
  },
  {
    question:
      "After the Greeks, which of the following groups occupied Punjab?",
    options: ["Shakas", "Kushans", "Parthians", "Mauryas"],
    answer: "Shakas",
  },
  {
    question: "Which ruler introduced gold coins of the Yupa type?",
    options: ["Samudragupta", "Chandragupta Maurya", "Ashoka", "Kanishka"],
    answer: "Samudragupta",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which Chinese traveler visited India during the reign of Harshvardhan?",
    options: ["Hiuen Tsang", "Fa Hien", "I-Tsing", "Xuanzang"],
    answer: "Hiuen Tsang",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which Chinese traveler visited India during the time of Chandragupta?",
    options: ["Fa Hien", "Hiuen Tsang", "I-Tsing", "Xuanzang"],
    answer: "Fa Hien",
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following is NOT located in Sirhind?",
    options: [
      "Sri Guru Granth Sahib World University",
      "Gurdwara Jyoti Sarup",
      "Gurdwara Shahid Ganj",
      "Golden Temple",
    ],
    answer: "Golden Temple",
  },
  {
    question: "Who founded the Slave Dynasty?",
    options: [
      "Qutb-Din-Aibak",
      "Iltutmish",
      "Ala-ud-Din Khilji",
      "Ghiyas-ud-Din Tughlaq",
    ],
    answer: "Qutb-Din-Aibak",
  },
  {
    question: "The Tughlaq Dynasty was founded by which ruler?",
    options: [
      "Ghiyas-ud-Din Tughlaq",
      "Muhammad-bin-Tughlaq",
      "Sikandar Lodi",
      "Ala-ud-Din Khilji",
    ],
    answer: "Ghiyas-ud-Din Tughlaq",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which sequence correctly represents the dynasties that ruled in India?",
    options: [
      "Slaves → Khiljis → Tughlaqs → Sayyids → Lodhis → Mughals",
      "Khiljis → Slaves → Tughlaqs → Lodhis → Sayyids → Mughals",
      "Sayyids → Tughlaqs → Mughals → Slaves → Khiljis → Lodhis",
      "Mughals → Sayyids → Tughlaqs → Khiljis → Slaves → Lodhis",
    ],
    answer: "Slaves → Khiljis → Tughlaqs → Sayyids → Lodhis → Mughals",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who did Timur appoint as the governor of Punjab after annexing it from the Tughlaqs?",
    options: ["Khizr Khan", "Ibrahim Lodi", "Sher Shah Suri", "Qutb-Din-Aibak"],
    answer: "Khizr Khan",
  },
  {
    question: "Which dynasty was founded by Bahlol Lodi?",
    options: [
      "Lodi Dynasty",
      "Sayyid Dynasty",
      "Tughlaq Dynasty",
      "Khilji Dynasty",
    ],
    answer: "Lodi Dynasty",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who was the last ruler of the Lodi Dynasty, who lost to Babur in 1526?",
    options: [
      "Ibrahim Lodi",
      "Bahlol Lodi",
      "Sikandar Lodi",
      "Shams-ud-Din Lodi",
    ],
    answer: "Ibrahim Lodi",
  },
  {
    question: "Where is the tomb (makbara) of Ibrahim Lodi located?",
    options: ["Panipat", "Delhi", "Agra", "Lahore"],
    answer: "Panipat",
  },
  {
    question: "The word 'Sikh' has its origin in which language?",
    options: ["Sanskrit", "Hindi", "Persian", "Punjabi"],
    answer: "Sanskrit",
  },
  {
    question: "Which composition was written by Guru Nanak?",
    options: [
      "Sidh Gosht",
      "Bani of Guru Granth Sahib",
      "Japuji Sahib",
      "Asa Di War",
    ],
    answer: "Sidh Gosht",
  },
  {
    question: "Which compositions are attributed to Guru Nanak?",
    options: [
      "Japuji Sahib, Asa Di War, Onkar, Sidh Gosht, Bara Mah, 974 Shabd",
      "Japuji Sahib, Asa Di War, Guru Granth Sahib, Shabad Hazare",
      "Japuji Sahib, Asa Di War, Rehras Sahib, Sidh Gosht",
      "Japuji Sahib, Asa Di War, Sukhmani Sahib, Shabad Hazare",
    ],
    answer: "Japuji Sahib, Asa Di War, Onkar, Sidh Gosht, Bara Mah, 974 Shabd",
  },
  {
    question: "Where did Guru Nanak Dev Ji gain enlightenment?",
    options: ["Bein River", "Narmada River", "Sarasvati River", "Ganges River"],
    answer: "Bein River",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who is credited with cleaning the Bein River where Guru Nanak gained enlightenment?",
    options: [
      "Balbir Singh Sichewala",
      "Baba Deep Singh",
      "Bhai Gurdas Ji",
      "Bhai Mani Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Balbir Singh Sichewala",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which eco-saint from Punjab is also a Rajya Sabha member from AAP?",
    options: [
      "Balbir Singh Sichewala",
      "Gurcharan Singh Babbar",
      "Baba Ram Singh",
      "Baba Balwant Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Balbir Singh Sichewala",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Where was the Gurdwara Guru Ki Wadali installed to mark the birth of Guru Hargobind?",
    options: ["Amritsar", "Anandpur Sahib", "Patna Sahib", "Kolkata"],
    answer: "Amritsar",
  },
  {
    question: "Who was deported to Mandalay Jail along with Lala Lajpat Rai?",
    options: [
      "Bhai Maharaj Singh",
      "Bhai Ram Singh",
      "Bhai Taru Singh",
      "Bhai Puran Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Bhai Maharaj Singh",
  },
  {
    question: "To which language does Punjabi owe its origin?",
    options: [
      "Indo-Aryan languages",
      "Dravidian languages",
      "Tibeto-Burman languages",
      "Munda languages",
    ],
    answer: "Indo-Aryan languages",
  },
  {
    question: "Who acted as the scribe to write the Adi Granth?",
    options: [
      "Bhai Gurdas Ji",
      "Bhai Mani Singh",
      "Guru Arjan Dev Ji",
      "Guru Gobind Singh Ji",
    ],
    answer: "Bhai Gurdas Ji",
  },
  {
    question:
      "In which year was Guru Granth Sahib accorded the status of Guru?",
    options: ["1708", "1699", "1715", "1650"],
    answer: "1708",
  },
  {
    question: "Who introduced the Masand system in Sikhism?",
    options: [
      "Guru Ram Das Ji",
      "Guru Hargobind Ji",
      "Guru Arjan Dev Ji",
      "Guru Gobind Singh Ji",
    ],
    answer: "Guru Ram Das Ji",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is called the first saint of Punjab?",
    options: ["Sheikh Farid", "Bhai Mardana", "Baba Nanak", "Bhai Gurdas"],
    answer: "Sheikh Farid",
  },
  {
    question: "What was the real name of Sheikh Farid?",
    options: [
      "Fariduddin Ganjshakar",
      "Sheikh Nooruddin",
      "Farid Ali",
      "Sheikh Moinuddin",
    ],
    answer: "Fariduddin Ganjshakar",
  },
  {
    question: "Where was Sheikh Farid born?",
    options: ["Kotewal (Multan)", "Lahore", "Amritsar", "Chandigarh"],
    answer: "Kotewal (Multan)",
  },
  {
    question: "Who was the Guru of Sheikh Farid?",
    options: [
      "Qutbuddin Bakhtiar Kaki",
      "Guru Nanak Dev Ji",
      "Baba Farid",
      "Baba Deep Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Qutbuddin Bakhtiar Kaki",
  },
  {
    question: "Which place is associated with Sheikh Farid Mela?",
    options: ["Faridkot", "Amritsar", "Ludhiana", "Jalandhar"],
    answer: "Faridkot",
  },
  {
    question: "Which battle was led by Ranjodh Singh from the Sikh side?",
    options: [
      "Battle of Baddowal",
      "Battle of Ferozeshah",
      "Battle of Mudki",
      "Battle of Sobraon",
    ],
    answer: "Battle of Baddowal",
  },
  {
    question: "What was the main aim of the Singh Sabha movement?",
    options: [
      "To protect the interests of Sikhs through education and literature",
      "To increase the Sikh population",
      "To promote political power for Sikhs",
      "To establish a Sikh state",
    ],
    answer:
      "To protect the interests of Sikhs through education and literature",
  },
  {
    question: "What was the Namdhari movement also known as?",
    options: [
      "Kuka movement",
      "Singh Sabha movement",
      "Khalsa Raj movement",
      "Sikh Rehat Maryada movement",
    ],
    answer: "Kuka movement",
  },
  {
    question: "Who started the Namdhari movement (Kuka movement)?",
    options: [
      "Baba Ram Singh",
      "Bhai Gurdas",
      "Guru Gobind Singh",
      "Baba Banda Singh Bahadur",
    ],
    answer: "Baba Ram Singh",
  },
  {
    question:
      "On which date was the Namdhari movement (Kuka movement) started?",
    options: [
      "1 April 1857",
      "15 August 1857",
      "26 January 1900",
      "31 March 1900",
    ],
    answer: "1 April 1857",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which battle took place in 1897 between the British Indian Empire and Afghan tribesmen?",
    options: [
      "Battle of Saragarhi",
      "Battle of Plassey",
      "Battle of Waterloo",
      "Battle of Panipat",
    ],
    answer: "Battle of Saragarhi",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which movement began in 1913 and was related to Indian independence?",
    options: [
      "Ghadar movement",
      "Quit India movement",
      "Khilafat movement",
      "Swaraj movement",
    ],
    answer: "Ghadar movement",
  },
  {
    question: "In which year did the Komagata Maru incident occur?",
    options: ["1914", "1905", "1920", "1916"],
    answer: "1914",
  },
  {
    question: "In which year did the Jallianwala Bagh incident occur?",
    options: ["1919", "1915", "1920", "1922"],
    answer: "1919",
  },
  {
    question: "Which towns were attacked by Baba Banda Singh Bahadur?",
    options: [
      "Sonipat, Kaithal, Samana, Bilaspur",
      "Delhi, Amritsar, Firozpur, Jalandhar",
      "Lahore, Peshawar, Multan, Gujranwala",
      "Chandigarh, Ludhiana, Patiala, Bhatinda",
    ],
    answer: "Sonipat, Kaithal, Samana, Bilaspur",
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following events occurred in 1716?",
    options: [
      "Execution of Baba Banda Singh",
      "Execution of Bhai Mani Singh",
      "Chhota Ghallughara",
      "Vadda Ghallughara",
    ],
    answer: "Execution of Baba Banda Singh",
  },
  {
    question: "Who was executed in 1735?",
    options: [
      "Bhai Mani Singh",
      "Baba Banda Singh",
      "Guru Gobind Singh",
      "Guru Tegh Bahadur",
    ],
    answer: "Bhai Mani Singh",
  },
  {
    question: "Which event took place in 1746?",
    options: [
      "Chhota Ghallughara",
      "Execution of Bhai Mani Singh",
      "Vadda Ghallughara",
      "Battle of Plassey",
    ],
    answer: "Chhota Ghallughara",
  },
  {
    question: "When did the Vadda Ghallughara take place?",
    options: ["1762", "1746", "1716", "1735"],
    answer: "1762",
  },
  {
    question: "Lala Lajpat Rai was associated with which newspapers?",
    options: [
      "Vande Mataram and The People",
      "The Tribune and The Hindustan Times",
      "Kesari and Maratha",
      "Indian National Congress Journal and Hind Swaraj",
    ],
    answer: "Vande Mataram and The People",
  },
  {
    question: "Who was the founder of the Namdhari movement?",
    options: [
      "Baba Balak Singh / Baba Ram Singh",
      "Baba Banda Singh Bahadur",
      "Baba Guru Nanak Dev Ji",
      "Baba Deep Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Baba Balak Singh / Baba Ram Singh",
  },
  {
    question: "Who founded the Nirankari movement?",
    options: [
      "Dyal Das",
      "Swami Dayanand Saraswati",
      "Shiv Dayal",
      "Baba Ram Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Dyal Das",
  },
  {
    question: "Who founded the Arya Samaj?",
    options: [
      "Swami Dayanand Saraswati",
      "Dyal Das",
      "Baba Balak Singh",
      "Shiv Dayal",
    ],
    answer: "Swami Dayanand Saraswati",
  },
  {
    question: "Who founded the Radha Soami movement?",
    options: [
      "Shiv Dayal",
      "Baba Balak Singh",
      "Swami Dayanand Saraswati",
      "Dyal Das",
    ],
    answer: "Shiv Dayal",
  },
  {
    question: "What was the objective of the Akali movement?",
    options: [
      "Freeing the Gurudwaras from the control of Mahants",
      "Establishing the Sikh Empire",
      "Fighting against the British colonial rule",
      "Promoting the teachings of Guru Nanak",
    ],
    answer: "Freeing the Gurudwaras from the control of Mahants",
  },
  {
    question: "Why were the Mahants loyal to the British regime?",
    options: [
      "They had administrative ties with the British",
      "They were part of the Akali movement",
      "They were religious leaders of the Sikh community",
      "They were opposed to the Gurudwaras' independence",
    ],
    answer: "They had administrative ties with the British",
  },
  {
    question: "Which general was honored in the Golden Temple?",
    options: [
      "General Dyer",
      "General Montgomery",
      "General Cornwallis",
      "General Gough",
    ],
    answer: "General Dyer",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following were associated with the Peasant movement?",
    options: [
      "Baba Sohan Singh, Baba Rur Singh, Teja Singh Swatantar, Wadhawa Ram",
      "Baba Banda Singh, Teja Singh, Lala Lajpat Rai, Balbir Singh",
      "Sardar Patel, Bhagat Singh, Lala Hardayal, Wadhawa Ram",
      "Guru Gobind Singh Ji, Baba Deep Singh, Baba Tegh Singh, Guru Ram Das",
    ],
    answer:
      "Baba Sohan Singh, Baba Rur Singh, Teja Singh Swatantar, Wadhawa Ram",
  },
  {
    question: "When did the First Anglo-Sikh War start?",
    options: ["1845", "1849", "1857", "1839"],
    answer: "1845",
  },
  {
    question: "What was Baba Banda Singh Bahadur originally?",
    options: ["A Rajput", "A Brahmin", "A Sikh warrior", "A Hindu saint"],
    answer: "A Rajput",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following names is associated with Baba Banda Singh?",
    options: [
      "Lachman Dev, Madho Das Bairagi, Banda Bairagi, Gurbaksh Singh",
      "Guru Nanak Dev, Guru Tegh Bahadur, Guru Arjan, Guru Gobind Singh",
      "Raja Ranjit Singh, Sardar Hari Singh, Bhai Gurdas, Bhai Mati Das",
      "Maharaja Ranjit Singh, Bhai Taru Singh, Bhai Sukha Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Lachman Dev, Madho Das Bairagi, Banda Bairagi, Gurbaksh Singh",
  },
  {
    question: "When was Baba Banda Singh Bahadur born?",
    options: [
      "27 October 1670",
      "12 May 1710",
      "22 December 1675",
      "5 January 1678",
    ],
    answer: "27 October 1670",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which battle is associated with Baba Banda Singh Bahadur's victory over Wazir Khan?",
    options: [
      "Battle of Chappar Chiri",
      "Battle of Saragarhi",
      "Battle of Baddowal",
      "Battle of Mudki",
    ],
    answer: "Battle of Chappar Chiri",
  },
  {
    question: "Where did Baba Banda Singh Bahadur establish the new capital?",
    options: ["Mukhlispur (Lohgarh)", "Amritsar", "Lahore", "Patiala"],
    answer: "Mukhlispur (Lohgarh)",
  },
  {
    question: "Which system did Baba Banda Singh Bahadur abolish?",
    options: [
      "Zamindari system",
      "Caste system",
      "Feudal system",
      "Religious system",
    ],
    answer: "Zamindari system",
  },
  {
    question: "Which two coins did Baba Banda Singh Bahadur introduce?",
    options: [
      "Guru Nanak Dev, Guru Gobind Singh",
      "Guru Tegh Bahadur, Guru Hargobind",
      "Guru Arjan Dev, Guru Ram Das",
      "Guru Gobind Singh, Guru Nanak",
    ],
    answer: "Guru Nanak Dev, Guru Gobind Singh",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What was the official language during Baba Banda Singh Bahadur's rule?",
    options: ["Persian", "Punjabi", "Sanskrit", "Urdu"],
    answer: "Persian",
  },
  {
    question: "Which concept was given by Guru Hargobind?",
    options: ["Miri Piri", "Gurbani", "Sikhism", "Khalsa"],
    answer: "Miri Piri",
  },
  {
    question: "Where was the last battle of the Anglo-Sikh wars fought?",
    options: ["Gujarat", "Mudki", "Amritsar", "Sialkot"],
    answer: "Gujarat",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Lala Lajpat Rai was a prominent leader in the protests against which commission?",
    options: [
      "Simon Commission",
      "Hunter Commission",
      "Wardha Commission",
      "Independence Commission",
    ],
    answer: "Simon Commission",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following compositions is NOT by Guru Hargobind in the Adi Granth?",
    options: [
      "Guru Hargobind does not have any composition in Adi Granth",
      "Asa Di Var",
      "Japuji Sahib",
      "Sidh Gosht",
    ],
    answer: "Guru Hargobind does not have any composition in Adi Granth",
  },
  {
    question: "Which Granth contains the Chandi Di War?",
    options: [
      "Dasam Granth",
      "Adi Granth",
      "Benti Chaupai",
      "Vaaran Bhai Gurdas",
    ],
    answer: "Dasam Granth",
  },
  {
    question: "Chandi Di War is taken from which Puran?",
    options: [
      "Markande Puran",
      "Vishnu Puran",
      "Shiva Puran",
      "Bhagavata Puran",
    ],
    answer: "Markande Puran",
  },
  {
    question: "Which prominent leader is associated with the Ghadar Party?",
    options: [
      "Kartar Singh Sarabha",
      "Udham Singh",
      "Lala Lajpat Rai",
      "Bhagat Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Kartar Singh Sarabha",
  },
  {
    question: "Which revenue system did the British introduce in Punjab?",
    options: [
      "Mahalwari revenue system",
      "Permanent settlement",
      "Ryotwari system",
      "Zamindari system",
    ],
    answer: "Mahalwari revenue system",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which settlement system was introduced in Bengal by the British?",
    options: [
      "Permanent settlement",
      "Mahalwari revenue system",
      "Ryotwari system",
      "Village community system",
    ],
    answer: "Permanent settlement",
  },
  {
    question: "In which regions did the British introduce the Ryotwari system?",
    options: [
      "Madras, Bombay",
      "Punjab, Bengal",
      "Delhi, Uttar Pradesh",
      "Assam, Orissa",
    ],
    answer: "Madras, Bombay",
  },
  {
    question: "Who ordered the killing of Baba Banda Singh Bahadur?",
    options: ["Farukhsiyar", "Aurangzeb", "Bahadur Shah Zafar", "Nadir Shah"],
    answer: "Farukhsiyar",
  },
  {
    question: "Who was the founder of the Bhangi Misl?",
    options: [
      "Hari Singh Dhillon, Chhajja Singh",
      "Jai Singh",
      "Nawab Kapur Singh, Kushal Singh",
      "Buddha Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Hari Singh Dhillon, Chhajja Singh",
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following was the founder of the Kanhaiya Misl?",
    options: [
      "Jai Singh",
      "Hari Singh Dhillon",
      "Phul Singh",
      "Jassa Singh Ahluwalia",
    ],
    answer: "Jai Singh",
  },
  {
    question: "Who founded the Singhpuria or Faizalpuria Misl?",
    options: [
      "Nawab Kapur Singh, Kushal Singh",
      "Jai Singh",
      "Buddha Singh",
      "Heera Singh Nakai",
    ],
    answer: "Nawab Kapur Singh, Kushal Singh",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which Misl was founded by Buddha Singh, followed by Charat Singh, Naudh Singh, Maha Singh, and Ranjit Singh?",
    options: ["Sukherchakia", "Bhangi", "Ramgarhia", "Ahluwalia"],
    answer: "Sukherchakia",
  },
  {
    question: "Who was the founder of the Phulkian Misl?",
    options: [
      "Phul Singh",
      "Buddha Singh",
      "Jassa Singh Ahluwalia",
      "Nawab Kapur Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Phul Singh",
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following was founded by Jassa Singh Ahluwalia?",
    options: ["Ahluwalia", "Ramgarhia", "Sukherchakia", "Shaheedan"],
    answer: "Ahluwalia",
  },
  {
    question: "Who was the founder of the Ramgarhia Misl?",
    options: [
      "Jassa Singh Ramgarhia",
      "Sadho Singh",
      "Buddha Singh",
      "Kushal Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Jassa Singh Ramgarhia",
  },
  {
    question: "Which Misl was founded by Karora Singh?",
    options: [
      "Karor Singhia / Panjgarhia",
      "Nishanwalia",
      "Dallewalia",
      "Bhangi",
    ],
    answer: "Karor Singhia / Panjgarhia",
  },
  {
    question: "Who founded the Nishanwalia Misl?",
    options: [
      "Dasaundha Singh",
      "Heera Singh Nakai",
      "Buddha Singh",
      "Jassa Singh Ramgarhia",
    ],
    answer: "Dasaundha Singh",
  },
  {
    question: "Which Misl was founded by Gulab Singh Rathore?",
    options: ["Dallewalia", "Shaheedan", "Bhangi", "Kanhaiya"],
    answer: "Dallewalia",
  },
  {
    question: "Who was the founder of the Nakai Misl?",
    options: ["Heera Singh Nakai", "Jai Singh", "Sadho Singh", "Buddha Singh"],
    answer: "Heera Singh Nakai",
  },
  {
    question: "Which Misl was founded by Deep Singh?",
    options: ["Shaheedan", "Phulkian", "Sukherchakia", "Bhangi"],
    answer: "Shaheedan",
  },
  {
    question: "How many Misls were part of the Dal Khalsa?",
    options: ["10", "11 (except Phulkian Misl)", "12", "13"],
    answer: "11 (except Phulkian Misl)",
  },
  {
    question: "What was the main objective of the Jaito Morcha?",
    options: [
      "Restoration of Maharaja Ripudaman Singh of Nabha to his throne",
      "Fighting for the rights of farmers",
      "Protesting against the British Raj",
      "Raising awareness about Sikh education",
    ],
    answer: "Restoration of Maharaja Ripudaman Singh of Nabha to his throne",
  },
  {
    question: "Where did the Jaito Morcha take place?",
    options: [
      "Gurudwara Gangsar Sahib, Jaito (Nabha)",
      "Golden Temple, Amritsar",
      "Gurudwara Fatehgarh Sahib",
      "Gurudwara Patna Sahib",
    ],
    answer: "Gurudwara Gangsar Sahib, Jaito (Nabha)",
  },
  {
    question: "On which date was the Jaito Morcha held?",
    options: [
      "29 July 1923",
      "15 August 1923",
      "5 July 1923",
      "1 September 1923",
    ],
    answer: "29 July 1923",
  },
  {
    question: "When is Nabha Day celebrated?",
    options: [
      "9 September 1923",
      "15 August 1923",
      "1 January 1924",
      "5 March 1923",
    ],
    answer: "9 September 1923",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The Battle of Khidrana was fought between Guru Gobind Singh Ji and the Mughals. On which date did this battle take place?",
    options: [
      "29 December 1705",
      "14 December 1705",
      "1 January 1706",
      "20 January 1705",
    ],
    answer: "29 December 1705",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which Guru was born at Rai Bhoe Di Talwandi (Nankana Sahib), Lahore, Pakistan?",
    options: [
      "Guru Nanak Dev Ji",
      "Guru Angad Dev Ji",
      "Guru Ram Das Ji",
      "Guru Hargobind Ji",
    ],
    answer: "Guru Nanak Dev Ji",
  },
  {
    question: "Where was Guru Angad Dev Ji born?",
    options: [
      "Matte Di Sarai, Muktsar Sahib",
      "Chuna Mandi, Lahore",
      "Goindwal Sahib, Tarn Taran",
      "Kiratpur Sahib",
    ],
    answer: "Matte Di Sarai, Muktsar Sahib",
  },
  {
    question: "Which Guru was born at Basarke, Amritsar?",
    options: [
      "Guru Amar Das Ji",
      "Guru Nanak Dev Ji",
      "Guru Gobind Singh Ji",
      "Guru Ram Das Ji",
    ],
    answer: "Guru Amar Das Ji",
  },
  {
    question: "Where was Guru Ram Das Ji born?",
    options: [
      "Chuna Mandi, Lahore",
      "Goindwal Sahib, Tarn Taran",
      "Wadali, Amritsar",
      "Kiratpur Sahib",
    ],
    answer: "Chuna Mandi, Lahore",
  },
  {
    question: "Which Guru was born at Goindwal Sahib, Tarn Taran?",
    options: [
      "Guru Arjan Dev Ji",
      "Guru Har Gobind Ji",
      "Guru Tegh Bahadur Ji",
      "Guru Hargobind Ji",
    ],
    answer: "Guru Arjan Dev Ji",
  },
  {
    question: "Where was Guru Hargobind Ji born?",
    options: [
      "Wadali, Amritsar",
      "Basarke, Amritsar",
      "Kiratpur Sahib",
      "Goindwal Sahib",
    ],
    answer: "Wadali, Amritsar",
  },
  {
    question: "Which Guru was born at Kiratpur Sahib?",
    options: [
      "Guru Har Rai Ji",
      "Guru Gobind Singh Ji",
      "Guru Har Krishan Ji",
      "Guru Amar Das Ji",
    ],
    answer: "Guru Har Rai Ji",
  },
  {
    question: "Which Guru was born at Patna, Bihar?",
    options: [
      "Guru Gobind Singh Ji",
      "Guru Har Rai Ji",
      "Guru Har Krishan Ji",
      "Guru Nanak Dev Ji",
    ],
    answer: "Guru Gobind Singh Ji",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What was the last battle fought by Banda Singh Bahadur against the Mughals?",
    options: [
      "Battle of Gurdas Nangal",
      "Battle of Lohgarh",
      "Battle of Chappar Chiri",
      "Battle of Khidrana",
    ],
    answer: "Battle of Gurdas Nangal",
  },
  {
    question: "Which battle was fought by Banda Singh Bahadur in 1710?",
    options: [
      "Battle of Lohgarh",
      "Battle of Gurdas Nangal",
      "Battle of Khidrana",
      "Battle of Saragarhi",
    ],
    answer: "Battle of Lohgarh",
  },
  {
    question: "In which battle did Bahadar Shah's army capture Lohgarh?",
    options: [
      "Battle of Lohgarh",
      "Battle of Gurdas Nangal",
      "Battle of Saragarhi",
      "Battle of Khidrana",
    ],
    answer: "Battle of Lohgarh",
  },
  {
    question: "On which date did the Battle of Gurdas Nangal take place?",
    options: [
      "7 December 1715",
      "12 May 1710",
      "29 December 1705",
      "1 January 1706",
    ],
    answer: "7 December 1715",
  },
  {
    question: "Who was the Mughal Emperor during the Battle of Gurdas Nangal?",
    options: ["Farukhsiyar", "Aurangzeb", "Bahadar Shah", "Shah Alam"],
    answer: "Farukhsiyar",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who was the Mughal Commander during the Battle of Gurdas Nangal?",
    options: [
      "Abd al-Samad Khan",
      "Zulfiqar Ali Khan",
      "Mirza Raja Jai Singh",
      "Nawab Asad Khan",
    ],
    answer: "Abd al-Samad Khan",
  },
  {
    question:
      "After the Battle of Gurdas Nangal, where was Banda Singh Bahadur taken?",
    options: [
      "To the Dargah of Khwaja Bakhtyar Kaki at Delhi",
      "To the Red Fort",
      "To the Sultan's Palace",
      "To Agra Fort",
    ],
    answer: "To the Dargah of Khwaja Bakhtyar Kaki at Delhi",
  },
  {
    question: "On whose orders was Banda Singh Bahadur martyred in 1716?",
    options: ["Farukhsiyar", "Bahadar Shah", "Aurangzeb", "Shah Alam"],
    answer: "Farukhsiyar",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is considered the pioneer of the Punjabi Suba movement?",
    options: [
      "Master Tara Singh",
      "Banda Singh Bahadur",
      "Lala Lajpat Rai",
      "Bhagat Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Master Tara Singh",
  },
  {
    question: "Which dynasty founded Ludhiana city?",
    options: ["Lodhis", "Mughals", "Mauryas", "Guptas"],
    answer: "Lodhis",
  },
  {
    question: "Which city is known as the 'Manchester of Punjab'?",
    options: ["Ludhiana", "Amritsar", "Chandigarh", "Jalandhar"],
    answer: "Ludhiana",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which district of Punjab is the largest area-wise and population-wise?",
    options: ["Ludhiana", "Amritsar", "Patiala", "Sangrur"],
    answer: "Ludhiana",
  },
  {
    question: "Which city is considered the financial capital of Punjab?",
    options: ["Ludhiana", "Amritsar", "Chandigarh", "Jalandhar"],
    answer: "Ludhiana",
  },
  {
    question: "Which stadium is located in Ludhiana?",
    options: [
      "Guru Nanak Stadium",
      "Ludhiana International Stadium",
      "Baba Farid Stadium",
      "Patiala Stadium",
    ],
    answer: "Guru Nanak Stadium",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which university is located in Ludhiana and is associated with veterinary and animal sciences?",
    options: [
      "Guru Angad Dev Veterinary and Animal Sciences University",
      "Punjab Agricultural University",
      "Guru Nanak Dev University",
      "Shivaji University",
    ],
    answer: "Guru Angad Dev Veterinary and Animal Sciences University",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which university in Ludhiana is famous for agricultural studies?",
    options: [
      "Punjab Agricultural University",
      "Guru Angad Dev University",
      "Amritsar Agricultural University",
      "Panjab University",
    ],
    answer: "Punjab Agricultural University",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which prominent leader was associated with the Kirti Kisan Sabha, Hindustan Socialist Republican Association, and Naujawan Bharat Sabha?",
    options: [
      "Bhagat Singh",
      "Lala Lajpat Rai",
      "Master Tara Singh",
      "Jassa Singh Ahluwalia",
    ],
    answer: "Bhagat Singh",
  },
  {
    question: "Who laid the foundation of the Golden Temple?",
    options: [
      "Sai Mian Mir",
      "Guru Arjan Dev Ji",
      "Guru Nanak Dev Ji",
      "Guru Hargobind Ji",
    ],
    answer: "Sai Mian Mir",
  },
  {
    question:
      "In 1907, which prominent leader was deported without trial to Mandalay?",
    options: [
      "Lala Lajpat Rai",
      "Baba Banda Singh Bahadur",
      "Bhai Mani Singh",
      "Bhagat Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Lala Lajpat Rai",
  },
  {
    question: "Who confirmed Ranjit Singh as the governor of Lahore in 1799?",
    options: [
      "Zaman Shah",
      "Maharaja Dalip Singh",
      "Guru Gobind Singh Ji",
      "Maharaja Ranjit Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Zaman Shah",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which ruler was the Afghan king of Kabul during the time of Ranjit Singh's rise?",
    options: ["Zaman Shah", "Shah Shuja", "Nadir Shah", "Durrani Shah"],
    answer: "Zaman Shah",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who made Ranjit Singh the governor of Lahore after he helped him during an attack on Punjab?",
    options: [
      "Zaman Shah",
      "Raja Ranjit Singh",
      "Maharaja Dalip Singh",
      "Guru Gobind Singh Ji",
    ],
    answer: "Zaman Shah",
  },
  {
    question: "When was Punjabi declared the official language of Punjab?",
    options: ["1967/68", "1950", "1947", "1980"],
    answer: "1967/68",
  },
  {
    question: "Which Act declared Punjabi as the official language of Punjab?",
    options: [
      "Punjab Official Languages Act 1967",
      "Punjabi Language Act 1955",
      "Punjabi Recognition Act 1970",
      "Punjabi Language Amendment Act 1968",
    ],
    answer: "Punjab Official Languages Act 1967",
  },
  {
    question: "When was the Punjabi Official Language Act activated?",
    options: [
      "13 April 1968",
      "15 August 1965",
      "25 December 1967",
      "1 January 1970",
    ],
    answer: "13 April 1968",
  },
  {
    question: "Who was the ruler of Punjab when the British annexed Punjab?",
    options: [
      "Maharaja Dalip Singh",
      "Maharaja Ranjit Singh",
      "Maharaja Charat Singh",
      "Maharaja Hira Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Maharaja Dalip Singh",
  },
  {
    question: "Who was the contemporary ruler during Guru Ram Das's time?",
    options: ["Akbar", "Aurangzeb", "Jahangir", "Sher Shah"],
    answer: "Akbar",
  },
  {
    question: "Who was the contemporary ruler during Guru Hargobind's time?",
    options: ["Jahangir and Shah Jahan", "Aurangzeb", "Humayun", "Akbar"],
    answer: "Jahangir and Shah Jahan",
  },
  {
    question: "Who was the contemporary ruler during Guru Har Krishan's time?",
    options: ["Aurangzeb", "Jahangir", "Shah Jahan", "Akbar"],
    answer: "Aurangzeb",
  },
  {
    question: "Who was the contemporary ruler during Guru Angad Dev's time?",
    options: ["Humayun and Sher Shah", "Akbar", "Jahangir", "Aurangzeb"],
    answer: "Humayun and Sher Shah",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Under which Guru did Sikhs become a political and military force?",
    options: [
      "Guru Hargobind",
      "Guru Nanak Dev",
      "Guru Gobind Singh",
      "Guru Amar Das",
    ],
    answer: "Guru Hargobind",
  },
  {
    question: "Who was the Guru of Bhai Ram Singh (Namdhari)?",
    options: [
      "Baba Balak Singh",
      "Baba Ram Singh",
      "Guru Gobind Singh Ji",
      "Guru Hargobind",
    ],
    answer: "Baba Balak Singh",
  },
  {
    question: "Where was Guru Amar Das born?",
    options: ["Basarke", "Kiratpur", "Goindwal", "Patna"],
    answer: "Basarke",
  },
  {
    question: "Where was Guru Har Rai born?",
    options: ["Kiratpur", "Patna", "Basarke", "Goindwal"],
    answer: "Kiratpur",
  },
  {
    question: "Where was Guru Gobind Singh born?",
    options: ["Patna", "Goindwal", "Basarke", "Kiratpur"],
    answer: "Patna",
  },
  {
    question: "Where was Guru Arjan born?",
    options: ["Goindwal", "Patna", "Kiratpur", "Basarke"],
    answer: "Goindwal",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who won the Battle of Hydaspes in 326 BC against the local Punjabi ruler Porus?",
    options: ["Alexander", "Seleucus Nicator", "Julius Caesar", "Ashoka"],
    answer: "Alexander",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who was the Senapati (commander) of Alexander during the Battle of Hydaspes?",
    options: ["Seleucus Nicator", "Darius III", "Bucephalus", "Perdiccas"],
    answer: "Seleucus Nicator",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who named the city Bucephala in honor of his horse Bucephalus after the Battle of Hydaspes in 326 BCE?",
    options: ["Alexander", "Julius Caesar", "Darius III", "Cyrus the Great"],
    answer: "Alexander",
  },
  {
    question: "Which river was called 'Hesidros' by the Greeks?",
    options: ["Satluj", "Jhelum", "Beas", "Chenab"],
    answer: "Satluj",
  },
  {
    question: "Which river was called 'Hydaspes' by the Greeks?",
    options: ["Jhelum", "Beas", "Chenab", "Ravi"],
    answer: "Jhelum",
  },
  {
    question: "Which river was called 'Hyphasis' by the Greeks?",
    options: ["Beas", "Jhelum", "Satluj", "Chenab"],
    answer: "Beas",
  },
  {
    question: "Which river was called 'Acensines' by the Greeks?",
    options: ["Chenab", "Ravi", "Beas", "Jhelum"],
    answer: "Chenab",
  },
  {
    question: "Which river was called 'Hydroatis' by the Greeks?",
    options: ["Ravi", "Chenab", "Beas", "Jhelum"],
    answer: "Ravi",
  },
  {
    question: "Which river was called 'Shutudri' in Vedic texts?",
    options: ["Satluj", "Beas", "Jhelum", "Chenab"],
    answer: "Satluj",
  },
  {
    question: "Which river was called 'Vitasta' in Vedic texts?",
    options: ["Jhelum", "Beas", "Satluj", "Chenab"],
    answer: "Jhelum",
  },
  {
    question: "Which river was called 'Vipasa' in Vedic texts?",
    options: ["Beas", "Chenab", "Ravi", "Satluj"],
    answer: "Beas",
  },
  {
    question: "Which river was called 'Asikni' in Vedic texts?",
    options: ["Chenab", "Ravi", "Satluj", "Beas"],
    answer: "Chenab",
  },
  {
    question: "Which river was called 'Parushni' in Vedic texts?",
    options: ["Ravi", "Satluj", "Beas", "Jhelum"],
    answer: "Ravi",
  },
  {
    question: "Which Sikh Guru was born and died at the same place?",
    options: [
      "Guru Har Rai",
      "Guru Nanak Dev Ji",
      "Guru Gobind Singh Ji",
      "Guru Tegh Bahadur Ji",
    ],
    answer: "Guru Har Rai",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is the modern name of 'Khidrane di Dhab', a historical place associated with Guru Gobind Singh Ji?",
    options: [
      "Sri Muktsar Sahib",
      "Sri Amritsar Sahib",
      "Sri Tarn Taran Sahib",
      "Sri Fatehgarh Sahib",
    ],
    answer: "Sri Muktsar Sahib",
  },
  {
    question: "When did the Chief Khalsa Diwan come into existence?",
    options: [
      "30 October 1902",
      "15 August 1902",
      "13 April 1902",
      "5 November 1902",
    ],
    answer: "30 October 1902",
  },
  {
    question: "Who was the first president of the Chief Khalsa Diwan?",
    options: [
      "Bhai Arjan Singh Bagrhiya",
      "Sundar Singh Majithiya",
      "Bhai Taru Singh",
      "Bhai Kanhaiya",
    ],
    answer: "Bhai Arjan Singh Bagrhiya",
  },
  {
    question: "What was the language of the Khalsa Durbar records?",
    options: ["Persian", "Punjabi", "Sanskrit", "Urdu"],
    answer: "Persian",
  },
  {
    question: "Why was Punjab called 'Takk Country' in ancient times?",
    options: [
      "Because of the Takk tribe",
      "Because of the rivers",
      "Because of the agriculture",
      "Because of the Sikh Gurus",
    ],
    answer: "Because of the Takk tribe",
  },
  {
    question: "In which year did Babur attack Punjab for the first time?",
    options: ["1519", "1526", "1530", "1524"],
    answer: "1519",
  },
  {
    question: "What was the last battle fought by Babur in Punjab in 1526?",
    options: [
      "Battle of Panipat",
      "Battle of Gurdas Nangal",
      "Battle of Amritsar",
      "Battle of Lahore",
    ],
    answer: "Battle of Panipat",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who invited Babur to attack Punjab in 1526, leading to the Battle of Panipat?",
    options: ["Ibrahim Lodi", "Daulat Khan Lodi", "Sher Shah Suri", "Humayun"],
    answer: "Ibrahim Lodi",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who was the Fauzdar of Sirhind at the time of Banda Singh Bahadur?",
    options: ["Wazir Khan", "Mirza Hakim", "Nawab Kapur Singh", "Shah Jahan"],
    answer: "Wazir Khan",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which Mughal Emperor ordered the execution of Banda Singh Bahadur?",
    options: ["Farukh Siyar", "Aurangzeb", "Bahadur Shah Zafar", "Jahangir"],
    answer: "Farukh Siyar",
  },
  {
    question: "In which year was the First Battle of Anandpur Sahib fought?",
    options: ["1701", "1699", "1704", "1688"],
    answer: "1701",
  },
  {
    question: "Which battle was fought by Guru Gobind Singh Ji in 1688?",
    options: [
      "Battle of Bhangani",
      "Battle of Khidrana",
      "Battle of Chamkaur",
      "Battle of Nirmoh",
    ],
    answer: "Battle of Bhangani",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who was the main opponent in the Battle of Anandpur Sahib in 1701?",
    options: ["Bhim Chand", "Alif Khan", "Wazir Khan", "Mirza Hakim"],
    answer: "Bhim Chand",
  },
  {
    question: "Which battle was fought in 1704 against Wazir Khan?",
    options: [
      "Second Battle of Anandpur",
      "Battle of Basoli",
      "Battle of Chamkaur",
      "Battle of Nirmoh",
    ],
    answer: "Second Battle of Anandpur",
  },
  {
    question:
      "In which battle did Guru Gobind Singh Ji capture Kalmot in 1702?",
    options: [
      "Battle of Basoli",
      "Battle of Anandpur",
      "Battle of Nirmoh",
      "Battle of Khidrana",
    ],
    answer: "Battle of Basoli",
  },
  {
    question: "Who was the last Sikh Maharaja of Punjab?",
    options: [
      "Dalip Singh",
      "Maharaja Ranjit Singh",
      "Maharaja Sher Singh",
      "Maharaja Gulab Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Dalip Singh",
  },
  {
    question:
      "In which year did Maharaja Ranjit Singh win Amritsar from the Bhangi Misl?",
    options: ["1805", "1800", "1810", "1799"],
    answer: "1805",
  },
  {
    question:
      "In which year did Maharaja Ranjit Singh win Lahore from the Bhangi Misl (Chet Singh)?",
    options: ["1799", "1800", "1805", "1810"],
    answer: "1799",
  },
  {
    question: "From whom did Maharaja Ranjit Singh win Amritsar in 1805?",
    options: [
      "Mai Sukhan (widow of Gulab Singh Bhangi)",
      "Jeevan Singh",
      "Sansar Chand",
      "Muzaffar Khan",
    ],
    answer: "Mai Sukhan (widow of Gulab Singh Bhangi)",
  },
  {
    question:
      "In which year did Maharaja Ranjit Singh win Kasur from Qutb-ud-din?",
    options: ["1807", "1805", "1813", "1818"],
    answer: "1807",
  },
  {
    question: "From whom did Maharaja Ranjit Singh win Jhang in 1807?",
    options: ["Ahmed Khan", "Jeevan Singh", "Sansar Chand", "Jabar Khan"],
    answer: "Ahmed Khan",
  },
  {
    question:
      "In which year did Maharaja Ranjit Singh win Sialkot from Jeevan Singh?",
    options: ["1808", "1807", "1813", "1819"],
    answer: "1808",
  },
  {
    question: "From whom did Maharaja Ranjit Singh win Kangra in 1809?",
    options: ["Sansar Chand", "Jeevan Singh", "Muzaffar Khan", "Azam Khan"],
    answer: "Sansar Chand",
  },
  {
    question:
      "In which year did Maharaja Ranjit Singh win Attock from Jahandad Khan?",
    options: ["1813", "1810", "1818", "1807"],
    answer: "1813",
  },
  {
    question: "From whom did Maharaja Ranjit Singh win Multan in 1818?",
    options: ["Muzaffar Khan", "Azam Khan", "Jeevan Singh", "Sansar Chand"],
    answer: "Muzaffar Khan",
  },
  {
    question:
      "In which year did Maharaja Ranjit Singh win Kashmir from Jabar Khan?",
    options: ["1819", "1818", "1813", "1834"],
    answer: "1819",
  },
  {
    question: "From whom did Maharaja Ranjit Singh win Peshawar in 1834?",
    options: ["Azam Khan", "Jeevan Singh", "Jabar Khan", "Muzaffar Khan"],
    answer: "Azam Khan",
  },
  {
    question: "Who was the first Senapati of Dal Khalsa?",
    options: [
      "Jassa Singh Ahluwalia",
      "Maharaja Ranjit Singh",
      "Baba Banda Singh Bahadur",
      "Raja Kesar Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Jassa Singh Ahluwalia",
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following is the location of Qila Mubarak?",
    options: ["Patiala", "Ludhiana", "Amritsar", "Pathankot"],
    answer: "Patiala",
  },
  {
    question: "Where is Shahpur Kandi Qila located?",
    options: ["Pathankot", "Amritsar", "Ludhiana", "SBS Nagar"],
    answer: "Pathankot",
  },
  {
    question: "Which fort is located in Ludhiana?",
    options: [
      "Philor Qila",
      "Gobindgarh Qila",
      "Shahpur Kandi Qila",
      "Qila Mubarak",
    ],
    answer: "Philor Qila",
  },
  {
    question: "Where is Gobindgarh Qila located?",
    options: ["Amritsar", "Ludhiana", "Pathankot", "Patiala"],
    answer: "Amritsar",
  },
  {
    question: "Where is Bhagat Singh Ajaib Ghar located?",
    options: [
      "Khatkarkalan, SBS Nagar",
      "Ludhiana",
      "Mohali",
      "Anandpur Sahib",
    ],
    answer: "Khatkarkalan, SBS Nagar",
  },
  {
    question: "Which museum is located in Anandpur Sahib?",
    options: [
      "Virasat-e-Khalsa",
      "Sikh Ajaib Ghar",
      "Rural (Pendu) Ajaib Ghar",
      "Bhagat Singh Ajaib Ghar",
    ],
    answer: "Virasat-e-Khalsa",
  },
  {
    question: "Where is the Sikh Ajaib Ghar located?",
    options: ["Mohali", "Ludhiana", "Anandpur Sahib", "Patiala"],
    answer: "Mohali",
  },
  {
    question: "Where is Rural (Pendu) Ajaib Ghar located?",
    options: ["Ludhiana", "Mohali", "Amritsar", "Patiala"],
    answer: "Ludhiana",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which two mahal are located in Patiala and were built by Narinder Singh?",
    options: [
      "Mauti Mahal and Sis Mahal",
      "Gobind Mahal and Fateh Mahal",
      "Kesar Mahal and Bahram Mahal",
      "Patiala Mahal and Darbara Mahal",
    ],
    answer: "Mauti Mahal and Sis Mahal",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following forts are associated with Anandpur Sahib?",
    options: [
      "Keshgarh Sahib, Qila Taragarh, Qila Fatehgarh, Qila Lohgarh, Qila Holgarh, Anandgarh",
      "Philor Qila, Gobindgarh Qila, Qila Lohgarh",
      "Qila Mubarak, Qila Fatehgarh, Qila Lohgarh",
      "Gobindgarh Qila, Qila Holgarh, Qila Fatehgarh",
    ],
    answer:
      "Keshgarh Sahib, Qila Taragarh, Qila Fatehgarh, Qila Lohgarh, Qila Holgarh, Anandgarh",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Where is the Sports Museum, National Institute of Sports located?",
    options: [
      "Patiala (Moti Mahal)",
      "Anandpur Sahib",
      "Fatehgarh Sahib",
      "Amritsar",
    ],
    answer: "Patiala (Moti Mahal)",
  },
  {
    question: "Where is Guru Teg Bahadur Museum located?",
    options: ["Anandpur Sahib", "Amritsar", "Fatehgarh Sahib", "Patiala"],
    answer: "Anandpur Sahib",
  },
  {
    question: "Where is Sanghol Museum located?",
    options: ["Fatehgarh Sahib", "Amritsar", "Bathinda", "Anandpur Sahib"],
    answer: "Fatehgarh Sahib",
  },
  {
    question: "Where is the Anglo Sikh War Memorial located?",
    options: ["Firozpur", "Amritsar", "Ludhiana", "Patiala"],
    answer: "Firozpur",
  },
  {
    question: "Where is the Maharaja Ranjit Singh Museum located?",
    options: ["Amritsar", "Patiala", "Firozpur", "Ludhiana"],
    answer: "Amritsar",
  },
  {
    question: "What is the shape of Punjab?",
    options: ["Triangular", "Circular", "Square", "Rectangular"],
    answer: "Triangular",
  },
  {
    question: "Where is Qila Mubarak located?",
    options: ["Bathinda", "Amritsar", "Fatehgarh Sahib", "Pathankot"],
    answer: "Bathinda",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which community’s initiative to protect endangered black buck species is associated with Abohar Wildlife Sanctuary?",
    options: [
      "Bishnoi Community",
      "Sikh Community",
      "Rajput Community",
      "Jat Community",
    ],
    answer: "Bishnoi Community",
  },
  {
    question: "Where is Harike Wildlife Sanctuary located?",
    options: ["Tarn Taran", "Hoshiarpur", "Ferozepur", "Patiala"],
    answer: "Tarn Taran",
  },
  {
    question: "Where is Takhni-Rehmapur Wildlife Sanctuary located?",
    options: ["Hoshiarpur", "Tarn Taran", "Rupnagar", "Gurdaspur"],
    answer: "Hoshiarpur",
  },
  {
    question: "Where is Abohar Wildlife Sanctuary located?",
    options: ["Ferozepur", "Patiala", "Sangrur", "Mansa"],
    answer: "Ferozepur",
  },
  {
    question: "Which wildlife sanctuary is located in Patiala?",
    options: [
      "Bir Moti Baag Wildlife Sanctuary",
      "Harike Wildlife Sanctuary",
      "Nangal Wildlife Sanctuary",
      "Bir Aishwan Wildlife Sanctuary",
    ],
    answer: "Bir Moti Baag Wildlife Sanctuary",
  },
  {
    question: "Where is Bir Gurdialpura Wildlife Sanctuary located?",
    options: ["Patiala", "Mansa", "Sangrur", "Amritsar"],
    answer: "Patiala",
  },
  {
    question: "Which wildlife sanctuary is located in Rupnagar?",
    options: [
      "Jhajjar Bacholi Wildlife Sanctuary",
      "Tarn Taran Wildlife Sanctuary",
      "Hoshiarpur Wildlife Sanctuary",
      "Ferozepur Wildlife Sanctuary",
    ],
    answer: "Jhajjar Bacholi Wildlife Sanctuary",
  },
  {
    question: "Where is Nangal Wildlife Sanctuary located?",
    options: ["Ropar", "Patiala", "Mansa", "Firozpur"],
    answer: "Ropar",
  },
  {
    question: "What is the total cultivable area of Punjab?",
    options: [
      "4.2 million ha",
      "5.0 million ha",
      "3.5 million ha",
      "6.0 million ha",
    ],
    answer: "4.2 million ha",
  },
  {
    question: "Which mountain range fringes Punjab to the northeast and north?",
    options: ["Shivalik Range", "Himalayas", "Aravalli Range", "Vindhya Range"],
    answer: "Shivalik Range",
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following dams are built on the Satluj River?",
    options: [
      "Bhakhra Dam, Koldan Dam, Nathpa Jhakri, Karcham Wantoo",
      "Dulhasti Dam, Baira Siul Dam, Pong Dam",
      "Ranjit Sagar Dam, Harike Dam, Nangal Dam",
      "Indira Sagar Dam, Sardar Sarovar Dam, Tehri Dam",
    ],
    answer: "Bhakhra Dam, Koldan Dam, Nathpa Jhakri, Karcham Wantoo",
  },
  {
    question: "Where does the Satluj River originate?",
    options: [
      "Rakas Lake, Tibet, China",
      "Kailash Mountain, Tibet",
      "Himalayan Range, India",
      "Nanda Devi, Uttarakhand",
    ],
    answer: "Rakas Lake, Tibet, China",
  },
  {
    question: "What is the Tibetan name for the Satluj River?",
    options: ["Langqen Zangbo", "Mekong", "Yarlung Tsangpo", "Lancang"],
    answer: "Langqen Zangbo",
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following are tributaries of the Satluj River?",
    options: [
      "Baspa, Spiti, Beas",
      "Chenab, Ravi, Jhelum",
      "Sindhu, Sutlej, Beas",
      "Ganga, Yamuna, Beas",
    ],
    answer: "Baspa, Spiti, Beas",
  },
  {
    question: "Where do the Satluj and Chenab rivers meet to form Panhcnad?",
    options: [
      "Ujj Sharif, Pakistan",
      "Attock, Pakistan",
      "Lahore, Pakistan",
      "Faisalabad, Pakistan",
    ],
    answer: "Ujj Sharif, Pakistan",
  },
  {
    question: "Where does the Satluj River enter India from Tibet?",
    options: [
      "Shipki La, Himachal Pradesh",
      "Nathu La, Sikkim",
      "Khyber Pass, KPK",
      "Bara Lachha Pass, Himachal Pradesh",
    ],
    answer: "Shipki La, Himachal Pradesh",
  },
  {
    question:
      "When was the first Software Technology Park (STP) in Punjab established?",
    options: [
      "1998-99 at Mohali",
      "2000-01 at Chandigarh",
      "1995-96 at Patiala",
      "2005-06 at Ludhiana",
    ],
    answer: "1998-99 at Mohali",
  },
  {
    question: "Which community is associated with the Vimukt tribe in Punjab?",
    options: ["Naat", "Bishnoi", "Jat", "Rajput"],
    answer: "Naat",
  },
  {
    question: "Which Gurudwara has the largest Sarowar?",
    options: [
      "Gurudwara Sri Tarn Taran Sahib",
      "Gurudwara Sri Harmandir Sahib",
      "Gurudwara Sri Anandpur Sahib",
      "Gurudwara Sri Patna Sahib",
    ],
    answer: "Gurudwara Sri Tarn Taran Sahib",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which city was the most populated in Punjab according to the 2011 Census?",
    options: ["Ludhiana", "Amritsar", "Patiala", "Jalandhar"],
    answer: "Ludhiana",
  },
  {
    question: "Which year was the 2011 Census conducted in India?",
    options: [
      "15th Census and 7th after Independence",
      "16th Census and 6th after Independence",
      "14th Census and 8th after Independence",
      "13th Census and 5th after Independence",
    ],
    answer: "15th Census and 7th after Independence",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What was the total population of Punjab according to the 2011 Census?",
    options: ["277.43 lakh", "289.56 lakh", "267.89 lakh", "315.22 lakh"],
    answer: "277.43 lakh",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What was the literacy rate in Punjab according to the 2011 Census?",
    options: ["75.84%", "78.34%", "71.23%", "80.11%"],
    answer: "75.84%",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What was the sex ratio (female per 1000 males) in Punjab according to the 2011 Census?",
    options: ["895", "915", "880", "905"],
    answer: "895",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What was the child sex ratio (female per 1000 males) in Punjab according to the 2011 Census?",
    options: ["846", "825", "860", "880"],
    answer: "846",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What was the population growth rate in Punjab between 2001-2011?",
    options: ["13.9%", "12.5%", "14.2%", "15.3%"],
    answer: "13.9%",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is the population density in Punjab according to the 2011 Census?",
    options: [
      "551 per sq. km",
      "530 per sq. km",
      "565 per sq. km",
      "600 per sq. km",
    ],
    answer: "551 per sq. km",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is the percentage of Scheduled Caste population in Punjab according to the 2011 Census?",
    options: ["31.94%", "28.50%", "35.10%", "30.20%"],
    answer: "31.94%",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which district had the highest literacy rate in Punjab according to the 2011 Census?",
    options: [
      "Hoshiarpur (84.6%)",
      "Amritsar (82.4%)",
      "Chandigarh (88.5%)",
      "Jalandhar (80.5%)",
    ],
    answer: "Hoshiarpur (84.6%)",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which district had the lowest literacy rate in Punjab according to the 2011 Census?",
    options: [
      "Mansa (61.8%)",
      "Fazilka (63.2%)",
      "Patiala (70.4%)",
      "Sangrur (65.1%)",
    ],
    answer: "Mansa (61.8%)",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Where does the Indira Gandhi Canal, the largest irrigation canal in India, start?",
    options: [
      "Harike Barrage (Tarn Taran)",
      "Ferozepur Barrage",
      "Ropar Barrage",
      "Himachal Pradesh",
    ],
    answer: "Harike Barrage (Tarn Taran)",
  },
  {
    question: "What is the length of the Indira Gandhi Canal?",
    options: ["650 km", "600 km", "700 km", "500 km"],
    answer: "650 km",
  },
  {
    question:
      "In which year did the construction of the Indira Gandhi Canal begin?",
    options: ["1952", "1950", "1960", "1947"],
    answer: "1952",
  },
  {
    question:
      "From which river does the Indira Gandhi Canal receive its water?",
    options: ["Satluj River", "Beas River", "Chenab River", "Yamuna River"],
    answer: "Satluj River",
  },
  {
    question: "Where does the Indira Gandhi Canal end?",
    options: [
      "Gunjangarh, Jaiselmer District",
      "Sriganganagar, Rajasthan",
      "Jodhpur, Rajasthan",
      "Barmer, Rajasthan",
    ],
    answer: "Gunjangarh, Jaiselmer District",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The Phillaur Fort, which was originally a Sarai, was rebuilt as a fort by which Maharaja?",
    options: [
      "Maharaja Ranjit Singh",
      "Maharaja Kesar Singh",
      "Maharaja Gulab Singh",
      "Maharaja Hari Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Maharaja Ranjit Singh",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who designed the Phillaur Fort during the reign of Maharaja Ranjit Singh?",
    options: [
      "Dewan Mohkam Chand",
      "Maharaja Ranjit Singh",
      "Sardar Hari Singh Nalwa",
      "Lala Lajpat Rai",
    ],
    answer: "Dewan Mohkam Chand",
  },
  {
    question:
      "In which year was the Phillaur Fort renamed as Maharaja Ranjit Singh Fort by the Punjab government?",
    options: [
      "6 April 1973",
      "1 January 1970",
      "15 August 1975",
      "10 October 1980",
    ],
    answer: "6 April 1973",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What was the original purpose of the structure at Phillaur before it was rebuilt as a fort by Maharaja Ranjit Singh?",
    options: [
      "Shahi Sarai (royal inn)",
      "Maharaja's palace",
      "Military barracks",
      "Religious temple",
    ],
    answer: "Shahi Sarai (royal inn)",
  },
  {
    question:
      "After the defeat of the Sikhs in the Battle of Aliwal in 1846, who took control of the Phillaur Fort?",
    options: ["The British", "The Mughals", "The Marathas", "The Rajputs"],
    answer: "The British",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What was the purpose of the Phillaur Fort after it was transferred to civil authorities in 1890?",
    options: [
      "Police training centre",
      "Museum",
      "Courthouse",
      "Military base",
    ],
    answer: "Police training centre",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which Sufi saint's shrine is located at Phillaur Fort, making it a sacred place for local Muslims?",
    options: [
      "Peer Baba Abdulla Shah Ji",
      "Peer Ghulam Shah Ji",
      "Peer Nizamuddin Auliya",
      "Peer Sufiyan Shah Ji",
    ],
    answer: "Peer Baba Abdulla Shah Ji",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following features are found in the Phillaur Fort related to the Muslim community?",
    options: [
      "Graves of Shah Suja's family members",
      "Hindu temple",
      "Sikh Guru Granth Sahib",
      "British military relics",
    ],
    answer: "Graves of Shah Suja's family members",
  },
  {
    question:
      "According to the 2011 census, what was Punjab's national rank with regard to literacy?",
    options: ["14th", "10th", "18th", "20th"],
    answer: "14th",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What was Punjab's rank according to population in the 2011 census?",
    options: ["15th", "10th", "20th", "25th"],
    answer: "15th",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is the total area of Punjab according to the 2011 census (in sq km)?",
    options: ["50,362 sq km", "60,000 sq km", "45,000 sq km", "40,000 sq km"],
    answer: "50,362 sq km",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is the sex ratio in Punjab’s Hoshiarpur district according to the 2011 census?",
    options: ["961", "920", "950", "890"],
    answer: "961",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is the sex ratio in Punjab’s Bathinda district according to the 2011 census?",
    options: ["868", "920", "950", "890"],
    answer: "868",
  },
  {
    question:
      "According to the 2011 census, what percentage of Punjab's population belongs to Scheduled Castes (SC)?",
    options: ["31.94%", "35.00%", "40.00%", "25.00%"],
    answer: "31.94%",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which district in Punjab has the highest literacy rate according to the 2011 census?",
    options: [
      "Hoshiarpur (84.6%)",
      "Ludhiana (75%)",
      "Patiala (80%)",
      "Amritsar (77%)",
    ],
    answer: "Hoshiarpur (84.6%)",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which district in Punjab has the lowest literacy rate according to the 2011 census?",
    options: [
      "Mansa (61.8%)",
      "Ludhiana (75%)",
      "Patiala (70%)",
      "Barnala (65%)",
    ],
    answer: "Mansa (61.8%)",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is the population density of Punjab according to the 2011 census?",
    options: [
      "551 people per sq km",
      "600 people per sq km",
      "500 people per sq km",
      "450 people per sq km",
    ],
    answer: "551 people per sq km",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which district in Punjab has the highest population density according to the 2011 census?",
    options: ["Ludhiana", "Amritsar", "Patiala", "Jalandhar"],
    answer: "Ludhiana",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which district in Punjab has the lowest population density according to the 2011 census?",
    options: ["Barnala", "Mansa", "Rupnagar", "Fatehgarh Sahib"],
    answer: "Barnala",
  },
  {
    question: "Where does the Jhelum river originate?",
    options: [
      "Vernag, Kashmir",
      "Shimla, Himachal Pradesh",
      "Ladakh, India",
      "Rajasthan, India",
    ],
    answer: "Vernag, Kashmir",
  },
  {
    question: "What is the Malwa tract region situated between?",
    options: [
      "Sutlej and Yamuna/Ghaggar rivers",
      "Ganga and Yamuna rivers",
      "Indus and Sutlej rivers",
      "Ravi and Beas rivers",
    ],
    answer: "Sutlej and Yamuna/Ghaggar rivers",
  },
  {
    question: "How many districts are there in the Malwa region of Punjab?",
    options: ["15", "10", "20", "12"],
    answer: "15",
  },
  {
    question: "Which river originates in South-West Tibet?",
    options: ["Satluj", "Indus", "Chenab", "Ravi"],
    answer: "Satluj",
  },
  {
    question: "From where does the Satluj river enter India?",
    options: [
      "Shipki La pass in Himachal",
      "Kali Nangma pass in Jammu & Kashmir",
      "Kunzum La pass in Himachal",
      "Nathu La pass in Sikkim",
    ],
    answer: "Shipki La pass in Himachal",
  },
  {
    question: "What was Punjab’s population according to the 2011 census?",
    options: ["27.7 million", "25.6 million", "30.1 million", "33.5 million"],
    answer: "27.7 million",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following seeds were introduced during the Green Revolution in Punjab for wheat?",
    options: ["Mexico", "USA", "Australia", "China"],
    answer: "Mexico",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which countries introduced HYV seeds for rice during the Green Revolution in Punjab?",
    options: [
      "Philippines, Malaysia",
      "USA, Japan",
      "China, India",
      "Australia, Thailand",
    ],
    answer: "Philippines, Malaysia",
  },
  {
    question: "What was the capital of Punjab before independence?",
    options: ["Lahore", "Shimla", "Chandigarh", "Amritsar"],
    answer: "Lahore",
  },
  {
    question: "Which bird is the state bird of Punjab?",
    options: [
      "Northern Goshawk (Baaz)",
      "Indian Peacock",
      "Indian Eagle",
      "Kestrel",
    ],
    answer: "Northern Goshawk (Baaz)",
  },
  {
    question: "Which animal is the state animal of Punjab?",
    options: [
      "Antilope Cervicapra (Black Buck)",
      "Indian Lion",
      "Indian Elephant",
      "Indian Wolf",
    ],
    answer: "Antilope Cervicapra (Black Buck)",
  },
  {
    question: "Which aquatic animal is the state aquatic animal of Punjab?",
    options: [
      "Indus River Dolphin (Platanista Minor)",
      "Indian Crocodile",
      "Ganges River Dolphin",
      "Freshwater Tortoise",
    ],
    answer: "Indus River Dolphin (Platanista Minor)",
  },
  {
    question: "Which flower is the state flower of Punjab?",
    options: [
      "Acidanthera Gladiolus (Sword Lily)",
      "Lotus",
      "Rose",
      "Sunflower",
    ],
    answer: "Acidanthera Gladiolus (Sword Lily)",
  },
  {
    question: "Which tree is the state tree of Punjab?",
    options: ["Sheesham (Dalbergia Sissoo)", "Peepal", "Neem", "Bamboo"],
    answer: "Sheesham (Dalbergia Sissoo)",
  },
  {
    question: "Which Punjabi novel was written by Surinder Singh Narula?",
    options: [
      "Pio Puttar",
      "Chandigarh Diyan Kahaniyan",
      "Bharat Da Ghar",
      "Dhol Baje",
    ],
    answer: "Pio Puttar",
  },
  {
    question: "Who first introduced Nanakshahi coins?",
    options: [
      "Banda Singh Bahadur",
      "Guru Gobind Singh Ji",
      "Maharaja Ranjit Singh",
      "Guru Nanak Dev Ji",
    ],
    answer: "Banda Singh Bahadur",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following districts are part of the Doaba area of Punjab?",
    options: [
      "Hoshiarpur, Kapurthala, Jalandhar, SBS Nagar",
      "Amritsar, Gurdaspur, Tarn Taran",
      "Ludhiana, Patiala, Mansa",
      "Bathinda, Faridkot, Sangrur",
    ],
    answer: "Hoshiarpur, Kapurthala, Jalandhar, SBS Nagar",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following districts are part of the Majha area of Punjab?",
    options: [
      "Pathankot, Gurdaspur, Amritsar, Tarn Taran",
      "Ludhiana, Jalandhar, Moga",
      "Barnala, Patiala, Fatehgarh Sahib",
      "Bathinda, Fazilka, Sangrur",
    ],
    answer: "Pathankot, Gurdaspur, Amritsar, Tarn Taran",
  },
  {
    question: "Which district has the least population density in Punjab?",
    options: ["Sri Muktsar Sahib", "Barnala", "Fazilka", "Mansa"],
    answer: "Sri Muktsar Sahib",
  },
  {
    question: "Which district in Punjab has the least population?",
    options: ["Barnala", "Mansa", "Sangrur", "Patiala"],
    answer: "Barnala",
  },
  {
    question: "In which district does Gidderbaha Tehsil fall?",
    options: ["Sri Muktsar Sahib", "Bathinda", "Fazilka", "Mansa"],
    answer: "Sri Muktsar Sahib",
  },
  {
    question: "Which district is referred to as the area of white gold?",
    options: ["Mansa", "Fazilka", "Barnala", "Ludhiana"],
    answer: "Mansa",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is known as the Nightingale of Punjab?",
    options: ["Surinder Kaur", "Gurdas Maan", "Jagjit Singh", "Amrita Pritam"],
    answer: "Surinder Kaur",
  },
  {
    question: "Which district has the least sex ratio in Punjab?",
    options: ["Bathinda", "Mansa", "Fazilka", "Jalandhar"],
    answer: "Bathinda",
  },
  {
    question: "Who was the architect of Chandigarh?",
    options: [
      "Le Corbusier",
      "Pierre Jeanneret",
      "Louis Kahn",
      "Frank Lloyd Wright",
    ],
    answer: "Le Corbusier",
  },
  {
    question: "Where is Chandigarh situated?",
    options: [
      "At the foot of the Shivalik Hills",
      "On the banks of the Beas River",
      "Near the Himalayas",
      "In the plains of Malwa",
    ],
    answer: "At the foot of the Shivalik Hills",
  },
  {
    question: "Chandigarh is named after which temple?",
    options: [
      "Chandi Mata Temple",
      "Durga Devi Temple",
      "Shiva Temple",
      "Hari Mandir",
    ],
    answer: "Chandi Mata Temple",
  },
  {
    question: "What is the area of Chandigarh?",
    options: ["114 sq km", "80 sq km", "100 sq km", "150 sq km"],
    answer: "114 sq km",
  },
  {
    question: "When was the foundation stone of Chandigarh laid?",
    options: ["1952", "1947", "1960", "1966"],
    answer: "1952",
  },
  {
    question: "When did Chandigarh become the capital of Punjab?",
    options: ["1952", "1947", "1965", "1980"],
    answer: "1952",
  },
  {
    question: "Which city was the capital of Punjab before Chandigarh?",
    options: ["Shimla", "Lahore", "Delhi", "Patiala"],
    answer: "Shimla",
  },
  {
    question: "How many districts are in Chandigarh?",
    options: ["1", "2", "3", "5"],
    answer: "1",
  },
  {
    question: "How many Lok Sabha seats does Chandigarh have?",
    options: ["1", "2", "3", "4"],
    answer: "1",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the current Member of Parliament for Chandigarh?",
    options: [
      "Manish Tiwari",
      "Harsimrat Kaur Badal",
      "Navjot Singh Sidhu",
      "Raghav Chadha",
    ],
    answer: "Manish Tiwari",
  },
  {
    question: "Who designed Rock Garden in Chandigarh?",
    options: ["Nek Chand", "Le Corbusier", "Pierre Jeanneret", "Sanjay Kumar"],
    answer: "Nek Chand",
  },
  {
    question: "Where is Zakir Hussain Rose Garden located in Chandigarh?",
    options: ["Sector 16", "Sector 22", "Sector 10", "Sector 4"],
    answer: "Sector 16",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who is the famous poet behind the romantic story of Heer Ranjha?",
    options: [
      "Waris Shah",
      "Bulleh Shah",
      "Shiv Kumar Batalvi",
      "Amrita Pritam",
    ],
    answer: "Waris Shah",
  },
  {
    question: "Which district in Punjab is the least literate?",
    options: ["Mansa", "Fazilka", "Bathinda", "Jalandhar"],
    answer: "Mansa",
  },
  {
    question: "Which tehsil in Punjab has no urban population?",
    options: ["Khadur Sahib", "Amritsar", "Ludhiana", "Patiala"],
    answer: "Khadur Sahib",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What percentage of Punjab's geographical area is covered by forests?",
    options: ["6%", "10%", "3%", "5%"],
    answer: "6%",
  },
  {
    question: "How much area of Punjab is covered by forests?",
    options: ["3058 sq.km", "2500 sq.km", "4000 sq.km", "3500 sq.km"],
    answer: "3058 sq.km",
  },
  {
    question: "Which districts of Punjab have the largest forest area?",
    options: [
      "Hoshiarpur, Ropar",
      "Ludhiana, Amritsar",
      "Bathinda, Patiala",
      "Fazilka, Mansa",
    ],
    answer: "Hoshiarpur, Ropar",
  },
  {
    question: "When is the monsoon withdrawal observed in Punjab?",
    options: ["September", "July", "October", "August"],
    answer: "September",
  },
  {
    question: "What is the cause of winter rainfall in Punjab?",
    options: [
      "Temperate cyclones",
      "Tropical cyclones",
      "Monsoon winds",
      "Western disturbances",
    ],
    answer: "Temperate cyclones",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Where do the cold winds causing frost and fog in Punjab originate from?",
    options: [
      "Caspian Sea and Turkmenistan",
      "Arabian Sea",
      "Himalayas",
      "Mediterranean Sea",
    ],
    answer: "Caspian Sea and Turkmenistan",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which river borders the districts of Amritsar, Pathankot, and Gurdaspur?",
    options: ["Ravi", "Beas", "Sutlej", "Chenab"],
    answer: "Ravi",
  },
  {
    question: "Which river in Punjab constitutes the largest catchment area?",
    options: ["Satluj", "Ravi", "Beas", "Chenab"],
    answer: "Satluj",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which landform in Punjab has been badly dissected with choes (chhote nale)?",
    options: ["Kandi", "Majha", "Malwa", "Doaba"],
    answer: "Kandi",
  },
  {
    question: "Sakki Kiran Nala is a tributary of which river?",
    options: ["Ravi", "Beas", "Sutlej", "Chenab"],
    answer: "Ravi",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Where does the Ravi River join the combined Jhelum and Chenab rivers?",
    options: ["Trimab", "Harike", "Kundli", "Sultanpur"],
    answer: "Trimab",
  },
  {
    question: "Parbati and Suketri are the tributaries of which river?",
    options: ["Beas", "Sutlej", "Ravi", "Chenab"],
    answer: "Beas",
  },
  {
    question: "What is the other name of the Satluj River?",
    options: ["Langchen Khambab", "Shinga Khamba", "Ravi", "Brahmaputra"],
    answer: "Langchen Khambab",
  },
  {
    question: "What is the other name of the Indus River?",
    options: ["Shinga Khamba", "Langchen Khambab", "Beas", "Sutlej"],
    answer: "Shinga Khamba",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following is a wetland of international importance (Ramsar site) in Punjab?",
    options: [
      "Beas Conservation Reserve",
      "Harike Lake",
      "Kanjli Lake",
      "All of the above",
    ],
    answer: "All of the above",
  },
  {
    question: "Which is the longest Ramsar site wetland in Punjab?",
    options: [
      "Beas Conservation Reserve",
      "Harike Lake",
      "Keshopur-Miani Community Reserve",
      "Ropar Lake",
    ],
    answer: "Beas Conservation Reserve",
  },
  {
    question: "Which Ramsar site wetland in Punjab is considered the oldest?",
    options: [
      "Harike Lake",
      "Beas Conservation Reserve",
      "Kanjli Lake",
      "Keshopur-Miani Community Reserve",
    ],
    answer: "Harike Lake",
  },
  {
    question: "Which Ramsar site is located in Kapurthala district?",
    options: [
      "Kanjli Lake",
      "Harike Lake",
      "Ropar Lake",
      "Nangal Wildlife Sanctuary",
    ],
    answer: "Kanjli Lake",
  },
  {
    question: "Which Ramsar site is located in Gurdaspur district?",
    options: [
      "Keshopur-Miani Community Reserve",
      "Nangal Wildlife Sanctuary",
      "Beas Conservation Reserve",
      "Ropar Lake",
    ],
    answer: "Keshopur-Miani Community Reserve",
  },
  {
    question: "Which Ramsar site is located in Ropar district?",
    options: [
      "Nangal Wildlife Sanctuary",
      "Ropar Lake",
      "Kanjli Lake",
      "Harike Lake",
    ],
    answer: "Nangal Wildlife Sanctuary",
  },
  {
    question: "Which river is associated with the Ropar Wetland in Punjab?",
    options: ["Satluj", "Beas", "Ravi", "Chenab"],
    answer: "Satluj",
  },
  {
    question: "Ranjit Sagar Wetland is located in which district of Punjab?",
    options: ["Pathankot", "Gurdaspur", "Amritsar", "Hoshiarpur"],
    answer: "Pathankot",
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following is a wetland located in Pathankot?",
    options: [
      "Ranjit Sagar Wetland",
      "Keshopur-Miani Community Reserve",
      "Harike Lake",
      "Kanjli Lake",
    ],
    answer: "Ranjit Sagar Wetland",
  },
  {
    question: "Where is Jastarwal Wetland located?",
    options: [
      "Ajnala, Amritsar",
      "Hoshiarpur, Ropar",
      "Ludhiana, Patiala",
      "Pathankot, Gurdaspur",
    ],
    answer: "Ajnala, Amritsar",
  },
  {
    question: "Which wetland is located in Gurdaspur district?",
    options: [
      "Kahnuwal Chamb Wetland",
      "Harike Lake",
      "Beas Conservation Reserve",
      "Kanjli Lake",
    ],
    answer: "Kahnuwal Chamb Wetland",
  },
  {
    question: "Where is Mand Bharthala Wetland located?",
    options: ["Nawanshahar", "Kapurthala", "Amritsar", "Pathankot"],
    answer: "Nawanshahar",
  },
  {
    question: "Which wetland is located in Kapurthala district?",
    options: ["Rababsar", "Ropar Lake", "Harike Lake", "Sital Sagar"],
    answer: "Rababsar",
  },
  {
    question: "Where is Sital Sagar Wetland located?",
    options: ["Hoshiarpur", "Amritsar", "Jalandhar", "Patiala"],
    answer: "Hoshiarpur",
  },
  {
    question: "Maily Dam is a manmade wetland in which district of Punjab?",
    options: ["Hoshiarpur", "Gurdaspur", "Patiala", "Ludhiana"],
    answer: "Hoshiarpur",
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following is a manmade wetland in Punjab?",
    options: [
      "Dholbaha Reservoir",
      "Sital Sagar",
      "Harike Lake",
      "Beas Conservation Reserve",
    ],
    answer: "Dholbaha Reservoir",
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following is a natural wetland in Punjab?",
    options: [
      "Sital Sagar",
      "Maily Dam",
      "Hussaainiwala Reservoir",
      "Mangrowal Dam",
    ],
    answer: "Sital Sagar",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Rakh Sarai Amanat Khan Conservation Reserve is located in which district of Punjab?",
    options: ["Tarn Taran", "Rupnagar", "Hoshiarpur", "Amritsar"],
    answer: "Tarn Taran",
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following is a conservation reserve in Punjab?",
    options: [
      "Rakh Sarai Amanat Khan",
      "Keshopur-Miani Community Reserve",
      "Harike Lake",
      "Rababsar",
    ],
    answer: "Rakh Sarai Amanat Khan",
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following is a community reserve in Punjab?",
    options: [
      "Keshopur-Chamb",
      "Ranjit Sagar Wetland",
      "Harike Lake",
      "Kanjli Lake",
    ],
    answer: "Keshopur-Chamb",
  },
  {
    question:
      "In which district is the Jhajjar-Bachauli Wildlife Sanctuary located?",
    options: ["Rupnagar", "Mansa", "Gurdaspur", "Hoshiarpur"],
    answer: "Rupnagar",
  },
  {
    question:
      "During which age did early man start manufacturing earthen jars?",
    options: [
      "Neolithic Age",
      "Mesolithic Age",
      "Paleolithic Age",
      "Bronze Age",
    ],
    answer: "Neolithic Age",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which type of soil is the most fertile and productive in Punjab?",
    options: [
      "Loamy Soil / Alluvial Soil",
      "Clay Soil",
      "Black Soil",
      "Saline Soil",
    ],
    answer: "Loamy Soil / Alluvial Soil",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following is a conservation reserve located along the Beas river in Punjab?",
    options: [
      "Beas Conservation Reserve",
      "Harike Lake",
      "Ranjit Sagar Wetland",
      "Sital Sagar",
    ],
    answer: "Beas Conservation Reserve",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following community reserves is located in Mohali district?",
    options: ["Siswan", "Keshopur-Miani", "Mand Bharthala", "Sital Sagar"],
    answer: "Siswan",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following is a conservation reserve located in Rupnagar district?",
    options: [
      "Ropar Conservation Reserve",
      "Beas Conservation Reserve",
      "Ranjit Sagar Wetland",
      "Harike Lake",
    ],
    answer: "Ropar Conservation Reserve",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following soils is found on the banks of rivers in Punjab?",
    options: ["Bet soils", "Sandy soils", "Loamy soils", "Kandi soils"],
    answer: "Bet soils",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following soils is found in areas bordering Rajasthan in Punjab?",
    options: ["Sandy soils", "Bet soils", "Loamy soils", "Sierozems soils"],
    answer: "Sandy soils",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which soil type is the most abundant in Punjab and is also known as Jalod Miti?",
    options: ["Loamy soils", "Kandi soils", "Sierozems soils", "Sandy soils"],
    answer: "Loamy soils",
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following is known as 'Khadar' in Punjab?",
    options: ["New Loamy soils", "Old Loamy soils", "Kandi soils", "Bet soils"],
    answer: "New Loamy soils",
  },
  {
    question: "Which type of soil in Punjab is known as 'Bangar'?",
    options: [
      "Old Loamy soils",
      "Kandi soils",
      "Sandy soils",
      "Sierozems soils",
    ],
    answer: "Old Loamy soils",
  },
  {
    question: "Kandi soils in Punjab are primarily found in which area?",
    options: [
      "Shivalik Hills",
      "Rajasthan border",
      "Malwa region",
      "Beas River banks",
    ],
    answer: "Shivalik Hills",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is the term for the area referred to as the Ghaggar Bet in Punjab?",
    options: ["Nalli area", "Kandi area", "Bet area", "Loamy area"],
    answer: "Nalli area",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which soil type is primarily found in the Malwa region of Punjab?",
    options: ["Sierozems soil", "Loamy soil", "Kandi soil", "Bet soil"],
    answer: "Sierozems soil",
  },
  {
    question: "Which soil type is deficient in organic matter in Punjab?",
    options: ["Sierozems", "Loamy soil", "Kandi soil", "Bet soil"],
    answer: "Sierozems",
  },
  {
    question: "Amloh tehsil falls in which district of Punjab?",
    options: ["Fatehgarh Sahib", "Mansa", "Ludhiana", "Sangrur"],
    answer: "Fatehgarh Sahib",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which city is known as the 'Manchester of India' and the financial capital of Punjab?",
    options: ["Ludhiana", "Amritsar", "Chandigarh", "Jalandhar"],
    answer: "Ludhiana",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which district of Punjab ranks first in both sex ratio and literacy rate?",
    options: ["Hoshiarpur", "Ludhiana", "Amritsar", "Sangrur"],
    answer: "Hoshiarpur",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Mansa district in Punjab is often referred to as the 'Bihar of Punjab.' What is its known attribute?",
    options: [
      "Mansa is known for agriculture and low literacy",
      "Mansa is a commercial hub",
      "Mansa is a historical district",
      "Mansa is known for its cultural significance",
    ],
    answer: "Mansa is known for agriculture and low literacy",
  },
  {
    question: "Sangrur district is often compared to which state in India?",
    options: ["Tamil Nadu", "Uttar Pradesh", "Bihar", "Kerala"],
    answer: "Tamil Nadu",
  },
  {
    question: "Batala tehsil is located in which district of Punjab?",
    options: ["Gurdaspur", "Amritsar", "Sangrur", "Mansa"],
    answer: "Gurdaspur",
  },
  {
    question: "Kalanaur and Qadian are located in which district of Punjab?",
    options: ["Gurdaspur", "Fatehgarh Sahib", "Amritsar", "Ludhiana"],
    answer: "Gurdaspur",
  },
  {
    question: "Akbar's tajposhi ceremony took place in which location?",
    options: ["Kalanaur", "Amritsar", "Sultanpur Lodhi", "Fatehgarh Sahib"],
    answer: "Kalanaur",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Mirza Gulam Ahmad, the founder of the Ahmadiyya sect, was born in which town?",
    options: ["Qadian", "Amritsar", "Ludhiana", "Chandigarh"],
    answer: "Qadian",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Ranjit Sagar Dam, also known as Thien Dam, is located in which district of Punjab?",
    options: ["Pathankot", "Sangrur", "Jalandhar", "Gurdaspur"],
    answer: "Pathankot",
  },
  {
    question: "Which district of Punjab has shown the least decadal growth?",
    options: ["SBS Nagar (Nawanshahar)", "Amritsar", "Hoshiarpur", "Ludhiana"],
    answer: "SBS Nagar (Nawanshahar)",
  },
  {
    question: "Which district of Punjab has shown the highest decadal growth?",
    options: ["SAS Nagar (Mohali)", "Amritsar", "Ludhiana", "Patiala"],
    answer: "SAS Nagar (Mohali)",
  },
  {
    question: "Kharar and Dera Bassi are tehsils of which district in Punjab?",
    options: ["SAS Nagar", "Pathankot", "Amritsar", "Ludhiana"],
    answer: "SAS Nagar",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Where has the Borlaug Institute of South Asia (BISA) been set up?",
    options: ["Ludhiana", "Patiala", "Chandigarh", "Amritsar"],
    answer: "Ludhiana",
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following is an archaeological site in Punjab?",
    options: ["Dher Majra", "Amritsar", "Ludhiana", "Jalandhar"],
    answer: "Dher Majra",
  },
  {
    question: "Kheti Bhawan has been set up in which town of Punjab?",
    options: ["Ajitgarh (Mohali)", "Chandigarh", "Ludhiana", "Amritsar"],
    answer: "Ajitgarh (Mohali)",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which center of excellence for citrus has been established in collaboration with the Government of Israel?",
    options: ["Khanauri, Hoshiarpur", "Amritsar", "Patiala", "Ludhiana"],
    answer: "Khanauri, Hoshiarpur",
  },
  {
    question: "India and Israel jointly developed a missile named:",
    options: ["Barak", "Agni", "Nirbhay", "Brahmos"],
    answer: "Barak",
  },
  {
    question:
      "A center of excellence for potato has been set up in which city of Punjab?",
    options: ["Jalandhar", "Amritsar", "Ludhiana", "Pathankot"],
    answer: "Jalandhar",
  },
  {
    question: "Devi Talab Mandir is located in which city of Punjab?",
    options: ["Jalandhar", "Patiala", "Amritsar", "Ludhiana"],
    answer: "Jalandhar",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Where has the Lichi Estate been established by Punjab Government?",
    options: ["Gurdaspur", "Amritsar", "Ludhiana", "Jalandhar"],
    answer: "Gurdaspur",
  },
  {
    question: "What is the main source of irrigation in Punjab?",
    options: ["Tubewells (71%)", "Canals", "Rainwater harvesting", "Rivers"],
    answer: "Tubewells (71%)",
  },
  {
    question:
      "When was the Punjab State Electricity Board (PSEB) unbundled into Punjab State Power Corporation Limited (PSPCL) and Punjab State Transmission Corporation Limited (PSTCL)?",
    options: [
      "16 April 2010",
      "1 January 2005",
      "25 December 2000",
      "14 August 2015",
    ],
    answer: "16 April 2010",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Where is the headquarters of the Punjab State Electricity Board (PSEB) located?",
    options: ["Patiala", "Chandigarh", "Amritsar", "Ludhiana"],
    answer: "Patiala",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who is the Chairman and Managing Director of Punjab State Electricity Board (PSEB)?",
    options: [
      "Er. Baldev Singh Sran",
      "Dr. Jagdeep Singh",
      "Er. Harpreet Singh",
      "Mr. Gurpreet Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Er. Baldev Singh Sran",
  },
  {
    question: "Which is the oldest thermal power plant in Punjab?",
    options: [
      "Guru Nanak Thermal Plant, Bathinda",
      "Rajpura Thermal Power Plant",
      "Talwandi Sabo Power Project",
      "Goindwal Sahib Power Plant",
    ],
    answer: "Guru Nanak Thermal Plant, Bathinda",
  },
  {
    question: "Which thermal power plant in Punjab has the highest capacity?",
    options: [
      "Talwandi Sabo Power Project, Mansa (1980 MW)",
      "Guru Nanak Thermal Plant, Bathinda",
      "Rajpura Thermal Power Plant, Rajpura",
      "Goindwal Sahib Power Plant",
    ],
    answer: "Talwandi Sabo Power Project, Mansa (1980 MW)",
  },
  {
    question: "Which thermal power plants are located in Punjab?",
    options: [
      "Guru Nanak Dev Thermal Plant, Bathinda, Rajpura Thermal Power Plant, Talwandi Sabo Power Project, Guru Gobind Singh Super Thermal Power Plant, Guru Hargobind Thermal Plant, Goindwal Sahib Power Plant",
      "Guru Nanak Dev Thermal Plant, Bathinda, Ropar Thermal Plant, Nangal Power Plant",
      "Patiala Thermal Power Plant, Rajpura Thermal Power Plant",
      "Guru Gobind Singh Super Thermal Power Plant, Ropar, Goindwal Sahib Power Plant",
    ],
    answer:
      "Guru Nanak Dev Thermal Plant, Bathinda, Rajpura Thermal Power Plant, Talwandi Sabo Power Project, Guru Gobind Singh Super Thermal Power Plant, Guru Hargobind Thermal Plant, Goindwal Sahib Power Plant",
  },
  {
    question: "Which river feeds the Mukerian Hydel Project?",
    options: ["River Beas", "River Ravi", "River Sutlej", "River Chenab"],
    answer: "River Beas",
  },
  {
    question: "Which river feeds the Mukerian Canal?",
    options: ["River Beas", "River Ravi", "River Sutlej", "River Chenab"],
    answer: "River Beas",
  },
  {
    question: "Which area is fed by the Mukerian Canal?",
    options: ["Doaba", "Majha", "Majha and Malwa", "Doaba and Majha"],
    answer: "Doaba",
  },
  {
    question: "The Upper Bari Doab Canal draws water from which river?",
    options: ["River Ravi", "River Beas", "River Sutlej", "River Chenab"],
    answer: "River Ravi",
  },
  {
    question: "Which area is fed by the Upper Bari Doab Canal?",
    options: ["Majha", "Doaba", "Majha and Doaba", "Malwa"],
    answer: "Majha",
  },
  {
    question: "Where is the Sanan Power House, owned by Punjab State, located?",
    options: ["Himachal Pradesh", "Punjab", "Uttarakhand", "Jammu and Kashmir"],
    answer: "Himachal Pradesh",
  },
  {
    question: "Where is the Pushpa Gujral Science City located?",
    options: ["Kapurthala", "Amritsar", "Jalandhar", "Patiala"],
    answer: "Kapurthala",
  },
  {
    question: "Who founded the city of Kapurthala?",
    options: [
      "Rana Kapur",
      "Maharaja Jagatjit Singh",
      "Rana Bahram",
      "Rana Bahadur",
    ],
    answer: "Rana Kapur",
  },
  {
    question: "Where is the Sainik School in Kapurthala located?",
    options: [
      "Jagatjit Palace",
      "Kapurthala Fort",
      "Kanjli Wetlands",
      "Shalimar Garden",
    ],
    answer: "Jagatjit Palace",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following is a replica of the Grand Mosque of Marrakesh, Morocco?",
    options: [
      "Moorish Mosque",
      "Shalimar Garden",
      "Panch Mandir",
      "Brahmkund Mandir",
    ],
    answer: "Moorish Mosque",
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following is a significant landmark in Kapurthala?",
    options: ["Moorish Mosque", "Taj Mahal", "Golden Temple", "Red Fort"],
    answer: "Moorish Mosque",
  },
  {
    question: "Which wetland is located in Kapurthala?",
    options: [
      "Kanjli Wetlands",
      "Harike Wetlands",
      "Sultanpur Wetlands",
      "Ropar Wetlands",
    ],
    answer: "Kanjli Wetlands",
  },
  {
    question: "Which is a major industry in Kapurthala?",
    options: [
      "Rail Coach Factory",
      "Textile Industry",
      "Sugar Mills",
      "Paper Mills",
    ],
    answer: "Rail Coach Factory",
  },
  {
    question: "Which state is the largest wheat producer in India?",
    options: ["Uttar Pradesh", "Punjab", "Haryana", "Madhya Pradesh"],
    answer: "Uttar Pradesh",
  },
  {
    question: "Which place is also known as Guru Ki Kashi?",
    options: [
      "Takht Sri Damdama Sahib, Talwandi Sabo",
      "Sri Harmandir Sahib, Amritsar",
      "Sri Akal Takht Sahib, Amritsar",
      "Takht Sri Patna Sahib",
    ],
    answer: "Takht Sri Damdama Sahib, Talwandi Sabo",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Bhaini Sahib Gurudwara in Ludhiana district is related to which movement?",
    options: [
      "Namdhari Movement",
      "Arya Samaj Movement",
      "Sikh Reform Movement",
      "Rama Krishna Mission",
    ],
    answer: "Namdhari Movement",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following characteristics are true for the Kandi area of Punjab?",
    options: [
      "Sub-mountainous undulating terrain, lack of perennial water source, high cost of cultivation, low fertile land",
      "Flat terrain, abundant water sources, high fertility",
      "High altitude with cold climate, fertile soil",
      "Highly urbanized with high agriculture productivity",
    ],
    answer:
      "Sub-mountainous undulating terrain, lack of perennial water source, high cost of cultivation, low fertile land",
  },
  {
    question:
      "As per the 2011 census, which of the following districts has the highest population density in Punjab?",
    options: ["Ludhiana", "Amritsar", "Patiala", "Jalandhar"],
    answer: "Ludhiana",
  },
  {
    question:
      "According to the 2011 census, the population of Punjab increased from 2.44 crores to what in 2011?",
    options: ["2.77 crores", "3.02 crores", "2.55 crores", "2.80 crores"],
    answer: "2.77 crores",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following is a reason for the sluggish growth in the agriculture sector in Punjab?",
    options: [
      "Per acre yield of crops has peaked, decreased land holdings, increased dependence on ground water",
      "Increase in crop diversity, use of modern technology",
      "Rise in exports of agricultural products, increased mechanization",
      "Government policies promoting organic farming",
    ],
    answer:
      "Per acre yield of crops has peaked, decreased land holdings, increased dependence on ground water",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Where was the stock exchange located before it was removed in Punjab?",
    options: ["Ludhiana", "Amritsar", "Patiala", "Jalandhar"],
    answer: "Ludhiana",
  },
  {
    question: "The Beas River originates from which location?",
    options: [
      "Beas Kund, Rohtang, Kullu Manali Mountains",
      "Satluj River, Shivalik Hills",
      "Chenab River, Jammu and Kashmir",
      "Jhelum River, Himalayas",
    ],
    answer: "Beas Kund, Rohtang, Kullu Manali Mountains",
  },
  {
    question: "Which reservoirs are built over the Beas River?",
    options: [
      "Pandoh and Pong Reservoir",
      "Ranjit Sagar and Harike Reservoir",
      "Bhakra and Nangal Reservoir",
      "Chamera and Koldam Reservoir",
    ],
    answer: "Pandoh and Pong Reservoir",
  },
  {
    question: "Which river joins the Beas at Hari-Ke-Pattan?",
    options: ["Satluj River", "Chenab River", "Ravi River", "Jhelum River"],
    answer: "Satluj River",
  },
  {
    question: "What was the Vedic name of the Beas River?",
    options: ["Vipasa", "Parushni", "Aksini", "Vitasta"],
    answer: "Vipasa",
  },
  {
    question: "Which wildlife sanctuary is located in Rupnagar district?",
    options: [
      "Jhajjar Bachauli",
      "Kathalaur Kushlian",
      "Bir Aishwan",
      "Bir Dosanjh",
    ],
    answer: "Jhajjar Bachauli",
  },
  {
    question: "Which wildlife sanctuary is located in Pathankot district?",
    options: [
      "Kathalaur Kushlian",
      "Bir Aishwan",
      "Bir Dosanjh",
      "Jhajjar Bachauli",
    ],
    answer: "Kathalaur Kushlian",
  },
  {
    question: "Which wildlife sanctuary is located in Sangrur district?",
    options: [
      "Bir Aishwan",
      "Bir Dosanjh",
      "Kathalaur Kushlian",
      "Jhajjar Bachauli",
    ],
    answer: "Bir Aishwan",
  },
  {
    question: "Which wildlife sanctuary is located in Patiala district?",
    options: [
      "Bir Dosanjh",
      "Bir Aishwan",
      "Kathalaur Kushlian",
      "Jhajjar Bachauli",
    ],
    answer: "Bir Dosanjh",
  },
  {
    question: "The Chatrik/Pong Dam is built on which river?",
    options: ["Beas River", "Ravi River", "Satluj River", "Chenab River"],
    answer: "Beas River",
  },
  {
    question: "Which district in Punjab has the highest female literacy rate?",
    options: ["Hoshiarpur", "Patiala", "Amritsar", "Ludhiana"],
    answer: "Hoshiarpur",
  },
  {
    question: "Which district falls under the Central Plain Agro-climate zone?",
    options: ["Jalandhar", "Moga", "Ferozepur", "Bathinda"],
    answer: "Jalandhar",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following is a district in the Sub-mountain Undulating Agro-climate zone?",
    options: ["Hoshiarpur", "Ludhiana", "Faridkot", "Patiala"],
    answer: "Hoshiarpur",
  },
  {
    question: "Which district is in the Western Zone Agro-climate zone?",
    options: ["Moga", "Faridkot", "Ferozepur", "Tarn Taran"],
    answer: "Moga",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following is in the Western Plain Zone Agro-climate zone?",
    options: ["Ferozepur", "Jalandhar", "Barnala", "Sangrur"],
    answer: "Ferozepur",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following districts is in the Central Plain Agro-climate zone?",
    options: ["Tarn Taran", "Mansa", "Muktsar", "Patiala"],
    answer: "Tarn Taran",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which districts are part of the Central Plain Agro-climate zone? (Select all that apply)",
    options: [
      "Amritsar, Fatehgarh Sahib, Jalandhar, Kapurthala, Ludhiana, Patiala, Tarn Taran",
      "Faridkot, Ferozepur",
      "Moga, Bathinda, Mansa",
      "Jalandhar, Moga, Ludhiana",
    ],
    answer:
      "Amritsar, Fatehgarh Sahib, Jalandhar, Kapurthala, Ludhiana, Patiala, Tarn Taran",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following districts are part of the Western Zone Agro-climate zone? (Select all that apply)",
    options: [
      "Barnala, Bathinda, Mansa, Moga, Muktsar, Sangrur",
      "Amritsar, Fatehgarh Sahib",
      "Faridkot, Ferozepur",
      "Tarn Taran, Patiala",
    ],
    answer: "Barnala, Bathinda, Mansa, Moga, Muktsar, Sangrur",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following is true about the Western Plain Zone Agro-climate zone?",
    options: [
      "It includes districts like Faridkot and Ferozepur",
      "It includes Ludhiana and Amritsar",
      "It has the highest agricultural productivity",
      "It is known for high-tech industries",
    ],
    answer: "It includes districts like Faridkot and Ferozepur",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following districts is in the Sub-mountain Undulating Agro-climate zone?",
    options: ["Gurdaspur", "Moga", "Faridkot", "Ferozepur"],
    answer: "Gurdaspur",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following districts is part of the Undulating Plain Agro-climate zone?",
    options: ["Mohali", "Amritsar", "Patiala", "Jalandhar"],
    answer: "Mohali",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following hydropower projects is located on the Chenab River?",
    options: [
      "Baglihar Hydropower Project",
      "Dulhasti Hydropower Project",
      "Salal Hydropower Project",
      "All of the above",
    ],
    answer: "All of the above",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following details are correct about Bhagat Puran Singh, the founder of Pingalwara?",
    options: [
      "Real name - Ramji Das, Born on June 4, 1904, in Rajewal, Ludhiana; Died on August 4, 1992, in Amritsar; Movie - Eh Janam Tumhare Lekhe",
      "Real name - Bhagat Singh, Born on March 23, 1907, in Punjab; Died in 1931; Movie - The Legend of Bhagat Singh",
      "Real name - Ramji Das, Born on July 1, 1910, in Amritsar; Died on January 1, 1995, in Ludhiana",
      "Real name - Bhagat Puran, Born in 1910 in Jalandhar; Died on July 4, 1990, in Amritsar",
    ],
    answer:
      "Real name - Ramji Das, Born on June 4, 1904, in Rajewal, Ludhiana; Died on August 4, 1992, in Amritsar; Movie - Eh Janam Tumhare Lekhe",
  },
  {
    question: "At which fair are donkeys specially decorated?",
    options: ["Jarag Da Mela", "Baisakhi Mela", "Lohri Mela", "Dussehra Mela"],
    answer: "Jarag Da Mela",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following is a notable feature of the Jarag Da Mela in Ludhiana?",
    options: [
      "Donkeys are specially decorated",
      "Worship of Goddess Durga",
      "Horse races",
      "Traditional wrestling matches",
    ],
    answer: "Donkeys are specially decorated",
  },
  {
    question:
      "In which month and day is the Sitala Mata Mela held in Ludhiana?",
    options: [
      "First Tuesday of Chetra month",
      "First Friday of Baisakhi month",
      "Last Monday of December",
      "First Sunday of March",
    ],
    answer: "First Tuesday of Chetra month",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is the special prasada offered at the Sitala Mata Mela in Ludhiana?",
    options: ["Gul-gule", "Pinni", "Langar", "Kheer"],
    answer: "Gul-gule",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following fairs is held in Ludhiana in Bhadoon month on the 14th day of the full moon night?",
    options: [
      "Chhapar Da Mela",
      "Gugga Jaharveer Mela",
      "Jagrawan Di Roshni Mela",
      "Sitala Mata Mela",
    ],
    answer: "Gugga Jaharveer Mela",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Where is the Gurudwara Mal Akhara Sahib located and what is its significance?",
    options: [
      "Anandpur Sahib, known as the family of Guru Angad Dev Ji",
      "Amritsar, birthplace of Guru Arjan Dev Ji",
      "Patiala, related to Guru Gobind Singh Ji",
      "Ludhiana, dedicated to Guru Nanak Dev Ji",
    ],
    answer: "Anandpur Sahib, known as the family of Guru Angad Dev Ji",
  },
  {
    question: "Where is the Virasat-e-Khalsa museum situated?",
    options: ["Anandpur Sahib", "Amritsar", "Patiala", "Jalandhar"],
    answer: "Anandpur Sahib",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The National Martyrs Memorial, Hussainiwala, is located in which district of Punjab?",
    options: ["Ferozepur", "Ludhiana", "Amritsar", "Moga"],
    answer: "Ferozepur",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The Ranjit Sagar Dam (Thein Dam) is located in which district of Punjab?",
    options: ["Pathankot", "Amritsar", "Ferozepur", "Jalandhar"],
    answer: "Pathankot",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which city in Punjab is popular for furniture goods manufacturing?",
    options: ["Kartarpur", "Ludhiana", "Amritsar", "Jalandhar"],
    answer: "Kartarpur",
  },
  {
    question: "The Salal Hydropower Project is located on which river?",
    options: ["Chenab", "Beas", "Ravi", "Sutlej"],
    answer: "Chenab",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The Chandra and Bhaga rivers from Jammu combine to form which river?",
    options: ["Chenab", "Ravi", "Jhelum", "Sutlej"],
    answer: "Chenab",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The floodplains of Punjab, known as Khaddar, are called which of the following?",
    options: ["Bet", "Bhar", "Taksal", "Nalli"],
    answer: "Bet",
  },
  {
    question: "The area of Ghaggar Bet is called which area?",
    options: ["Nalli", "Sarai", "Chadar", "Shikarpur"],
    answer: "Nalli",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Scheduled castes are not present in which of the following regions?",
    options: [
      "Lakshadweep and Nagaland",
      "Goa and Sikkim",
      "Jammu & Kashmir and Ladakh",
      "Kerala and Mizoram",
    ],
    answer: "Lakshadweep and Nagaland",
  },
  {
    question: "Jalandhar city is famous for which industry?",
    options: [
      "Sports goods manufacturing",
      "Textiles",
      "Automobiles",
      "Handicrafts",
    ],
    answer: "Sports goods manufacturing",
  },
  {
    question: "What was the old name of Jalandhar city?",
    options: ["Trigarta", "Suryapur", "Nagarkot", "Rajasthan"],
    answer: "Trigarta",
  },
  {
    question: "Where is the Fateh Burj-Chappar Chiri Memorial located?",
    options: ["SAS Nagar (Mohali)", "Patiala", "Jalandhar", "Amritsar"],
    answer: "SAS Nagar (Mohali)",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following is true about the Fateh Burj-Chappar Chiri Memorial?",
    options: [
      "It is the tallest minar in India, standing 328 feet tall",
      "It was built to commemorate the victory at Anandpur Sahib",
      "It marks the site of Guru Gobind Singh Ji's last battle",
      "It is located in Ferozepur",
    ],
    answer: "It is the tallest minar in India, standing 328 feet tall",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The Fateh Burj-Chappar Chiri Memorial was built as a memorial to the victory of which Sikh leader?",
    options: [
      "Banda Singh Bahadur",
      "Guru Gobind Singh Ji",
      "Maharaja Ranjit Singh",
      "Guru Tegh Bahadur Ji",
    ],
    answer: "Banda Singh Bahadur",
  },
  {
    question: "The Rachna Doab lies between which two rivers?",
    options: [
      "Ravi and Chenab",
      "Chenab and Sutlej",
      "Beas and Sutlej",
      "Jhelum and Chenab",
    ],
    answer: "Ravi and Chenab",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following Doabs lies between the Indus and Jhelum rivers?",
    options: ["Indus Sagar Doab", "Chaj Doab", "Rachna Doab", "Bist Doab"],
    answer: "Indus Sagar Doab",
  },
  {
    question: "The Chaj Doab lies between which two rivers?",
    options: [
      "Jhelum and Chenab",
      "Chenab and Ravi",
      "Ravi and Beas",
      "Beas and Sutlej",
    ],
    answer: "Jhelum and Chenab",
  },
  {
    question: "Which Doab lies between the Beas and Sutlej rivers?",
    options: ["Bist Doab", "Cis-Satluj Doab", "Bari Doab", "Indus Sagar Doab"],
    answer: "Bist Doab",
  },
  {
    question: "The Cis-Satluj Doab lies between which two rivers?",
    options: [
      "Sutlej and Ghaggar",
      "Sutlej and Beas",
      "Beas and Ravi",
      "Chenab and Sutlej",
    ],
    answer: "Sutlej and Ghaggar",
  },
  {
    question: "The Delhi Doab lies between which two rivers?",
    options: [
      "Ghaggar and Yamuna",
      "Ravi and Beas",
      "Sutlej and Beas",
      "Jhelum and Chenab",
    ],
    answer: "Ghaggar and Yamuna",
  },
  {
    question: "Which states does Punjab share its borders with?",
    options: [
      "Haryana, Himachal Pradesh, Rajasthan",
      "Haryana, Jammu & Kashmir, Himachal Pradesh",
      "Rajasthan, Jammu & Kashmir, Uttar Pradesh",
      "Himachal Pradesh, Delhi, Uttar Pradesh",
    ],
    answer: "Haryana, Himachal Pradesh, Rajasthan",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following districts in Punjab shares a border with Pakistan?",
    options: ["Pathankot", "Chandigarh", "SAS Nagar", "Faridkot"],
    answer: "Pathankot",
  },
  {
    question: "How many districts in Punjab share a border with Pakistan?",
    options: ["6", "5", "4", "3"],
    answer: "6",
  },
  {
    question: "Which district in Punjab shares its border with Haryana?",
    options: ["Ferozepur", "Gurdaspur", "Pathankot", "Tarn Taran"],
    answer: "Ferozepur",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which two districts in Punjab share their borders with Rajasthan?",
    options: [
      "Fazilka and Muktsar Sahib",
      "Amritsar and Tarn Taran",
      "Gurdaspur and Pathankot",
      "Ludhiana and Moga",
    ],
    answer: "Fazilka and Muktsar Sahib",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which district in Punjab shares its border with Jammu & Kashmir?",
    options: ["Pathankot", "Amritsar", "Fazilka", "SAS Nagar"],
    answer: "Pathankot",
  },
  {
    question: "Which district in Punjab shares its border with Chandigarh?",
    options: ["SAS Nagar (Mohali)", "Ludhiana", "Jalandhar", "Amritsar"],
    answer: "SAS Nagar (Mohali)",
  },
  {
    question: "The Sirhind Canal carries water from which river?",
    options: ["Sutlej", "Beas", "Chenab", "Ravi"],
    answer: "Sutlej",
  },
  {
    question: "The Dehar Power House is associated with which project?",
    options: ["Pandoh Dam", "Baglihar Dam", "Chamera Dam", "Nangal Dam"],
    answer: "Pandoh Dam",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the creator of the Rock Garden?",
    options: [
      "Nek Chand Saini",
      "Gurbachan Singh",
      "Manjeet Singh",
      "Sukhdev Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Nek Chand Saini",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Where is the confluence of the Beas and Sutlej rivers located in Punjab?",
    options: [
      "Harike Wetland",
      "Kanjli Wetlands",
      "Ropar Wetland",
      "Sultanpur Lodhi",
    ],
    answer: "Harike Wetland",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Hazur Sahib, the holy Sikh pilgrimage, is located on the banks of which river?",
    options: ["Godavari", "Ganges", "Yamuna", "Krishna"],
    answer: "Godavari",
  },
  {
    question: "Which river is referred to as 'Dakshin Ki Ganga'?",
    options: ["Kaveri", "Narmada", "Godavari", "Krishna"],
    answer: "Kaveri",
  },
  {
    question: "Which is the first notified wildlife sanctuary in Punjab?",
    options: [
      "Bir Aishwan",
      "Jhajjar Bachauli",
      "Khadar Takar",
      "Harike Wetland",
    ],
    answer: "Bir Aishwan",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which architect is associated with the design of Virasat-e-Khalsa?",
    options: [
      "Moshe Safdie",
      "B.V. Doshi",
      "Charles Correa",
      "Pierre Jeanneret",
    ],
    answer: "Moshe Safdie",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following rivers were India allowed to use under the Indus Water Treaty of 1960?",
    options: [
      "Satluj, Beas, Ravi",
      "Chenab, Jhelum, Ravi",
      "Beas, Sutlej, Ghaggar",
      "Ravi, Jhelum, Satluj",
    ],
    answer: "Satluj, Beas, Ravi",
  },
  {
    question:
      "In which year was the Indus Water Treaty between India and Pakistan signed?",
    options: ["1960", "1956", "1972", "1950"],
    answer: "1960",
  },
  {
    question: "What is the largest city of Punjab?",
    options: ["Ludhiana", "Amritsar", "Chandigarh", "Jalandhar"],
    answer: "Ludhiana",
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following pairs is correctly matched?",
    options: [
      "Harike - Punjab, Nokrek - Meghalaya, Ranthambore - Rajasthan, Gir - Gujarat",
      "Harike - Rajasthan, Nokrek - Punjab, Ranthambore - Gujarat, Gir - Meghalaya",
      "Harike - Gujarat, Nokrek - Punjab, Ranthambore - Rajasthan, Gir - Punjab",
      "Harike - Haryana, Nokrek - Rajasthan, Ranthambore - Gujarat, Gir - Punjab",
    ],
    answer:
      "Harike - Punjab, Nokrek - Meghalaya, Ranthambore - Rajasthan, Gir - Gujarat",
  },
  {
    question: "Where can Asiatic lions only be found?",
    options: ["Gir", "Ranthambore", "Kaziranga", "Sundarbans"],
    answer: "Gir",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which city is known for being the biggest grain market in Punjab?",
    options: ["Khanna", "Ludhiana", "Jalandhar", "Amritsar"],
    answer: "Khanna",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which district in Punjab is the most flood-prone due to the Ghaggar's Bet (Nalli area)?",
    options: ["Patiala", "Ferozepur", "Gurdaspur", "Ludhiana"],
    answer: "Patiala",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Although Punjab constitutes only 1.54% of India's geographical area, nearly how much of India's foodgrains are procured annually from the state?",
    options: ["2/3rd", "1/2", "3/4th", "1/4th"],
    answer: "2/3rd",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following thermal power plants is located in Punjab?",
    options: [
      "Ropar Thermal Plant",
      "Dharamsala Thermal Plant",
      "Nandini Thermal Plant",
      "Bathinda Thermal Plant",
    ],
    answer: "Ropar Thermal Plant",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following projects is associated with energy generation in Punjab?",
    options: [
      "Bhakra Nangal Project",
      "Narmada Valley Project",
      "Mahanadi Hydroelectric Project",
      "Kaveri River Project",
    ],
    answer: "Bhakra Nangal Project",
  },
  {
    question: "What type of climate is prevalent in Punjab?",
    options: [
      "Sub-tropical type",
      "Tropical type",
      "Temperate type",
      "Arid type",
    ],
    answer: "Sub-tropical type",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What percentage of India's total fertilizer consumption is used by Punjab?",
    options: ["9%", "15%", "5%", "12%"],
    answer: "9%",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What are the hot blowing winds called before monsoons arrive in Punjab?",
    options: ["Loo", "Khamsin", "Sirocco", "Mistral"],
    answer: "Loo",
  },
  {
    question: "Where are Chinook winds found?",
    options: ["USA", "India", "Australia", "Canada"],
    answer: "USA",
  },
  {
    question: "Where is Hari-ke Pattan located?",
    options: ["Tarn Taran", "Patiala", "Ludhiana", "Amritsar"],
    answer: "Tarn Taran",
  },
  {
    question: "In which district is Bansar Garden located?",
    options: ["Sangrur", "Ludhiana", "Bathinda", "Fatehgarh Sahib"],
    answer: "Sangrur",
  },
  {
    question: "Which historical site is located in Sirhind?",
    options: [
      "Aam Khas Bagh",
      "Bansar Garden",
      "Shalimar Bagh",
      "Harmandir Sahib",
    ],
    answer: "Aam Khas Bagh",
  },
  {
    question: "Shalimar Bagh is located in which district of Punjab?",
    options: ["Kapurthala", "Amritsar", "Patiala", "Jalandhar"],
    answer: "Kapurthala",
  },
  {
    question: "How many Lok Sabha seats does Punjab have?",
    options: ["13", "15", "10", "12"],
    answer: "13",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is the literacy rate of Punjab according to the 2011 census?",
    options: ["75.84%", "80.50%", "70.20%", "60.10%"],
    answer: "75.84%",
  },
  {
    question: "What is the sex ratio of Punjab according to the 2011 census?",
    options: ["895", "920", "850", "910"],
    answer: "895",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is the urbanization ratio of Punjab according to the 2011 census?",
    options: ["25.90%", "30.20%", "22.50%", "18.10%"],
    answer: "25.90%",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What percentage of the geographical area of Punjab is under forest?",
    options: ["2-3%", "4-5%", "1-2%", "3-4%"],
    answer: "2-3%",
  },
  {
    question: "Why is Ludhiana called the 'Manchester of India'?",
    options: [
      "Because of its industrialization or textile industry",
      "Because of its historical significance",
      "Because of its agricultural productivity",
      "Because of its IT sector",
    ],
    answer: "Because of its industrialization or textile industry",
  },
  {
    question: "Which city is known as the 'Manchester of India'?",
    options: ["Ahmedabad", "Ludhiana", "Mumbai", "Kolkata"],
    answer: "Ahmedabad",
  },
  {
    question: "What percentage of the world's cotton is produced by Punjab?",
    options: ["2%", "5%", "1%", "4%"],
    answer: "2%",
  },
  {
    question: "What percentage of the world's wheat is produced by Punjab?",
    options: ["2%", "5%", "1%", "3%"],
    answer: "2%",
  },
  {
    question: "What percentage of the world's rice is produced by Punjab?",
    options: ["1%", "2%", "3%", "4%"],
    answer: "1%",
  },
  {
    question: "How many civil aviation clubs are there in Punjab?",
    options: ["3", "4", "5", "2"],
    answer: "3",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following districts of Punjab had the highest literacy rate in 2001?",
    options: ["Hoshiarpur", "Jalandhar", "Mansa", "Roopnagar"],
    answer: "Hoshiarpur",
  },
  {
    question: "Which seismic zones are present in Punjab?",
    options: ["2, 3, 4", "3, 4, 5", "1, 2, 3", "2, 3, 5"],
    answer: "2, 3, 4",
  },
  {
    question: "What is the average annual rainfall in Punjab?",
    options: [
      "960 mm in sub-mountain region, 460 mm in plains",
      "800 mm in sub-mountain region, 400 mm in plains",
      "1000 mm in sub-mountain region, 500 mm in plains",
      "1200 mm in sub-mountain region, 600 mm in plains",
    ],
    answer: "960 mm in sub-mountain region, 460 mm in plains",
  },
  {
    question: "Until which year did the Mughals control the region of Punjab?",
    options: [
      "1739 (Battle of Karnal)",
      "1689 (Battle of Samugarh)",
      "1705 (Battle of Anandpur)",
      "1757 (Battle of Plassey)",
    ],
    answer: "1739 (Battle of Karnal)",
  },
  {
    question: "In which year did Chandigarh become a separate union territory?",
    options: ["1966", "1956", "1970", "1960"],
    answer: "1966",
  },
  {
    question: "What did the Anandpur Sahib resolution ask for?",
    options: [
      "Maximum autonomy to Punjab and other states",
      "Separation from India",
      "Strengthening of central government powers",
      "Economic reforms in Punjab",
    ],
    answer: "Maximum autonomy to Punjab and other states",
  },
  {
    question: "What is the approximate percentage of Sikhs in Punjab?",
    options: ["58%", "65%", "50%", "75%"],
    answer: "58%",
  },
  {
    question: "Where has the Central University of Punjab been set up?",
    options: ["Bathinda", "Amritsar", "Ludhiana", "Patiala"],
    answer: "Bathinda",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following is a jewelry item worn on the head by women in Punjab?",
    options: ["ਚੋਂਕ", "ਚੰਦਨਹਾਰ", "ਬੋਹਰ", "ਪਹੁੰਚਿਆ"],
    answer: "ਚੋਂਕ",
  },
  {
    question: "Which jewelry item is worn on the forehead by women in Punjab?",
    options: ["ਦਾਮਿਨੀ", "ਕਸ਼ਕਾ", "ਭਰਵੱਟਾ", "ਨੋਲਖਾ ਹਾਰ"],
    answer: "ਦਾਮਿਨੀ",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following is a type of earring worn by women in Punjab?",
    options: ["ਧੇੰਦੂ", "ਪਹੁੰਚਿਆ", "ਪ੍ਰਸਾਦੀ", "ਬਾਂਕਾ"],
    answer: "ਧੇੰਦੂ",
  },
  {
    question: "Which jewelry item is worn around the neck by women in Punjab?",
    options: ["ਚੰਦਨਹਾਰ", "ਫੁੱਲੀ", "ਬੋਹਰ", "ਨੋਲਖਾ ਹਾਰ"],
    answer: "ਚੰਦਨਹਾਰ",
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following is a nose ring worn by women in Punjab?",
    options: ["ਬੂੱਲਕ", "ਪਹੁੰਚਿਆ", "ਬਾਂਕਾ", "ਫੁੰਮ੍ਹੀ"],
    answer: "ਬੂੱਲਕ",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which jewelry item is a type of bracelet worn by women in Punjab?",
    options: ["ਬੇਈੰ", "ਛੰਨਕੰਗਣ", "ਮੋਹਰਾਂ", "ਕੰਟਾਲਾ"],
    answer: "ਛੰਨਕੰਗਣ",
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following is worn as an ornament on the hair?",
    options: ["ਚੋਂਕ", "ਨੋਲਖਾ ਹਾਰ", "ਹੱਸ", "ਫੁੰਮ੍ਹੀ"],
    answer: "ਚੋਂਕ",
  },
  {
    question: "What is the name of the bracelet worn by women in Punjab?",
    options: ["ਬੇਈੰ", "ਛੰਨਕੰਗਣ", "ਪਹੁੰਚਿਆ", "ਬਾਂਕਾ"],
    answer: "ਬੇਈੰ",
  },
  {
    question: "ਚੋਂਕ is worn on which part of the body?",
    options: ["Head", "Neck", "Wrist", "Foot"],
    answer: "Head",
  },
  {
    question: "ਮੋਲੀ is worn on which part of the body?",
    options: ["Head", "Neck", "Wrist", "Foot"],
    answer: "Head",
  },
  {
    question: "ਦਾਮਿਨੀ is worn on which part of the body?",
    options: ["Forehead", "Neck", "Wrist", "Foot"],
    answer: "Forehead",
  },
  {
    question: "ਭਰਵੱਟਾ is worn on which part of the body?",
    options: ["Forehead", "Neck", "Wrist", "Foot"],
    answer: "Forehead",
  },
  {
    question: "ਕਸ਼ਕਾ is worn on which part of the body?",
    options: ["Forehead", "Neck", "Wrist", "Foot"],
    answer: "Forehead",
  },
  {
    question: "ਧੇੰਦੂ is worn on which part of the body?",
    options: ["Ear", "Nose", "Neck", "Wrist"],
    answer: "Ear",
  },
  {
    question: "ਕੰਟਾਲਾ is worn on which part of the body?",
    options: ["Ear", "Nose", "Neck", "Wrist"],
    answer: "Ear",
  },
  {
    question: "ਖੁੱਲੀ is worn on which part of the body?",
    options: ["Ear", "Nose", "Neck", "Wrist"],
    answer: "Ear",
  },
  {
    question: "ਫੁੰਮ੍ਹੀ is worn on which part of the body?",
    options: ["Ear", "Nose", "Neck", "Wrist"],
    answer: "Ear",
  },
  {
    question: "ਦੇਡੀ is worn on which part of the body?",
    options: ["Ear", "Nose", "Neck", "Wrist"],
    answer: "Ear",
  },
  {
    question: "ਚੰਦਨਹਾਰ is worn on which part of the body?",
    options: ["Neck", "Wrist", "Foot", "Head"],
    answer: "Neck",
  },
  {
    question: "ਨੋਲਖਾ ਹਾਰ is worn on which part of the body?",
    options: ["Neck", "Wrist", "Foot", "Head"],
    answer: "Neck",
  },
  {
    question: "ਮੋਹਰਾਂ are worn on which part of the body?",
    options: ["Neck", "Wrist", "Foot", "Head"],
    answer: "Neck",
  },
  {
    question: "ਹੋਲਦਿਲ is worn on which part of the body?",
    options: ["Neck", "Wrist", "Foot", "Head"],
    answer: "Neck",
  },
  {
    question: "ਕੰਢੀ is worn on which part of the body?",
    options: ["Neck", "Wrist", "Foot", "Head"],
    answer: "Neck",
  },
  {
    question: "ਗੁਲੂਬੰਦ is worn on which part of the body?",
    options: ["Neck", "Wrist", "Foot", "Head"],
    answer: "Neck",
  },
  {
    question: "ਹੱਸ is worn on which part of the body?",
    options: ["Neck", "Wrist", "Foot", "Head"],
    answer: "Neck",
  },
  {
    question: "ਬੂੱਲਕ is worn on which part of the body?",
    options: ["Nose", "Ear", "Neck", "Wrist"],
    answer: "Nose",
  },
  {
    question: "ਫੁੱਲੀ is worn on which part of the body?",
    options: ["Nose", "Ear", "Neck", "Wrist"],
    answer: "Nose",
  },
  {
    question: "ਬੋਹਰ is worn on which part of the body?",
    options: ["Nose", "Ear", "Neck", "Wrist"],
    answer: "Nose",
  },
  {
    question: "ਲੋਂਗ is worn on which part of the body?",
    options: ["Nose", "Ear", "Neck", "Wrist"],
    answer: "Nose",
  },
  {
    question: "ਪਹੁੰਚਿਆ is worn on which part of the body?",
    options: ["Arm", "Leg", "Wrist", "Neck"],
    answer: "Arm",
  },
  {
    question: "ਬਾਂਕਾ is worn on which part of the body?",
    options: ["Arm", "Leg", "Wrist", "Neck"],
    answer: "Arm",
  },
  {
    question: "ਬੇਈੰ is worn on which part of the body?",
    options: ["Arm", "Leg", "Wrist", "Neck"],
    answer: "Arm",
  },
  {
    question: "ਛੰਨਕੰਗਣ is worn on which part of the body?",
    options: ["Arm", "Leg", "Wrist", "Neck"],
    answer: "Wrist",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who was the first Sufi poet of Punjab to adopt the popular measure of Kafi to express his mystic ideas?",
    options: ["Hussain", "Baba Farid", "Shah Hussain", "Bulleh Shah"],
    answer: "Hussain",
  },
  {
    question: "What is celebrated at Faridkot to honor Baba Sheikh Farid?",
    options: [
      "Baba Sheikh Farid Aagman",
      "Baba Farid Joti Diwas",
      "Baba Farid Mela",
      "Farid Jayanti",
    ],
    answer: "Baba Sheikh Farid Aagman",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What poetic form was popularized by the first Sufi poet of Punjab, Hussain?",
    options: ["Kafi", "Qawwali", "Ghazal", "Rubaiyat"],
    answer: "Kafi",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Baba Sheikh Farid Aagman is associated with which city in Punjab?",
    options: ["Faridkot", "Amritsar", "Bathinda", "Jalandhar"],
    answer: "Faridkot",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following is a traditional game played by females in Punjab?",
    options: ["ਗੀਟੇ", "ਕਬੱਡੀ", "ਗੁੱਲੀ-ਡੰਡਾ", "ਕੋਟਲਾ ਛਪਾਕੀ"],
    answer: "ਗੀਟੇ",
  },
  {
    question: "Which game is typically associated with males in Punjab?",
    options: ["ਪਿੱਠੂ ਗਰਮ", "ਚੂੰਢੀ-ਮੁੱਕਾ", "ਮਾਈ ਮਾਈ ਕੀ ਲੱਭਦੀ", "ਨਦੀ ਕਿਨਾਰਾ"],
    answer: "ਪਿੱਠੂ ਗਰਮ",
  },
  {
    question:
      "In traditional Punjabi games, which one is primarily played by females?",
    options: ["ਕਿੱਕਲੀ", "ਜੰਡ ਖਰੰਡ", "ਖਿੱਦੋ ਖੂੰਡੀ", "ਬੰਟੇ"],
    answer: "ਕਿੱਕਲੀ",
  },
  {
    question: "Which game is traditionally played by males in Punjab?",
    options: ["ਗੁੱਲੀ-ਡੰਡਾ", "ਰੱਸੀ ਟੱਪਣਾ", "ਚਿੜੀ ਉੱਡ ਕਾਂ ਉੱਡ", "ਸਮੁੰਦਰ ਤੇ ਮੱਛੀ"],
    answer: "ਗੁੱਲੀ-ਡੰਡਾ",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Among the following, which game is commonly played by females in Punjab?",
    options: [
      "ਟੋਚਨ ਪਾ ਬਈ ਟੋਚਨ ਪਾ",
      "ਥਾਲ",
      "ਕੋਟਲਾ ਛਪਾਕੀ",
      "ਬਿੱਲ ਬੱਚਿਆਂ ਦੀ ਮਾਂ (ਲੂਣ ਮਿਆਣੀ)",
    ],
    answer: "ਟੋਚਨ ਪਾ ਬਈ ਟੋਚਨ ਪਾ",
  },
  {
    question: "Which of these games is specifically played by males in Punjab?",
    options: ["ਖਿੱਦੋ ਖੂੰਡੀ", "ਤੇਰਾ ਮੇਰਾ ਮੇਲ ਨਹੀਂ", "ਰੁਮਾਲ ਚੁੱਕਣਾ", "ਉਠਕ ਬੈਠਕ"],
    answer: "ਖਿੱਦੋ ਖੂੰਡੀ",
  },
  {
    question: "Which game is popular among females in Punjab?",
    options: ["ਮਾਈ ਪਤੰਗੜਾ ਮਾਈ ਪਤੰਗੜਾ", "ਕਬੱਡੀ", "ਗੁੱਲੀ-ਡੰਡਾ", "ਕੋਟਲਾ ਛਪਾਕੀ"],
    answer: "ਮਾਈ ਪਤੰਗੜਾ ਮਾਈ ਪਤੰਗੜਾ",
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following is a traditional male game in Punjab?",
    options: ["ਜੰਡ ਖਰੰਡ", "ਚੂੰਢੀ-ਮੁੱਕਾ", "ਨਦੀ ਕਿਨਾਰਾ", "ਮਾਈ ਮਾਈ ਕੀ ਲੱਭਦੀ"],
    answer: "ਜੰਡ ਖਰੰਡ",
  },
  {
    question: "Which traditional Punjabi game is typically played by females?",
    options: ["ਸੂਈ ਧਾਗਾ", "ਲੁਕਣ ਮੀਟੀ", "ਬੰਟੇ", "ਕਬੱਡੀ"],
    answer: "ਸੂਈ ਧਾਗਾ",
  },
  {
    question: "Which game is traditionally associated with males in Punjab?",
    options: ["ਪਿੱਠੂ ਗਰਮ", "ਗੀਟੇ", "ਨਦੀ ਕਿਨਾਰਾ", "ਚਿੜੀ ਉੱਡ ਕਾਂ ਉੱਡ"],
    answer: "ਪਿੱਠੂ ਗਰਮ",
  },
  {
    question: "What is Chowk Purana known as?",
    options: [
      "A type of painting",
      "A type of architecture",
      "A form of folk music",
      "A traditional textile pattern",
    ],
    answer: "A type of painting",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What was the original name of Nanak Singh, the famous Punjabi writer?",
    options: ["Harnam Das", "Hansraj", "Baldev Singh", "Harbhajan Singh"],
    answer: "Hansraj",
  },
  {
    question: "In which village was Nanak Singh born?",
    options: [
      "Chak Hamid, Jhelum, Pakistan",
      "Talwandi Sabo, Punjab",
      "Nankana Sahib, Pakistan",
      "Faridkot, Punjab",
    ],
    answer: "Chak Hamid, Jhelum, Pakistan",
  },
  {
    question:
      "For which work did Nanak Singh receive the Sahitya Akademi Award in 1962?",
    options: [
      "Pavitar Papi",
      "Ik Miyan Do Talwaraan",
      "Chitta Lahoo",
      "Khooni Visakhi",
    ],
    answer: "Ik Miyan Do Talwaraan",
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following is NOT a work of Nanak Singh?",
    options: [
      "Chitta Lahoo",
      "Gangajal Vich Sharab",
      "Adam Khor",
      "Rajtarangini",
    ],
    answer: "Rajtarangini",
  },
  {
    question: "Who invented the musical instrument Dilruba?",
    options: [
      "Guru Nanak Dev Ji",
      "Guru Gobind Singh Ji",
      "Guru Arjan Dev Ji",
      "Guru Hargobind Ji",
    ],
    answer: "Guru Gobind Singh Ji",
  },
  {
    question: "What is the Dilruba a smaller form of?",
    options: ["Sarangi", "Tauns", "Rabab", "Sitar"],
    answer: "Tauns",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What does a veil or 'Dupatta' adorned with silk tassels traditionally symbolize in Punjabi culture?",
    options: [
      "A women’s accessory for festivals and folk dances",
      "A bride's wedding attire",
      "A farmer's protective clothing",
      "A symbol of royalty",
    ],
    answer: "A women’s accessory for festivals and folk dances",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is the Punjabi term for a silk tassel worn as part of traditional attire?",
    options: ["Dupatta", "Guchha", "Phulkari", "Chunni"],
    answer: "Guchha",
  },
  {
    question: "Who wrote the semi-historical 'Nader Shah di War'?",
    options: ["Nazabat", "Bhai Veer Singh", "Nanak Singh", "Amrita Pritam"],
    answer: "Nazabat",
  },
  {
    question: "What is described in 'Nader Shah di War'?",
    options: [
      "Nader Shah’s invasion of India in 1739",
      "The life of Guru Gobind Singh Ji",
      "The creation of the Khalsa",
      "The annexation of Punjab by the British",
    ],
    answer: "Nader Shah’s invasion of India in 1739",
  },
  {
    question: "What did Nader Shah loot during his invasion of India?",
    options: [
      "Mayur throne and Kohinoor diamond",
      "Golden Temple treasures",
      "Taxila artifacts",
      "Mughal paintings and manuscripts",
    ],
    answer: "Mayur throne and Kohinoor diamond",
  },
  {
    question: "Who founded 'Khalsa Samachar'?",
    options: [
      "Bhai Veer Singh",
      "Nanak Singh",
      "Bhai Randhir Singh",
      "Amrita Pritam",
    ],
    answer: "Bhai Veer Singh",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Bhai Veer Singh was the first person from Punjab to receive which award?",
    options: [
      "Sahitya Akademi Award",
      "Padma Shri",
      "Gyanpeeth Award",
      "Bharat Ratna",
    ],
    answer: "Sahitya Akademi Award",
  },
  {
    question: "Where was Bhai Veer Singh born?",
    options: ["Amritsar", "Lahore", "Chak Hamid", "Patiala"],
    answer: "Amritsar",
  },
  {
    question: "Which press was started by Bhai Veer Singh in 1892?",
    options: [
      "Khalsa Press",
      "Singh Sabha Press",
      "Sikh Heritage Press",
      "Golden Press",
    ],
    answer: "Khalsa Press",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of Bhai Veer Singh’s works won the Sahitya Akademi Award in 1955?",
    options: ["Mere Saiyan Ji", "Sundari", "Baba Naudh Singh", "Bijay Singh"],
    answer: "Mere Saiyan Ji",
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following is NOT a work of Bhai Veer Singh?",
    options: ["Khooni Visakhi", "Matak Hulare", "Bijay Singh", "Sundari"],
    answer: "Khooni Visakhi",
  },
  {
    question: "What type of publication was 'Khalsa Samachar'?",
    options: [
      "Weekly newspaper",
      "Monthly magazine",
      "Daily newspaper",
      "Yearly journal",
    ],
    answer: "Weekly newspaper",
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following is a folk dance of women in Punjab?",
    options: ["Giddha", "Bhangra", "Luddi", "Dhamaal"],
    answer: "Giddha",
  },
  {
    question: "The folk dance 'Sammi' belongs to which region?",
    options: ["Sandhalbar", "Malwa", "Majha", "Doaba"],
    answer: "Sandhalbar",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which folk dance involves women carrying decorated pots on their heads during celebrations?",
    options: ["Jago", "Dhamaal", "Kikli", "Bhangra"],
    answer: "Jago",
  },
  {
    question: "Which dance form involves women spinning and holding hands?",
    options: ["Kikli", "Luddi", "Sammi", "Jhumar"],
    answer: "Kikli",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Jhumar, a traditional folk dance of Punjab, belongs to which region?",
    options: ["Sandhalbar", "Doaba", "Majha", "Malwa"],
    answer: "Sandhalbar",
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following is a folk dance of men in Punjab?",
    options: ["Bhangra", "Jago", "Sammi", "Kikli"],
    answer: "Bhangra",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Dankaara, a folk dance of men in Punjab, is performed using which object?",
    options: ["Stick (Dang)", "Sword", "Dhol", "Cloth"],
    answer: "Stick (Dang)",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which folk dance of Punjab is performed while sitting and is common in Qawwalis?",
    options: ["Julli", "Luddi", "Dhamaal", "Malwai Giddha"],
    answer: "Julli",
  },
  {
    question: "Luddi, a Punjabi folk dance, involves which unique movement?",
    options: [
      "One hand behind the back and the other in front of the face",
      "Jumping in circles with arms stretched",
      "Spinning while holding hands",
      "Carrying pots on the head",
    ],
    answer: "One hand behind the back and the other in front of the face",
  },
  {
    question: "Malwai Giddha is performed by which group?",
    options: ["Men", "Women", "Children", "Both Men and Women"],
    answer: "Men",
  },
  {
    question: "Which dance form is performed by both men and women in Punjab?",
    options: ["Jindua", "Giddha", "Bhangra", "Dhamaal"],
    answer: "Jindua",
  },
  {
    question: "Kaarthi, a folk dance of Punjab, is performed by which group?",
    options: ["Both men and women", "Only men", "Only women", "Children"],
    answer: "Both men and women",
  },
  {
    question: "During which month is Hola Mohalla celebrated?",
    options: ["Chet", "Vaisakh", "Magh", "Phagun"],
    answer: "Chet",
  },
  {
    question: "Hola Mohalla is celebrated on which day relative to Holi?",
    options: [
      "Day after Holi",
      "Day before Holi",
      "Same day as Holi",
      "Two days after Holi",
    ],
    answer: "Day after Holi",
  },
  {
    question: "Who started the festival of Hola Mohalla?",
    options: [
      "Guru Gobind Singh Ji",
      "Guru Nanak Dev Ji",
      "Guru Arjan Dev Ji",
      "Guru Hargobind Ji",
    ],
    answer: "Guru Gobind Singh Ji",
  },
  {
    question: "Where was the festival of Hola Mohalla started?",
    options: ["Anandpur Sahib", "Amritsar", "Talwandi Sabo", "Kartarpur"],
    answer: "Anandpur Sahib",
  },
  {
    question: "Which book was authored by Surjit Singh Sethi?",
    options: ["ਰੇਤ ਦਾ ਪਹਾੜ", "ਕੁਝ ਅਣਕਿਹਾ ਵੀ", "ਸਚ ਦੀ ਵੀਚਾਰ", "ਜੀਵਨ ਦੀ ਰਾਹ"],
    answer: "ਰੇਤ ਦਾ ਪਹਾੜ",
  },
  {
    question: "Surjit Singh Sethi authored which of the following books?",
    options: [
      "ਇੱਕ ਸ਼ਹਿਰ ਦੀ ਗੱਲ",
      "ਆਬਰਾ ਕਦਾਬਰਾ",
      "ਬਿਰਸਾ ਦਾ ਸੱਚ",
      "ਨਿਭਾ ਨਹੀਂ ਹੋਇਆ",
    ],
    answer: "ਇੱਕ ਸ਼ਹਿਰ ਦੀ ਗੱਲ",
  },
  {
    question: "Which of these is a book by Surjit Singh Sethi?",
    options: ["ਆਬਰਾ ਕਦਾਬਰਾ", "ਮਿਟੀ ਦੀ ਮੋਹਕ", "ਗਿਆਨ ਤੇ ਧਾਰਾ", "ਸੋਚ ਤੇ ਸੰਘਰਸ਼"],
    answer: "ਆਬਰਾ ਕਦਾਬਰਾ",
  },
  {
    question: "Who authored the book 'ਕੁਝ ਅਣਕਿਹਾ ਵੀ'?",
    options: [
      "Prem Prakash",
      "Surjit Singh Sethi",
      "Nanak Singh",
      "Amrita Pritam",
    ],
    answer: "Prem Prakash",
  },
  {
    question: "What is the musical recitation of the Guru Granth Sahib called?",
    options: ["Shabad Kirtan", "Katha Vachik", "Naam Simran", "Path Sahib"],
    answer: "Shabad Kirtan",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Under whose patronage was the Ragi tradition of Shabad Kirtan started?",
    options: [
      "Guru Arjan Dev Ji",
      "Guru Gobind Singh Ji",
      "Guru Nanak Dev Ji",
      "Guru Ram Das Ji",
    ],
    answer: "Guru Arjan Dev Ji",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which traditional dance involves young girls holding hands and twirling in circles?",
    options: ["Kikli", "Bhangra", "Giddha", "Jhummar"],
    answer: "Kikli",
  },
  {
    question: "What is unique about the dance 'Kikli'?",
    options: [
      "Performed by young girls holding hands and twirling around in circles",
      "Performed by men with sticks",
      "Involves jumping and clapping in rhythm",
      "A solo dance performed during festivals",
    ],
    answer:
      "Performed by young girls holding hands and twirling around in circles",
  },
  {
    question: "Who introduced free verse in Punjabi literature?",
    options: [
      "Puran Singh",
      "Amrita Pritam",
      "Nanak Singh",
      "Shiv Kumar Batalvi",
    ],
    answer: "Puran Singh",
  },
  {
    question: "When was Puran Singh born?",
    options: [
      "17 February 1881",
      "15 August 1880",
      "10 March 1882",
      "25 December 1880",
    ],
    answer: "17 February 1881",
  },
  {
    question: "Where was Puran Singh born?",
    options: [
      "Salhad, Abottabad, Pakistan",
      "Ludhiana, Punjab, India",
      "Sialkot, Pakistan",
      "Amritsar, Punjab, India",
    ],
    answer: "Salhad, Abottabad, Pakistan",
  },
  {
    question: "'Sisters of the Spinning Wheel' (1921) is written by?",
    options: [
      "Puran Singh",
      "Rabindranath Tagore",
      "Amrita Pritam",
      "Sarojini Naidu",
    ],
    answer: "Puran Singh",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the author of 'Unstrung Beads' (1923)?",
    options: [
      "Puran Singh",
      "Mulk Raj Anand",
      "Nanak Singh",
      "Shiv Kumar Batalvi",
    ],
    answer: "Puran Singh",
  },
  {
    question: "'The Spirit of Oriental Poetry' (1926) was written by?",
    options: ["Puran Singh", "Rabindranath Tagore", "Khwaja Fareed", "Iqbal"],
    answer: "Puran Singh",
  },
  {
    question: "'The Book of Ten Masters' is authored by?",
    options: [
      "Puran Singh",
      "Max Arthur Macauliffe",
      "Kartar Singh Duggal",
      "Nanak Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Puran Singh",
  },
  {
    question: "Who wrote 'The Spirit Born People'?",
    options: ["Puran Singh", "Amrita Pritam", "Shiv Kumar Batalvi", "Gulzar"],
    answer: "Puran Singh",
  },
  {
    question: "'Swami Rama' is a book written by?",
    options: [
      "Puran Singh",
      "Swami Vivekananda",
      "R.K. Narayan",
      "Khwaja Fareed",
    ],
    answer: "Puran Singh",
  },
  {
    question: "Who authored 'Khulle Maidan' in Punjabi literature?",
    options: [
      "Puran Singh",
      "Nanak Singh",
      "Amrita Pritam",
      "Shiv Kumar Batalvi",
    ],
    answer: "Puran Singh",
  },
  {
    question: "'Khulle Ghund' (1923) is a Punjabi work by?",
    options: [
      "Puran Singh",
      "Gurdial Singh",
      "Nanak Singh",
      "Jaswant Singh Kanwal",
    ],
    answer: "Puran Singh",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the author of 'Khulle Asmani Rang' (1927)?",
    options: [
      "Puran Singh",
      "Amrita Pritam",
      "Shiv Kumar Batalvi",
      "Gurdial Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Puran Singh",
  },
  {
    question: "'Puran Nath Jogi' is written by?",
    options: [
      "Puran Singh",
      "Nanak Singh",
      "Balwant Gargi",
      "Jaswant Singh Kanwal",
    ],
    answer: "Puran Singh",
  },
  {
    question: "'Khulle Lekh' (1929) is authored by?",
    options: [
      "Puran Singh",
      "Gurdial Singh",
      "Amrita Pritam",
      "Shiv Kumar Batalvi",
    ],
    answer: "Puran Singh",
  },
  {
    question: "Who wrote the historical novel 'Sundari'?",
    options: ["Vir Singh", "Nanak Singh", "Amrita Pritam", "Puran Singh"],
    answer: "Vir Singh",
  },
  {
    question: "'Satwant Kaur' is a historical novel written by?",
    options: [
      "Vir Singh",
      "Gurdial Singh",
      "Shiv Kumar Batalvi",
      "Balwant Gargi",
    ],
    answer: "Vir Singh",
  },
  {
    question: "The novel 'Baba Naudh Singh' was authored by?",
    options: ["Vir Singh", "Mulk Raj Anand", "Gurdial Singh", "Nanak Singh"],
    answer: "Vir Singh",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Dhadis, a type of Sikh musicians, are associated with what kind of songs?",
    options: [
      "Heroic ballads to inspire valour",
      "Devotional hymns",
      "Romantic folk songs",
      "Sufi poetry",
    ],
    answer: "Heroic ballads to inspire valour",
  },
  {
    question: "What is the primary role of Dhadis in Sikh tradition?",
    options: [
      "Singing heroic ballads to inspire valour",
      "Performing classical ragas",
      "Narrating folk tales in song",
      "Composing Sufi poetry",
    ],
    answer: "Singing heroic ballads to inspire valour",
  },
  {
    question: "The Kila Raipur Sports Festival is popularly known as?",
    options: [
      "Rural Olympics",
      "Punjab Kabaddi League",
      "Kisan Sports Festival",
      "Desi Games Fair",
    ],
    answer: "Rural Olympics",
  },
  {
    question: "Where is the Kila Raipur Sports Festival held?",
    options: [
      "Ludhiana, Punjab",
      "Amritsar, Punjab",
      "Jalandhar, Punjab",
      "Patiala, Punjab",
    ],
    answer: "Ludhiana, Punjab",
  },
  {
    question: "How many days does the Kila Raipur Sports Festival last?",
    options: ["Three days", "One day", "Five days", "Seven days"],
    answer: "Three days",
  },
  {
    question: "What is the unique feature of the Kila Raipur Sports Festival?",
    options: [
      "Traditional rural sports and games",
      "Classical dance performances",
      "Sikh devotional music competitions",
      "Harvesting-related cultural displays",
    ],
    answer: "Traditional rural sports and games",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which is the last railway station in India between Amritsar and Lahore?",
    options: ["Attari", "Wagah", "Firozpur", "Dera Baba Nanak"],
    answer: "Attari",
  },
  {
    question: "Pong Dam is built on which river?",
    options: ["Beas River", "Sutlej River", "Ravi River", "Chenab River"],
    answer: "Beas River",
  },
  {
    question: "What is the name of the lake on the backside of Pong Dam?",
    options: [
      "Maharana Pratap Lake",
      "Gobind Sagar Lake",
      "Harike Wetland",
      "Sukhna Lake",
    ],
    answer: "Maharana Pratap Lake",
  },
  {
    question: "Which lake is located on the backside of the Bhakra Dam?",
    options: [
      "Gobind Sagar Lake",
      "Maharana Pratap Lake",
      "Harike Wetland",
      "Sukhna Lake",
    ],
    answer: "Gobind Sagar Lake",
  },
  {
    question: "In which year did Maharaja Ranjit Singh die?",
    options: ["1839", "1845", "1829", "1820"],
    answer: "1839",
  },
  {
    question: "Who was the Prime Minister of Maharaja Ranjit Singh?",
    options: [
      "Dhian Singh Dogra",
      "Sardar Hari Singh Nalwa",
      "Fakir Aziz-ud-Din",
      "Pandit Dina Nath",
    ],
    answer: "Dhian Singh Dogra",
  },
  {
    question: "Who was the Foreign Minister of Maharaja Ranjit Singh?",
    options: [
      "Fakir Aziz-ud-Din",
      "Dhian Singh Dogra",
      "Pandit Dina Nath",
      "Sardar Hari Singh Nalwa",
    ],
    answer: "Fakir Aziz-ud-Din",
  },
  {
    question: "Who was the Finance Minister of Maharaja Ranjit Singh?",
    options: [
      "Pandit Dina Nath",
      "Fakir Aziz-ud-Din",
      "Sardar Hari Singh Nalwa",
      "Dhian Singh Dogra",
    ],
    answer: "Pandit Dina Nath",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who was the first European officer to join Maharaja Ranjit Singh's army?",
    options: [
      "Prince Ventura",
      "Major James Abbott",
      "Lieutenant John Nicholson",
      "Allard",
    ],
    answer: "Prince Ventura",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which two European officers were responsible for modernizing the army of Maharaja Ranjit Singh?",
    options: [
      "Prince Ventura and Allard",
      "Prince Ventura and Fowke",
      "Major Abbott and Allard",
      "Prince Ventura and Burnes",
    ],
    answer: "Prince Ventura and Allard",
  },
  {
    question:
      "After Maharaja Ranjit Singh's death, who succeeded him as the next ruler?",
    options: [
      "Kharak Singh",
      "Sher Singh",
      "Maharaja Gulab Singh",
      "Chand Kaur",
    ],
    answer: "Kharak Singh",
  },
  {
    question: "Who gave the Koh-i-Noor diamond to Maharaja Ranjit Singh?",
    options: [
      "Wafa Begum",
      "Shah Shuja",
      "Maharaja Gulab Singh",
      "Rani Chand Kaur",
    ],
    answer: "Wafa Begum",
  },
  {
    question: "Which Gurudwaras were built by Maharaja Ranjit Singh?",
    options: [
      "Patna Sahib, Hazur Sahib",
      "Harmandir Sahib, Kesgarh Sahib",
      "Damdama Sahib, Darbar Sahib",
      "Hazur Sahib, Golden Temple",
    ],
    answer: "Patna Sahib, Hazur Sahib",
  },
  {
    question: "Maharaja Ranjit Singh donated gold to which religious places?",
    options: [
      "Harmandir Sahib, Kashi Vishwanath, Jwalamukhi Mandir",
      "Golden Temple, Vaishno Devi, Dwarka Temple",
      "Amritsar Gurudwara, Haridwar, Golden Temple",
      "Rishikesh, Haridwar, Jagannath Temple",
    ],
    answer: "Harmandir Sahib, Kashi Vishwanath, Jwalamukhi Mandir",
  },
  {
    question: "Where are Luv and Kush from the Ramayana believed to be born?",
    options: ["Amritsar", "Ayodhya", "Mathura", "Kashi"],
    answer: "Amritsar",
  },
  {
    question: "When does the festival Tiaan begin in Punjab?",
    options: [
      "Third day of the month of Saawan",
      "First day of the month of Vaisakh",
      "Fifth day of Baisakhi",
      "Fourth day of the month of Phagun",
    ],
    answer: "Third day of the month of Saawan",
  },
  {
    question:
      "In which district is Kalanaur town, where Akbar was enthroned, located?",
    options: ["Gurdaspur", "Amritsar", "Patiala", "Jalandhar"],
    answer: "Gurdaspur",
  },
  {
    question: "Who built Gurudwara Sis Ganj and Gurudwara Rakab Ganj in Delhi?",
    options: [
      "Sardar Baghel Singh",
      "Guru Gobind Singh",
      "Maharaja Ranjit Singh",
      "Sardar Jassa Singh Ahluwalia",
    ],
    answer: "Sardar Baghel Singh",
  },
  {
    question: "Which famous poem was written by Bulleh Shah?",
    options: [
      "Makke Gaye Gal Mukdi Nai",
      "Bullah Ki Jana Mai Kaun",
      "Ik Nukte Vich Gal Mukdi Hai",
      "Mai Jana Jogi De Nal",
    ],
    answer: "Makke Gaye Gal Mukdi Nai",
  },
  {
    question: "What is another well-known work of Bulleh Shah?",
    options: [
      "Bullah Ki Jana Mai Kaun",
      "Makke Gaye Gal Mukdi Nai",
      "Jogi De Nal Mai Jana",
      "Gulami Da Laga Vichar",
    ],
    answer: "Bullah Ki Jana Mai Kaun",
  },
  {
    question: "When was Punjabi University, Patiala established?",
    options: ["1962", "1955", "1971", "1980"],
    answer: "1962",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who is the Chancellor of Punjabi University, Patiala or any other university in Punjab?",
    options: [
      "Governor of Punjab",
      "Chief Minister of Punjab",
      "Education Minister of Punjab",
      "President of India",
    ],
    answer: "Governor of Punjab",
  },
  {
    question: "Who succeeded Raja Karam Singh as Maharaja?",
    options: [
      "Maharaja Narendra Singh",
      "Maharaja Ranjit Singh",
      "Maharaja Sher Singh",
      "Maharaja Kesar Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Maharaja Narendra Singh",
  },
  {
    question: "Who was the first Maharaja of Patiala?",
    options: [
      "Maharaja Ala Singh",
      "Maharaja Amr Singh",
      "Maharaja Sahib Singh",
      "Maharaja Karam Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Maharaja Ala Singh",
  },
  {
    question: "Which Maharaja of Patiala ruled from 1765 to 1781?",
    options: [
      "Maharaja Amr Singh",
      "Maharaja Ala Singh",
      "Maharaja Karam Singh",
      "Maharaja Rajinder Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Maharaja Amr Singh",
  },
  {
    question: "Maharaja Sahib Singh ruled Patiala during which years?",
    options: ["1781-1813", "1813-1845", "1862-1874", "1900-1938"],
    answer: "1781-1813",
  },
  {
    question: "Who was the Maharaja of Patiala from 1813 to 1845?",
    options: [
      "Maharaja Karam Singh",
      "Maharaja Bhupinder Singh",
      "Maharaja Yadavinder Singh",
      "Maharaja Narendra Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Maharaja Karam Singh",
  },
  {
    question: "Maharaja Narendra Singh ruled Patiala from 1845 to which year?",
    options: ["1862", "1900", "1813", "1938"],
    answer: "1862",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What notable event did Maharaja Narendra Singh contribute to in 1857?",
    options: [
      "Helped the British in 1857",
      "Led the rebellion against the British",
      "Founded the Patiala Gurudwara",
      "Built the Patiala fort",
    ],
    answer: "Helped the British in 1857",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which Maharaja of Patiala was included in the British executive council in 1861?",
    options: [
      "Maharaja Narendra Singh",
      "Maharaja Rajinder Singh",
      "Maharaja Bhupinder Singh",
      "Maharaja Ala Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Maharaja Narendra Singh",
  },
  {
    question: "Who succeeded Maharaja Narendra Singh as the ruler of Patiala?",
    options: [
      "Maharaja Mahinder Singh",
      "Maharaja Rajinder Singh",
      "Maharaja Bhupinder Singh",
      "Maharaja Yadavinder Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Maharaja Mahinder Singh",
  },
  {
    question: "Which Maharaja of Patiala ruled from 1900 to 1938?",
    options: [
      "Maharaja Bhupinder Singh",
      "Maharaja Yadavinder Singh",
      "Maharaja Rajinder Singh",
      "Maharaja Ala Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Maharaja Bhupinder Singh",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who was the last Maharaja of Patiala before India’s independence in 1947?",
    options: [
      "Maharaja Yadavinder Singh",
      "Maharaja Bhupinder Singh",
      "Maharaja Mahinder Singh",
      "Maharaja Rajinder Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Maharaja Yadavinder Singh",
  },
  {
    question: "Who became the Maharaja of Patiala after Yadavinder Singh?",
    options: [
      "Amrinder Singh",
      "Bhupinder Singh",
      "Rajinder Singh",
      "Mahinder Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Amrinder Singh",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the current Maharaja of Patiala as of 1971?",
    options: [
      "Amrinder Singh",
      "Rajinder Singh",
      "Yadavinder Singh",
      "Bhupinder Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Amrinder Singh",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which book earned Amrita Pritam the Bhartiya Jnanpith Award in 1982?",
    options: ["Kagaj te Canvas", "Pinjar", "Sagar te Sippiyan", "Kora Kagaz"],
    answer: "Kagaj te Canvas",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Amrita Pritam was the first woman to win which prestigious award in India?",
    options: [
      "Sahitya Akademi Award",
      "Jnanpith Award",
      "Padma Bhushan",
      "Padma Shri",
    ],
    answer: "Sahitya Akademi Award",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Amrita Pritam was the first Punjabi to win which prestigious award?",
    options: [
      "Bhartiya Jnanpith Award",
      "Sahitya Akademi Award",
      "Padma Bhushan",
      "Booker Prize",
    ],
    answer: "Bhartiya Jnanpith Award",
  },
  {
    question: "Which monthly magazine was edited by Amrita Pritam?",
    options: ["Nagmani", "Saras Salil", "Sheen", "Yojana"],
    answer: "Nagmani",
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following is a novel written by Amrita Pritam?",
    options: ["Pinjar", "Kagaj te Canvas", "Sahitya Akademi", "Nagmani"],
    answer: "Pinjar",
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following poems was written by Amrita Pritam?",
    options: ["Sunehe", "Meri Ma", "Chandni", "Nayi Zindagi"],
    answer: "Sunehe",
  },
  {
    question: "Amrita Pritam's autobiography is titled?",
    options: [
      "Raseedi Ticket",
      "Pinjar",
      "Kagaj te Canvas",
      "Delhi Diyaan Galiyan",
    ],
    answer: "Raseedi Ticket",
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following is NOT a work by Amrita Pritam?",
    options: ["Kora Kagaz", "Sunehe", "Sagar te Sippiyan", "Nayi Zindagi"],
    answer: "Nayi Zindagi",
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following poems was written by Amrita Pritam?",
    options: [
      "Aj Akhan Waris Shah Nu",
      "Aks",
      "Ek Nayi Zindagi",
      "Meri Aangan",
    ],
    answer: "Aj Akhan Waris Shah Nu",
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following is a novel written by Amrita Pritam?",
    options: [
      "Delhi Diyaan Galiyan",
      "Waris Shah",
      "Hasi Teri Bhi",
      "Nayi Zindagi",
    ],
    answer: "Delhi Diyaan Galiyan",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Amrita Pritam wrote which poetry collection about people's pain?",
    options: ["Lok Peeda", "Sunehe", "Raseedi Ticket", "Meri Ma"],
    answer: "Lok Peeda",
  },
  {
    question: "What is Amritsar known as?",
    options: [
      "Sifti da Ghar",
      "City of Golden Temple",
      "Heart of Punjab",
      "Gateway to India",
    ],
    answer: "Sifti da Ghar",
  },
  {
    question: "Who was associated with the musical tradition of Rababi?",
    options: ["Bhai Mardana", "Guru Nanak Dev", "Bhai Gurdas", "Mardana Singh"],
    answer: "Bhai Mardana",
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following plays was written by Balwant Gargi?",
    options: [
      "Sultan Razia",
      "Mirza Sahiba",
      "Soz-e-Siyaasat",
      "Sohni Mahival",
    ],
    answer: "Sultan Razia",
  },
  {
    question: "Where was Balwant Gargi born?",
    options: ["Bathinda", "Amritsar", "Ludhiana", "Patiala"],
    answer: "Bathinda",
  },
  {
    question: "Which award did Balwant Gargi win in 1962?",
    options: [
      "Sahitya Akademi Award for Theatre",
      "Jnanpith Award",
      "Padma Bhushan",
      "Sahitya Akademi Award for Poetry",
    ],
    answer: "Sahitya Akademi Award for Theatre",
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following novels was written by Balwant Gargi?",
    options: [
      "Sohni Mahival",
      "Rang Manch",
      "Mirza Sahiba",
      "Mirchaan Wala Saag",
    ],
    answer: "Mirchaan Wala Saag",
  },
  {
    question: "Who founded the Punjab Gharana of Tabla?",
    options: [
      "Lal Bhawani Das",
      "Ustad Zakir Hussain",
      "Bismillah Khan",
      "Allama Iqbal",
    ],
    answer: "Lal Bhawani Das",
  },
  {
    question: "Which musical instrument is associated with the Punjab Gharana?",
    options: ["Tabla", "Sitar", "Guitar", "Dholak"],
    answer: "Tabla",
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following novels was written by Amrita Pritam?",
    options: ["Rang Ka Patta", "Uddat Bare", "Soz-e-Siyaasat", "Sultan Razia"],
    answer: "Rang Ka Patta",
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following is a novel written by Harbhajan Singh?",
    options: ["Uddat Bare", "Pinjar", "Rang Ka Patta", "Yaari"],
    answer: "Uddat Bare",
  },
  {
    question: "Amrita Pritam wrote which famous novel?",
    options: ["Pinjar", "Uddat Bare", "Yaari", "Sohni Mahival"],
    answer: "Pinjar",
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following is a work written by Balwant Gargi?",
    options: [
      "Soz-e-Siyaasat",
      "Mirza Sahiba",
      "Rang Ka Patta",
      "Mirse Wala Saag",
    ],
    answer: "Mirza Sahiba",
  },
  {
    question: "What type of instrument is a 'Khanjari' in Punjabi folk music?",
    options: ["Drum", "Flute", "String Instrument", "Percussion Instrument"],
    answer: "Drum",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following is a Punjabi folk instrument made by joining two flutes?",
    options: ["Algoze", "Dilruba", "Sapp", "Tumbi"],
    answer: "Algoze",
  },
  {
    question: "Which Punjabi folk instrument is similar to a damroo?",
    options: ["Bugchu", "Dhol", "Ektara", "Sarangi"],
    answer: "Bugchu",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following instruments was made by Guru Gobind Singh Ji?",
    options: ["Dilruba", "Tumbi", "Khartal", "Kato"],
    answer: "Dilruba",
  },
  {
    question: "Which Punjabi folk instrument is similar to a Veena?",
    options: ["Dilruba", "Dhol", "Sapp", "Sarangi"],
    answer: "Dilruba",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following is a percussion instrument in Punjabi folk music?",
    options: ["Dhadd", "Ektara", "Algoze", "Sapp"],
    answer: "Dhadd",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following instruments is known for being a small version of Tauns?",
    options: ["Dilruba", "Khartal", "Gharha", "Sarangi"],
    answer: "Dilruba",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following is a string instrument in Punjabi folk music?",
    options: ["Ektara", "Dhol", "Khartal", "Kato"],
    answer: "Ektara",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which instrument is used in Punjabi folk music and is a type of cymbals?",
    options: ["Khartal", "Tumbi", "Sapp", "Dilruba"],
    answer: "Khartal",
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following instruments is a type of flute?",
    options: ["Algoze", "Tumbi", "Dhol", "Sarangi"],
    answer: "Algoze",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following instruments is used in Punjabi folk music to make rhythmic sounds?",
    options: ["Gharha", "Kato", "Dhol", "Sapp"],
    answer: "Gharha",
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following instruments is most similar to the dhol?",
    options: ["Dhadd", "Gagar", "Bugchu", "Sapp"],
    answer: "Dhadd",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which festival is celebrated annually in Muktsar to honor the 40 Sikh martyrs (Chali Mukte) who sacrificed their lives for the protection of Guru Gobind Singh Ji?",
    options: ["Mela Maghi", "Lohri", "Vaisakhi", "Gurpurab"],
    answer: "Mela Maghi",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which author won the National Sahitya Akademi award for his short story collection 'Nave Lok'?",
    options: [
      "Kulwant Singh Virk",
      "Surjit Patar",
      "Amrita Pritam",
      "Balwant Gargi",
    ],
    answer: "Kulwant Singh Virk",
  },
  {
    question: "Which traditional Punjabi song is associated with the bride?",
    options: ["Suhag", "Balle Balle", "Tappe", "Dhol Wajda"],
    answer: "Suhag",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which traditional Punjabi dance originated from the tribal communities of the Sandalbar region (now in Pakistan)?",
    options: ["Jhoomar", "Gidda", "Bhangra", "Dhamal"],
    answer: "Jhoomar",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is the traditional Punjabi gathering of farmers and farm laborers for collective crop harvesting called?",
    options: ["Aawat Paoni", "Langar", "Mela", "Pindi"],
    answer: "Aawat Paoni",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Anjuman-i-Punjab was founded with the purpose of translating important English books into Punjabi. Who established it?",
    options: [
      "Dr. Gottlieb Wilhelm Leitner",
      "Sir Michael O'Dwyer",
      "Sir Henry Lawrence",
      "Pandit Nehru",
    ],
    answer: "Dr. Gottlieb Wilhelm Leitner",
  },
  {
    question: "On which date was Anjuman-i-Punjab founded in Lahore?",
    options: [
      "21 January 1865",
      "15 August 1857",
      "14 November 1900",
      "25 December 1875",
    ],
    answer: "21 January 1865",
  },
  {
    question: "Guru Gobind Singh created which musical instrument?",
    options: ["Taus", "Dilruba", "Sitar", "Tabla"],
    answer: "Taus",
  },
  {
    question: "Who invented the Sarode musical instrument?",
    options: ["Bharat Muni", "Guru Nanak Dev Ji", "Baba Farid", "Miyan Tansen"],
    answer: "Bharat Muni",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is the art of mud wall paintings prevalent in villages of Punjab called?",
    options: ["Chowk-Poorana", "Mitti Rangan", "Kalamkari", "Mitti Chitra"],
    answer: "Chowk-Poorana",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following ornaments is worn on the head by men in Punjab?",
    options: ["Sarpesh", "Kutbladar", "Kalgi", "Mukut"],
    answer: "Sarpesh",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following ornaments is worn on the head by men in Punjab?",
    options: ["Kutbladar", "Kalgi", "Mukut", "Sarpesh"],
    answer: "Kutbladar",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following ornaments is worn on the head by men in Punjab?",
    options: ["Kalgi", "Mukut", "Kutbladar", "Sarpesh"],
    answer: "Kalgi",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following ornaments is worn on the head by men in Punjab?",
    options: ["Mukut", "Kalgi", "Kutbladar", "Sarpesh"],
    answer: "Mukut",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following ornaments is worn on the ears by men in Punjab?",
    options: ["Bala", "Murkhi", "Dur", "Birbali"],
    answer: "Bala",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following ornaments is worn on the ears by men in Punjab?",
    options: ["Murkhi", "Bala", "Dur", "Birbali"],
    answer: "Murkhi",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following ornaments is worn on the ears by men in Punjab?",
    options: ["Dur", "Bala", "Murkhi", "Birbali"],
    answer: "Dur",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following ornaments is worn on the ears by men in Punjab?",
    options: ["Birbali", "Bala", "Murkhi", "Dur"],
    answer: "Birbali",
  },
  {
    question: "Which ornament is worn by men on the forehead in Punjab?",
    options: ["Gokuru", "Pahunchi", "Takhti", "Kainta"],
    answer: "Gokuru",
  },
  {
    question: "Which ornament is worn by men around the neck in Punjab?",
    options: ["Naam", "Takhti", "Kainta", "Gokuru"],
    answer: "Naam",
  },
  {
    question: "Which ornament is worn by men around the neck in Punjab?",
    options: ["Takhti", "Naam", "Kainta", "Gokuru"],
    answer: "Takhti",
  },
  {
    question: "Which ornament is worn by men around the neck in Punjab?",
    options: ["Kainta", "Takhti", "Naam", "Gokuru"],
    answer: "Kainta",
  },
  {
    question: "Which fort is located in the Rupnagar district of Punjab?",
    options: [
      "Qila Taragarh",
      "Qila Holgarh",
      "Keshgarh Sahib Fort",
      "All of the above",
    ],
    answer: "All of the above",
  },
  {
    question: "Where is Gobindgarh Fort located?",
    options: ["Amritsar", "Ludhiana", "Patiala", "Jalandhar"],
    answer: "Amritsar",
  },
  {
    question: "Which fort has been named after Mughal emperor Shah Jahan?",
    options: [
      "Shahpur Kandi Fort",
      "Qila Mubarak",
      "Lahore Fort",
      "Kangra Fort",
    ],
    answer: "Shahpur Kandi Fort",
  },
  {
    question: "Which freedom fighter lived at Shahpur Kandi Fort during 1857?",
    options: [
      "Ram Singh Pathania",
      "Bhagat Singh",
      "Sardar Udham Singh",
      "Lala Lajpat Rai",
    ],
    answer: "Ram Singh Pathania",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which memorial commemorates the tercentenary of the Birth of Khalsa?",
    options: [
      "Khalsa Heritage Memorial",
      "Jallianwala Bagh Memorial",
      "Harmandir Sahib Memorial",
      "Patiala Memorial",
    ],
    answer: "Khalsa Heritage Memorial",
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following is a conjunction in Gurmukhi script?",
    options: ["ਰ", "ਤ", "ਨ", "ਪ"],
    answer: "ਰ",
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following is a conjunction in Gurmukhi script?",
    options: ["ਵ", "ਸ", "ਖ", "ਲ"],
    answer: "ਵ",
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following is a conjunction in Gurmukhi script?",
    options: ["ਹ", "ਬ", "ਕ", "ਧ"],
    answer: "ਹ",
  },
  {
    question: "Which dialect is also considered as Taxali Boli?",
    options: ["Majhi", "Doabi", "Malwai", "Pothohari"],
    answer: "Majhi",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which dialect is spoken in the areas between Beas and Satluj rivers?",
    options: ["Doabi", "Majhi", "Malwai", "Pahari"],
    answer: "Doabi",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is known as the Shakespeare of Punjab?",
    options: ["Waris Shah", "Bulleh Shah", "Faiz Ahmed Faiz", "Allama Iqbal"],
    answer: "Waris Shah",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is considered the creator of modern Punjab literature?",
    options: [
      "Bhai Vir Singh",
      "Puran Singh",
      "Amrita Pritam",
      "Chandigarh Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Bhai Vir Singh",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is known as the father of Punjabi drama?",
    options: [
      "Ishwar Chandra Nanda",
      "Bhai Vir Singh",
      "Waris Shah",
      "Amrita Pritam",
    ],
    answer: "Ishwar Chandra Nanda",
  },
  {
    question: "Where was Ishwar Chandra Nanda born?",
    options: ["Gurdaspur", "Amritsar", "Ludhiana", "Jalandhar"],
    answer: "Gurdaspur",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following plays was written by Ishwar Chandra Nanda?",
    options: ["Suhag", "Puran Singh", "Jago Punjabi", "Mirza Sahiba"],
    answer: "Suhag",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following is a play written by Ishwar Chandra Nanda?",
    options: ["Bebe Ram Bhajni", "Kali Gauri", "Heer Ranjha", "Sassi Punnu"],
    answer: "Bebe Ram Bhajni",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following is a play written by Ishwar Chandra Nanda?",
    options: [
      "Lilli Da Vivaah",
      "Mitti Di Khushboo",
      "Tere Ishq Nachaya",
      "Sheherazade",
    ],
    answer: "Lilli Da Vivaah",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following is a play written by Ishwar Chandra Nanda?",
    options: ["Maa Di Deputy", "Sass Khandi", "Khoon Da Badla", "Jagdi Raat"],
    answer: "Maa Di Deputy",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following is a play written by Ishwar Chandra Nanda?",
    options: ["Beeimaan", "Dilruba", "Nasha", "Kashmir Ki Kali"],
    answer: "Beeimaan",
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following compositions is written by Nanak Singh?",
    options: ["Chitta Lahu", "Mitti Da Khud", "Ik Raat", "Jugni"],
    answer: "Chitta Lahu",
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following compositions is written by Nanak Singh?",
    options: [
      "Ikk Mian Do Talware",
      "Sukhmani Sahib",
      "Mitti Da Khushboo",
      "Sassi Punnu",
    ],
    answer: "Ikk Mian Do Talware",
  },
  {
    question: "Which two authors received the Jnanpith Award?",
    options: [
      "Amrita Pritam and Gurdial Singh",
      "Bulleh Shah and Waris Shah",
      "Bhai Vir Singh and Nanak Singh",
      "Mohan Rakesh and Kamleshwar",
    ],
    answer: "Amrita Pritam and Gurdial Singh",
  },
  {
    question: "What is the highest literary award of India?",
    options: [
      "Jnanpith Award",
      "Sahitya Akademi Award",
      "Padma Bhushan",
      "National Film Award",
    ],
    answer: "Jnanpith Award",
  },
  {
    question: "In which year was the Jnanpith Award first instituted?",
    options: ["1961", "1955", "1971", "1982"],
    answer: "1961",
  },
  {
    question: "When was the first Jnanpith Award given?",
    options: ["1965", "1970", "1955", "1985"],
    answer: "1965",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Since which year has the Jnanpith Award been given only for lifetime contribution?",
    options: ["1982", "1975", "1990", "2000"],
    answer: "1982",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is eligible for the Jnanpith Award?",
    options: [
      "Only Indian citizens",
      "Anyone worldwide",
      "Indian citizens and non-residents",
      "Indian citizens and expatriates",
    ],
    answer: "Only Indian citizens",
  },
  {
    question: "Which languages are eligible for the Jnanpith Award?",
    options: [
      "23 languages from the 8th schedule and English",
      "Only Hindi and English",
      "Only Indian regional languages",
      "Any language with a literary tradition",
    ],
    answer: "23 languages from the 8th schedule and English",
  },
  {
    question: "Who awards the Jnanpith Award annually?",
    options: [
      "Bhartiya Jnanpith Organization",
      "Sahitya Akademi",
      "Government of India",
      "Indian Council for Cultural Relations",
    ],
    answer: "Bhartiya Jnanpith Organization",
  },
  {
    question: "Who was the first person to receive the Jnanpith Award?",
    options: [
      "G. Shankar Karup",
      "Sumitranandan Pant",
      "Ashapoorna Devi",
      "Amrita Pritam",
    ],
    answer: "G. Shankar Karup",
  },
  {
    question: "In which year did G. Shankar Karup receive the Jnanpith Award?",
    options: ["1965", "1968", "1976", "1981"],
    answer: "1965",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which language did G. Shankar Karup receive the Jnanpith Award for?",
    options: ["Malayalam", "Hindi", "Bengali", "Punjabi"],
    answer: "Malayalam",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who was the first person to receive the Jnanpith Award for Hindi?",
    options: [
      "Sumitranandan Pant",
      "G. Shankar Karup",
      "Amrita Pritam",
      "Ashapoorna Devi",
    ],
    answer: "Sumitranandan Pant",
  },
  {
    question:
      "In which year did Sumitranandan Pant receive the Jnanpith Award?",
    options: ["1968", "1976", "1981", "1965"],
    answer: "1968",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which language did Sumitranandan Pant receive the Jnanpith Award for?",
    options: ["Hindi", "Malayalam", "Bengali", "Punjabi"],
    answer: "Hindi",
  },
  {
    question: "Who was the first woman to receive the Jnanpith Award?",
    options: [
      "Ashapoorna Devi",
      "Amrita Pritam",
      "Sumitranandan Pant",
      "G. Shankar Karup",
    ],
    answer: "Ashapoorna Devi",
  },
  {
    question: "In which year did Ashapoorna Devi receive the Jnanpith Award?",
    options: ["1976", "1968", "1981", "1965"],
    answer: "1976",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which language did Ashapoorna Devi receive the Jnanpith Award for?",
    options: ["Bengali", "Hindi", "Punjabi", "Malayalam"],
    answer: "Bengali",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who was the first person to receive the Jnanpith Award for Punjabi?",
    options: [
      "Amrita Pritam",
      "Ashapoorna Devi",
      "Sumitranandan Pant",
      "G. Shankar Karup",
    ],
    answer: "Amrita Pritam",
  },
  {
    question: "In which year did Amrita Pritam receive the Jnanpith Award?",
    options: ["1981", "1976", "1965", "1968"],
    answer: "1981",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which language did Amrita Pritam receive the Jnanpith Award for?",
    options: ["Punjabi", "Bengali", "Hindi", "Malayalam"],
    answer: "Punjabi",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the youngest recipient of the Sahitya Akademi Award?",
    options: [
      "Shiv Kumar Batalvi",
      "Dalip Kaur Tiwana",
      "Amrita Pritam",
      "Harbhajan Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Shiv Kumar Batalvi",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is the Sahitya Akademi Award considered in terms of literary recognition in India?",
    options: [
      "2nd highest literary award",
      "Highest literary award",
      "3rd highest literary award",
      "National award for literature",
    ],
    answer: "2nd highest literary award",
  },
  {
    question: "In which year was the Sahitya Akademi Award first instituted?",
    options: ["1954", "1955", "1961", "1965"],
    answer: "1954",
  },
  {
    question: "In which year was the Sahitya Akademi Award first given?",
    options: ["1955", "1965", "1954", "1960"],
    answer: "1955",
  },
  {
    question: "How many languages are eligible for the Sahitya Akademi Award?",
    options: ["24", "23", "25", "22"],
    answer: "24",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following languages is included in the Sahitya Akademi Award eligibility?",
    options: ["Rajasthani", "Kashmiri", "Dogri", "Tamil"],
    answer: "Rajasthani",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who received the Sahitya Akademi Award for her compositions 'Eho Hamara Jeewana' in 1971?",
    options: [
      "Dalip Kaur Tiwana",
      "Amrita Pritam",
      "Shiv Kumar Batalvi",
      "Gurdial Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Dalip Kaur Tiwana",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What is the full title of the work for which Dalip Kaur Tiwana received the Sahitya Akademi Award?",
    options: [
      "Eho Hamara Jeewana",
      "Pinjar",
      "Suno Mere Pyaare",
      "Veer Di Savi",
    ],
    answer: "Eho Hamara Jeewana",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which work by Bhai Vir Singh won the Sahitya Akademi Award in 1955?",
    options: ["Mere Sainya Jio", "Sunehe", "Ik Mian Do Talwaran", "Wadda Vela"],
    answer: "Mere Sainya Jio",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who won the Sahitya Akademi Award for the work 'Sunehe' in 1956?",
    options: ["Amrita Pritam", "Bhai Vir Singh", "Mohan Singh", "Nanak Singh"],
    answer: "Amrita Pritam",
  },
  {
    question:
      "In which year did Mohan Singh win the Sahitya Akademi Award for 'Wadda Vela'?",
    options: ["1959", "1961", "1956", "1965"],
    answer: "1959",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which novel by Nanak Singh won the Sahitya Akademi Award in 1961?",
    options: ["Ik Mian Do Talwaran", "Wadda Vela", "Mere Sainya Jio", "Sunehe"],
    answer: "Ik Mian Do Talwaran",
  },
  {
    question: "Who won the Sahitya Akademi Award for 'Slow Down' in 2017?",
    options: [
      "Nachhatar",
      "Kirpal Kazak",
      "Gurdev Singh Rupana",
      "Dr. Mohanjeet",
    ],
    answer: "Nachhatar",
  },
  {
    question:
      "What work by Dr. Mohanjeet won the Sahitya Akademi Award in 2018?",
    options: [
      "Kone Da Sooraj",
      "Antheen",
      "Mann Di Chip",
      "Main Aynghosh Nahi",
    ],
    answer: "Kone Da Sooraj",
  },
  {
    question:
      "In which year did Kirpal Kazak win the Sahitya Akademi Award for 'Antheen'?",
    options: ["2019", "2020", "2021", "2018"],
    answer: "2019",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which work by Gurdev Singh Rupana won the Sahitya Akademi Award in 2020?",
    options: ["Aam Khass", "Mann Di Chip", "Sullan Da Salan", "Slow Down"],
    answer: "Aam Khass",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who won the Sahitya Akademi Award for 'Sullan Da Salan' in 2021?",
    options: [
      "Khalid Hussain",
      "Gurdev Singh Rupana",
      "Kirpal Kazak",
      "Nachhatar",
    ],
    answer: "Khalid Hussain",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which short story collection by Sukhjit won the Sahitya Akademi Award in 2022?",
    options: ["Main Aynghosh Nahi", "Antheen", "Sullan Da Salan", "Aam Khass"],
    answer: "Main Aynghosh Nahi",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which poetry collection by Swarnjit Savi won the Sahitya Akademi Award in 2023?",
    options: [
      "Mann Di Chip",
      "Kone Da Sooraj",
      "Wadda Vela",
      "Ik Mian Do Talwaran",
    ],
    answer: "Mann Di Chip",
  },
  {
    question: "For which book did Amrita Pritam receive the Jnanpith Award?",
    options: ["Kagaz Te Kanwas", "Sunehe", "Pinjar", "Meri Sainya Jio"],
    answer: "Kagaz Te Kanwas",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who was the first recipient of the Sahitya Akademi Award in the Punjabi language?",
    options: ["Bhai Vir Singh", "Amrita Pritam", "Mohan Singh", "Nanak Singh"],
    answer: "Bhai Vir Singh",
  },
  {
    question: "When was the Saraswati Samman instituted?",
    options: ["1991", "1985", "2000", "1982"],
    answer: "1991",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which language did Harivansh Rai Bachchan receive the Saraswati Samman for in 1991?",
    options: ["Hindi", "Marathi", "Punjabi", "Sanskrit"],
    answer: "Hindi",
  },
  {
    question: "Who received the Saraswati Samman in 2019 for 'Chequebook'?",
    options: [
      "Vasdev Mohi",
      "Surjit Paatar",
      "Harbhajan Singh",
      "Dalip Kaur Tiwana",
    ],
    answer: "Vasdev Mohi",
  },
  {
    question:
      "In which language did Sharankumar Limbale receive the Saraswati Samman in 2020 for 'Sanatan'?",
    options: ["Marathi", "Sindhi", "Bengali", "Tamil"],
    answer: "Marathi",
  },
  {
    question:
      "For which work did Harbhajan Singh receive the Saraswati Samman in 1994?",
    options: [
      "Rukh Te Rishi",
      "Lafzan Di Dargah",
      "Katha Kaho Urvashi",
      "Chequebook",
    ],
    answer: "Rukh Te Rishi",
  },
  {
    question: "In 2001, who won the Saraswati Samman for 'Katha Kaho Urvashi'?",
    options: [
      "Dalip Kaur Tiwana",
      "Harbhajan Singh",
      "Sivasankari",
      "Surjit Paatar",
    ],
    answer: "Dalip Kaur Tiwana",
  },
  {
    question:
      "For which work did Surjit Paatar win the Saraswati Samman in 2009?",
    options: [
      "Lafzan Di Dargah",
      "Rukh Te Rishi",
      "Sanatan",
      "Katha Kaho Urvashi",
    ],
    answer: "Lafzan Di Dargah",
  },
  {
    question:
      "In which language did Sivasankari receive the Saraswati Samman in 2022?",
    options: ["Tamil", "Punjabi", "Sindhi", "Hindi"],
    answer: "Tamil",
  },
  {
    question: "Which work by Prabha Verma won the Saraswati Samman in 2023?",
    options: ["Roudra Sathwikam", "Sanatan", "Chequebook", "Lafzan Di Dargah"],
    answer: "Roudra Sathwikam",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which prize is awarded by the Canada India Education Society and the Department of Asian Studies, University of British Columbia for Punjabi language works in Gurmukhi or Shahmukhi script?",
    options: [
      "The Dhahan Prize",
      "The Jnanpith Award",
      "The Saraswati Samman",
      "The Sahitya Akademi Award",
    ],
    answer: "The Dhahan Prize",
  },
  {
    question:
      "The Dhahan Prize is named after which Canadian Punjabi businessman?",
    options: [
      "Barj Singh Dhahan",
      "Avtar Singh Billing",
      "Darshan Singh",
      "Jarnail Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Barj Singh Dhahan",
  },
  {
    question: "In which year was the Dhahan Prize first awarded?",
    options: ["2013", "2014", "2015", "2016"],
    answer: "2013",
  },
  {
    question: "Who won the Dhahan Prize in 2014 for 'Khali Khoohaan Di Katha'?",
    options: [
      "Avtar Singh Billing",
      "Darshan Singh",
      "Jarnail Singh",
      "Pargat Singh Satauj",
    ],
    answer: "Avtar Singh Billing",
  },
  {
    question: "Who received the Dhahan Prize in 2015 for 'Lota'?",
    options: [
      "Darshan Singh",
      "Jarnail Singh",
      "Pargat Singh Satauj",
      "Baldev Singh Sadaknama",
    ],
    answer: "Darshan Singh",
  },
  {
    question: "Which work earned Jarnail Singh the Dhahan Prize in 2016?",
    options: [
      "Kaale Varke",
      "Khali Khoohaan Di Katha",
      "Sooraj Di Akh",
      "Jyona Sach Baki Jhooth",
    ],
    answer: "Kaale Varke",
  },
  {
    question: "Who won the Dhahan Prize in 2017 for 'Khabar Ik Pind Di'?",
    options: [
      "Pargat Singh Satauj",
      "Jarnail Singh",
      "Baldev Singh Sadaknama",
      "Jatinder Singh Haans",
    ],
    answer: "Pargat Singh Satauj",
  },
  {
    question:
      "For which work did Baldev Singh Sadaknama win the Dhahan Prize in 2018?",
    options: [
      "Sooraj Di Akh",
      "Khabar Ik Pind Di",
      "Jyona Sach Baki Jhooth",
      "Zanani Paud",
    ],
    answer: "Sooraj Di Akh",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which work earned Jatinder Singh Haans the Dhahan Prize in 2019?",
    options: [
      "Jyona Sach Baki Jhooth",
      "Zanani Paud",
      "Dubolia",
      "Bhukh Eon Sah Lendi Hai",
    ],
    answer: "Jyona Sach Baki Jhooth",
  },
  {
    question: "Who won the Dhahan Prize in 2020 for 'Zanani Paud'?",
    options: ["Kesra Ram", "Nain Sukh", "Balwinder Grewal", "Deepti Babuta"],
    answer: "Kesra Ram",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which short stories collection earned Nain Sukh the Dhahan Prize in 2021?",
    options: [
      "Jogi, Sap, Trah",
      "Safety Kit",
      "Dubolia",
      "Bhukh Eon Sah Lendi Hai",
    ],
    answer: "Jogi, Sap, Trah",
  },
  {
    question:
      "For which work did Balwinder Grewal win the Dhahan Prize in 2022?",
    options: [
      "Dubolia",
      "Jogi, Sap, Trah",
      "Bhukh Eon Sah Lendi Hai",
      "Safety Kit",
    ],
    answer: "Dubolia",
  },
  {
    question: "Which work earned Deepti Babuta the Dhahan Prize in 2023?",
    options: [
      "Bhukh Eon Sah Lendi Hai",
      "Dubolia",
      "Safety Kit",
      "Jogi, Sap, Trah",
    ],
    answer: "Bhukh Eon Sah Lendi Hai",
  },
  {
    question: "Who won the Dhahan Prize in 2024 for 'Safety Kit'?",
    options: ["Jinder", "Kesra Ram", "Nain Sukh", "Balwinder Grewal"],
    answer: "Jinder",
  },
  {
    question: "Which composition is associated with Guru Nanak?",
    options: ["Asa Di Var", "Bachitar Natak", "Lavan", "Anand Sahib"],
    answer: "Asa Di Var",
  },
  {
    question: "Which composition is associated with Guru Gobind Singh?",
    options: ["Bachitar Natak", "Asa Di Var", "Lavan", "Anand Sahib"],
    answer: "Bachitar Natak",
  },
  {
    question: "Which composition is associated with Guru Ram Das?",
    options: ["Lavan", "Bachitar Natak", "Asa Di Var", "Anand Sahib"],
    answer: "Lavan",
  },
  {
    question: "Which composition is associated with Guru Amar Das?",
    options: ["Anand Sahib", "Lavan", "Bachitar Natak", "Asa Di Var"],
    answer: "Anand Sahib",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the first recorded poet in Punjabi history?",
    options: ["Baba Farid", "Guru Nanak", "Guru Gobind Singh", "Guru Ram Das"],
    answer: "Baba Farid",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is considered the Adi Kavi (first poet) of Punjabi history?",
    options: [
      "Guru Goraknath",
      "Guru Nanak",
      "Baba Farid",
      "Guru Gobind Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Guru Goraknath",
  },
  {
    question: "Who wrote the Sikh Encyclopedia 'Mahan Kosh'?",
    options: [
      "Bhai Kahn Singh Nabha",
      "Bhai Vir Singh",
      "Bhai Randhir Singh",
      "Bhai Puran Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Bhai Kahn Singh Nabha",
  },
  {
    question: "Where was Bhai Kahn Singh Nabha born?",
    options: [
      "Sabaz Banera, Patiala",
      "Amritsar",
      "Ludhiana",
      "Fatehgarh Sahib",
    ],
    answer: "Sabaz Banera, Patiala",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following is NOT a work written by Bhai Kahn Singh Nabha?",
    options: [
      "Raj Dharma",
      "Ham Hindu Nahin",
      "Gurmat Prabhakar",
      "Sakhi Guru Nanak",
    ],
    answer: "Sakhi Guru Nanak",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following books was written by Bhai Kahn Singh Nabha?",
    options: [
      "Raj Dharma",
      "Bani Guru",
      "Sri Dasam Granth",
      "Chhandayan di Duniya",
    ],
    answer: "Raj Dharma",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which work was authored by Bhai Kahn Singh Nabha that deals with the teachings of Sikhism?",
    options: [
      "Gurmat Prabhakar",
      "Vishnu Puran",
      "Chandi Di Waar",
      "Gur Shabad Alankar",
    ],
    answer: "Gurmat Prabhakar",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which work written by Bhai Kahn Singh Nabha is a part of his contribution to Sikh literature?",
    options: [
      "Gurmat Sudhakar",
      "Vishnu Puran",
      "Gur Shabad Alankar",
      "Raj Dharma",
    ],
    answer: "Gurmat Sudhakar",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the author of 'Merian Abhul Yaddan'?",
    options: [
      "Gurbaksh Singh Preetlari",
      "Amrita Pritam",
      "Surjit Patar",
      "Bhai Vir Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Gurbaksh Singh Preetlari",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which composition earned Prof. Mohan Singh the Sahitya Akademi award in 1959?",
    options: ["Wadda Vela", "Ik Mian Do Talwaran", "Suhe Agni", "Sunehe"],
    answer: "Wadda Vela",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who won the Saraswati Samman for the composition 'Katha Kaho Urvashi'?",
    options: [
      "Dalip Kaur Tiwana",
      "Surjit Patar",
      "Harbhajan Singh",
      "Mohan Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Dalip Kaur Tiwana",
  },
  {
    question: "'Hanere Vich Sulagdi Varnmala' is a composition of which poet?",
    options: [
      "Surjit Patar",
      "Amrita Pritam",
      "Bhai Vir Singh",
      "Khalid Hussain",
    ],
    answer: "Surjit Patar",
  },
  {
    question: "Where was Surjit Patar born?",
    options: ["Patar Kalan, Jalandhar", "Amritsar", "Ludhiana", "Gurdaspur"],
    answer: "Patar Kalan, Jalandhar",
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following is a work of Surjit Patar?",
    options: [
      "Hanere Vich Sulagdi Varnmala",
      "Mere Sainya Jio",
      "Sunehe",
      "Rukh Te Rishi",
    ],
    answer: "Hanere Vich Sulagdi Varnmala",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which award did Surjit Patar receive for 'Hanere Vich Sulagdi Varnmala'?",
    options: [
      "Sahitya Akademi Award",
      "Padma Shri",
      "Saraswati Samman",
      "Jnanpith Award",
    ],
    answer: "Sahitya Akademi Award",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following works by Surjit Patar won the Saraswati Samman?",
    options: [
      "Lafzan Di Dargah",
      "Hanere Vich Sulagdi Varnmala",
      "Katha Kaho Urvashi",
      "Sunehe",
    ],
    answer: "Lafzan Di Dargah",
  },
  {
    question: "What recognition did Surjit Patar receive in 2012?",
    options: [
      "Padma Shri",
      "Sahitya Akademi Award",
      "Jnanpith Award",
      "Saraswati Samman",
    ],
    answer: "Padma Shri",
  },
  {
    question: "What is the autobiography of Dalip Kaur Tiwana?",
    options: [
      "Nange Pairan Da Safar",
      "Meri Zindagi",
      "Sunehe",
      "Ik Mian Do Talwaran",
    ],
    answer: "Nange Pairan Da Safar",
  },
  {
    question: "Where was Dalip Kaur Tiwana born?",
    options: ["Rabbow, Ludhiana", "Patiala", "Amritsar", "Fatehgarh Sahib"],
    answer: "Rabbow, Ludhiana",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following works by Dalip Kaur Tiwana won the Sahitya Akademi Award in 1971?",
    options: [
      "Eho Hamara Jeevana",
      "Ik Mian Do Talwaran",
      "Ikk Vela Pichhle Paas",
      "Eho Hamara Jeevana",
    ],
    answer: "Eho Hamara Jeevana",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which award did Dalip Kaur Tiwana receive for the composition 'Katha Kaho Urvashi'?",
    options: [
      "Saraswati Samman",
      "Sahitya Akademi Award",
      "Jnanpith Award",
      "Padma Bhushan",
    ],
    answer: "Saraswati Samman",
  },
  {
    question:
      "In honor of which Muslim Pir is the Roshni Fair celebrated at Jagraon?",
    options: [
      "Abdul Kader Jalani",
      "Baba Farid",
      "Khawaja Moinuddin Chishti",
      "Bulleh Shah",
    ],
    answer: "Abdul Kader Jalani",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which is one of the seven popular tragic romances from Sindh and Baluchistan?",
    options: ["Sassi Punnu", "Heer Ranjha", "Mirza Sahiban", "Laila Majnu"],
    answer: "Sassi Punnu",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which festival is celebrated to commemorate the establishment of Khalsa by Guru Gobind Singh?",
    options: ["Vaisakhi", "Diwali", "Gurpurab", "Lohri"],
    answer: "Vaisakhi",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Where is the Urs or Rauza Sharif celebrated with great pomp and show?",
    options: ["Sirhind", "Amritsar", "Nanded", "Damdama Sahib"],
    answer: "Sirhind",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following dances is performed by both males and females in Punjab?",
    options: ["Jindua", "Bhangra", "Gidda", "Karthi"],
    answer: "Jindua",
  },
  {
    question: "What does the term 'Jindua' mean?",
    options: ["Love", "Victory", "Peace", "Unity"],
    answer: "Love",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which of the following instruments consists of a pair of wooden flutes?",
    options: ["Algoza", "Dhol", "Sitar", "Sarangi"],
    answer: "Algoza",
  },
  {
    question: "Where is the Punjabi Sahitya Akademi situated?",
    options: ["Ludhiana", "Amritsar", "Chandigarh", "Patiala"],
    answer: "Ludhiana",
  },
  {
    question: "Which script is used to write Indian Punjabi?",
    options: ["Gurmukhi", "Shahmukhi", "Devanagari", "Roman"],
    answer: "Gurmukhi",
  },
  {
    question: "Who wrote Zafarnama?",
    options: [
      "Guru Gobind Singh Ji",
      "Guru Nanak Dev Ji",
      "Bhai Gurdas Ji",
      "Bhai Kahan Singh Nabha",
    ],
    answer: "Guru Gobind Singh Ji",
  },
  {
    question: "In which year was Zafarnama written and to whom was it sent?",
    options: [
      "1705, Aurangzeb",
      "1707, Ahmad Shah Durrani",
      "1700, Mughal Emperor",
      "1701, Nader Shah",
    ],
    answer: "1705, Aurangzeb",
  },
  {
    question: "Where was Zafarnama written?",
    options: ["Village Dina (now Moga)", "Chamkaur", "Amritsar", "Nanded"],
    answer: "Village Dina (now Moga)",
  },
  {
    question: "How many stanzas does Zafarnama contain?",
    options: ["111", "100", "150", "120"],
    answer: "111",
  },
  {
    question:
      "On which date did Guru Gobind Singh Ji send Zafarnama to Aurangzeb?",
    options: [
      "5th January 1707",
      "10th January 1707",
      "1st January 1705",
      "12th December 1705",
    ],
    answer: "5th January 1707",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who helped Guru Gobind Singh Ji in sending Zafarnama to Aurangzeb?",
    options: [
      "Daya Singh, Dharam Singh, and Sambhal Singh",
      "Bhai Kanhaiya, Bhai Jetha Singh",
      "Bhai Gurdas Ji",
      "Bhai Manjh Ji",
    ],
    answer: "Daya Singh, Dharam Singh, and Sambhal Singh",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which work of Guru Gobind Singh Ji contains the verse 'Chun akr az hameh heelate dar guzasht, halal ast burden bi-shamsher dast'?",
    options: ["Zafarnama", "Bachitar Natak", "Guru Granth Sahib", "Jangnama"],
    answer: "Zafarnama",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which verse was written by Guru Nanak Dev Ji after the invasion of Babur?",
    options: [
      "'Aiti maar pyi kurlane tain ki dard na aaya'",
      "'Ik onkar satnam'",
      "'Raag Asa di Var'",
      "'Satgur pyarey di jaat'",
    ],
    answer: "'Aiti maar pyi kurlane tain ki dard na aaya'",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Where was Guru Nanak Dev Ji arrested after his Udasis and later released?",
    options: ["Saidpura", "Kartarpur", "Amritsar", "Makkah"],
    answer: "Saidpura",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who is the author of 'Ain-i-Akbari' (Akbarnama), which mentions the word Punjab?",
    options: ["Abul Fazl", "Babar", "Akbar", "Ibn Battuta"],
    answer: "Abul Fazl",
  },
  {
    question: "Which historical book was written by Firdausi?",
    options: [
      "Shahnama",
      "Tuzuk-i-Jahangiri",
      "Rajtarangini",
      "Tariq-i-Mubarak Shah",
    ],
    answer: "Shahnama",
  },
  {
    question: "Who started the Todar Mal system or Dahsala tax system?",
    options: [
      "Todar Mal",
      "Guru Nanak Dev Ji",
      "Shivaji Maharaj",
      "Raja Kesar Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Todar Mal",
  },
  {
    question: "Asht Diggaj were part of the court of which king?",
    options: [
      "Krishna Dev Rai",
      "Shivaji Maharaj",
      "Akbar",
      "Prithviraj Chauhan",
    ],
    answer: "Krishna Dev Rai",
  },
  {
    question: "Asht Pradan were part of the court of which king?",
    options: [
      "Chhatrapati Shivaji Maharaj",
      "Raja Bhoj",
      "Sher Shah Suri",
      "Guru Gobind Singh Ji",
    ],
    answer: "Chhatrapati Shivaji Maharaj",
  },
  {
    question:
      "'Loona', a verse play based on the ancient legend of Puran Bhagat, was written by which author?",
    options: [
      "Shiv Kumar Batalvi",
      "Waris Shah",
      "Nanak Singh",
      "Surjit Patar",
    ],
    answer: "Shiv Kumar Batalvi",
  },
  {
    question: "In which year was Shiv Kumar Batalvi's work 'Loona' published?",
    options: ["1965", "1970", "1960", "1955"],
    answer: "1965",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Shiv Kumar Batalvi, the youngest recipient of the Sahitya Akademi Award in 1967, was born in which city?",
    options: ["Sialkot", "Amritsar", "Ludhiana", "Patiala"],
    answer: "Sialkot",
  },
  {
    question: "Which literary figure is known as the 'John Keats of Punjab'?",
    options: [
      "Shiv Kumar Batalvi",
      "Bhai Vir Singh",
      "Amrita Pritam",
      "Surjit Patar",
    ],
    answer: "Shiv Kumar Batalvi",
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following is a work by Shiv Kumar Batalvi?",
    options: ["Loona", "Rukh te Rishi", "Sunehe", "Meri Sainya Jio"],
    answer: "Loona",
  },
  {
    question: "Which of the following works was written by Shiv Kumar Batalvi?",
    options: [
      "Piran da Paraga",
      "Tariq-i-Mubarak Shah",
      "Wadda Vela",
      "Zafarnama",
    ],
    answer: "Piran da Paraga",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Shiv Kumar Batalvi's works like 'Aate Diyan Chiriyaan' and 'Birha Tru Sultan' are a part of which genre?",
    options: ["Poetry", "Drama", "Short Stories", "History"],
    answer: "Poetry",
  },
  {
    question: "Aarti is the work of which author?",
    options: [
      "Shiv Kumar Batalvi",
      "Surjit Patar",
      "Waris Shah",
      "Bhai Vir Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Shiv Kumar Batalvi",
  },
  {
    question: "'Piran da Paraga' is a work written by which author?",
    options: [
      "Shiv Kumar Batalvi",
      "Nanak Singh",
      "Mohan Singh",
      "Amrita Pritam",
    ],
    answer: "Shiv Kumar Batalvi",
  },
  {
    question: "'Lajwanti' is a composition by which Punjabi poet?",
    options: [
      "Shiv Kumar Batalvi",
      "Gurdev Singh Rupana",
      "Dalip Kaur Tiwana",
      "Surjit Patar",
    ],
    answer: "Shiv Kumar Batalvi",
  },
  {
    question: "'Aate Diyan Chiriyaan' is the work of which Punjabi poet?",
    options: [
      "Shiv Kumar Batalvi",
      "Amrita Pritam",
      "Nanak Singh",
      "Waris Shah",
    ],
    answer: "Shiv Kumar Batalvi",
  },
  {
    question: "'Mainu Vida Karo' is a work by which Punjabi author?",
    options: [
      "Shiv Kumar Batalvi",
      "Kirpal Kazak",
      "Surjit Patar",
      "Dalip Kaur Tiwana",
    ],
    answer: "Shiv Kumar Batalvi",
  },
  {
    question: "'Darmandan Diyan Aahin' was written by which poet?",
    options: [
      "Shiv Kumar Batalvi",
      "Bhai Vir Singh",
      "Nanak Singh",
      "Mohan Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Shiv Kumar Batalvi",
  },
  {
    question: "'Birha Tru Sultan' is a work written by?",
    options: [
      "Shiv Kumar Batalvi",
      "Surjit Patar",
      "Bhai Vir Singh",
      "Nanak Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Shiv Kumar Batalvi",
  },
  {
    question: "'Loona' is a famous work by which poet?",
    options: [
      "Shiv Kumar Batalvi",
      "Waris Shah",
      "Surjit Patar",
      "Nanak Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Shiv Kumar Batalvi",
  },
  {
    question: "'Main te Main' is written by which poet?",
    options: [
      "Shiv Kumar Batalvi",
      "Mohan Singh",
      "Amrita Pritam",
      "Nanak Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Shiv Kumar Batalvi",
  },
  {
    question: "'Samuchi Kavita' is a collection of poems by which poet?",
    options: [
      "Shiv Kumar Batalvi",
      "Surjit Patar",
      "Dalip Kaur Tiwana",
      "Bhai Vir Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Shiv Kumar Batalvi",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which bani is the first in the Sri Guru Granth Sahib and is recited in the morning?",
    options: ["Japji Sahib", "Rehraas Sahib", "Sukhmani Sahib", "Anand Sahib"],
    answer: "Japji Sahib",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is mentioned in the songs of the Lohri festival?",
    options: [
      "Dulla Bhatti",
      "Raja Dahir",
      "Maharaja Ranjit Singh",
      "Shivaji Maharaj",
    ],
    answer: "Dulla Bhatti",
  },
  {
    question: "What is the national musical instrument of Afghanistan?",
    options: ["Sitar", "Tabla", "Rabab", "Harmonium"],
    answer: "Rabab",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which crop is shown in the official seal of the Punjab government?",
    options: ["Rice", "Wheat", "Sugarcane", "Cotton"],
    answer: "Wheat",
  },
  {
    question:
      "In how many languages is 'Punjab Govt.' written in the official seal of Punjab?",
    options: ["2", "3", "4", "5"],
    answer: "3",
  },
  {
    question: "From which text is 'Satyamev Jayate' taken?",
    options: ["Bhagavad Gita", "Vedas", "Mundaka Upanishad", "Ramayana"],
    answer: "Mundaka Upanishad",
  },
  {
    question:
      "According to the Punjabi calendar, which is the first month of the year?",
    options: ["Chet", "Baisakh", "Maghar", "Phagun"],
    answer: "Chet",
  },
  {
    question: "Who started the Vikram Samwat calendar?",
    options: [
      "King Vikramaditya",
      "Emperor Ashoka",
      "Kushana King Kanishka",
      "Chandragupta Maurya",
    ],
    answer: "King Vikramaditya",
  },
  {
    question: "The Saka Samwat was started by which king?",
    options: [
      "King Vikramaditya",
      "King Kanishka",
      "Raja Harishchandra",
      "Samudragupta",
    ],
    answer: "King Kanishka",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which calendar is the official calendar of the Government of India?",
    options: [
      "Vikram Samwat",
      "Saka Samwat",
      "Gregorian Calendar",
      "Hijri Calendar",
    ],
    answer: "Saka Samwat",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Which honor was conferred upon Bhai Veer Singh by Punjab University?",
    options: [
      "Doctor of Oriental Learning",
      "Padma Bhushan",
      "Sahitya Akademi Award",
      "Shanti Swarup Bhatnagar Award",
    ],
    answer: "Doctor of Oriental Learning",
  },
  {
    question: "Who wrote the book 'Jung Nama'?",
    options: [
      "Bhai Veer Singh",
      "Shah Hussain",
      "Guru Nanak Dev Ji",
      "Amrita Pritam",
    ],
    answer: "Shah Hussain",
  },
  {
    question: "Who wrote 'Japji Sahib'?",
    options: [
      "Guru Gobind Singh Ji",
      "Guru Nanak Dev Ji",
      "Bhai Veer Singh",
      "Amrita Pritam",
    ],
    answer: "Guru Nanak Dev Ji",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is the author of 'Gulab Da Ful'?",
    options: [
      "Shah Hussain",
      "Bhai Veer Singh",
      "Bhai Kahan Singh Nabha",
      "Amrita Pritam",
    ],
    answer: "Bhai Veer Singh",
  },
  {
    question: "Who authored the book 'Delhi Diyan Gallan'?",
    options: [
      "Amrita Pritam",
      "Guru Nanak Dev Ji",
      "Bhai Veer Singh",
      "Shah Hussain",
    ],
    answer: "Amrita Pritam",
  },
  {
    question: "Who wrote 'Awwal Allah Noor Upaya, Kudrat De Sab Bande'?",
    options: [
      "Bhai Veer Singh",
      "Bhai Kahan Singh Nabha",
      "Bhagat Kabir",
      "Guru Nanak Dev Ji",
    ],
    answer: "Bhagat Kabir",
  },
  {
    question: "Where is the Maghi Mela celebrated?",
    options: ["Anandpur Sahib", "Muktsar", "Ludhiana", "Kila Raipur"],
    answer: "Muktsar",
  },
  {
    question: "Which mela is celebrated in Ludhiana?",
    options: ["Maghi Mela", "Chappar Mela", "Holla Mohalla", "Rural Sports"],
    answer: "Chappar Mela",
  },
  {
    question: "Where is the Holla Mohalla festival held?",
    options: ["Muktsar", "Anandpur Sahib", "Ludhiana", "Kila Raipur"],
    answer: "Anandpur Sahib",
  },
  {
    question: "Where are the Rural Sports held?",
    options: ["Anandpur Sahib", "Ludhiana", "Kila Raipur", "Muktsar"],
    answer: "Kila Raipur",
  },
  {
    question:
      "Who was the first Punjabi poet to use the symbol of human relationship between wife and husband to express his longing for union with the divine?",
    options: [
      "Baba Farid",
      "Guru Nanak Dev Ji",
      "Shah Hussain",
      "Guru Gobind Singh Ji",
    ],
    answer: "Baba Farid",
  },
  {
    question: "What is the meaning of the word 'Punjab'?",
    options: [
      "Land of five rivers",
      "Land of wheat",
      "Land of five kings",
      "Land of rivers",
    ],
    answer: "Land of five rivers",
  },
  {
    question: "Which are the major dialects of Punjabi spoken in Punjab?",
    options: [
      "Majhi, Malwi, Puadhi",
      "Majhi, Doabi, Bhatti",
      "Malwi, Puadhi, Dhani",
      "Majhi, Malwi, Gojri",
    ],
    answer: "Majhi, Malwi, Puadhi",
  },
  {
    question: "Which doab does Majha belong to?",
    options: ["Bari Doab", "Cis-Satluj Doab", "Bisht Doab", "Saraswati Doab"],
    answer: "Bari Doab",
  },
  {
    question: "Which doab does Malwa belong to?",
    options: ["Bari Doab", "Cis-Satluj Doab", "Bisht Doab", "Saraswati Doab"],
    answer: "Cis-Satluj Doab",
  },
  {
    question: "Which doab does Doaba belong to?",
    options: ["Bari Doab", "Cis-Satluj Doab", "Bisht Doab", "Bisht Doab"],
    answer: "Bisht Doab",
  },
  {
    question: "Who is known as Punjab’s bearded Mother Teresa?",
    options: [
      "Bhai Puran Singh",
      "Bhai Kahan Singh Nabha",
      "Bhai Vir Singh",
      "Baba Farid",
    ],
    answer: "Bhai Puran Singh",
  },
  {
    question: "Who wrote the composition 'ਮੜ੍ਹੀ ਦਾ ਦੀਵਾ'?",
    options: [
      "Bhai Veer Singh",
      "Gurdial Singh",
      "Surjit Patar",
      "Shiv Kumar Batalvi",
    ],
    answer: "Gurdial Singh",
  },
  {
    question: "Which famous Punjabi author wrote 'ਅਧ ਚਨਣੀ ਰਾਤ'?",
    options: [
      "Gurdial Singh",
      "Shiv Kumar Batalvi",
      "Surjit Patar",
      "Bhai Veer Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Gurdial Singh",
  },
  {
    question: "Who started The Tribune newspaper?",
    options: [
      "Dyal Singh Majithia",
      "Lala Lajpat Rai",
      "Bhai Vir Singh",
      "Shiv Kumar Batalvi",
    ],
    answer: "Dyal Singh Majithia",
  },
  {
    question: "Where is the centre of newspapers in Punjab?",
    options: ["Ludhiana", "Amritsar", "Jalandhar", "Patiala"],
    answer: "Jalandhar",
  },
  {
    question: "Who publishes Khoj Darpan?",
    options: [
      "Guru Nanak Dev University, Amritsar",
      "Punjabi University, Patiala",
      "Guru Gobind Singh University, Fatehgarh Sahib",
      "Punjab University, Chandigarh",
    ],
    answer: "Guru Nanak Dev University, Amritsar",
  },
  {
    question: "What was the profession of Bhai Lalo?",
    options: ["Carpenter", "Blacksmith", "Farmer", "Teacher"],
    answer: "Carpenter",
  },
  {
    question: "‘ਅੰਨੇ ਘੋੜੇ ਦਾ ਦਾਨ’ is the work of?",
    options: [
      "Gurdial Singh",
      "Shiv Kumar Batalvi",
      "Surjit Patar",
      "Bhai Vir Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Gurdial Singh",
  },
  {
    question: "‘ਬੇਗਾਨਾ ਪਿੰਡ’ is the work of?",
    options: [
      "Gurdial Singh",
      "Shiv Kumar Batalvi",
      "Surjit Patar",
      "Bhai Vir Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Gurdial Singh",
  },
  {
    question: "‘ਕੁੱਤਾ ਤੇ ਆਦਮੀ’ is the work of?",
    options: [
      "Gurdial Singh",
      "Shiv Kumar Batalvi",
      "Surjit Patar",
      "Bhai Vir Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Gurdial Singh",
  },
  {
    question: "The Tribune newspaper was started by?",
    options: [
      "Dyal Singh Majithia",
      "Bhai Vir Singh",
      "Shiv Kumar Batalvi",
      "Surjit Patar",
    ],
    answer: "Dyal Singh Majithia",
  },
  {
    question: "The center of newspapers in Punjab is located in?",
    options: ["Amritsar", "Jalandhar", "Ludhiana", "Patiala"],
    answer: "Jalandhar",
  },
  {
    question: "Khoj Darpan is published by?",
    options: [
      "Guru Nanak Dev University, Amritsar",
      "Punjabi University, Patiala",
      "Punjabi Sahitya Academy, Ludhiana",
      "Guru Gobind Singh University, Fatehgarh Sahib",
    ],
    answer: "Guru Nanak Dev University, Amritsar",
  },
  {
    question: "The profession of Bhai Lalo was?",
    options: ["Carpenter", "Blacksmith", "Merchant", "Farmer"],
    answer: "Carpenter",
  },
  {
    question: "Haider Sheikh Mela is celebrated at?",
    options: ["Malerkotla", "Amritsar", "Fatehgarh Sahib", "Patiala"],
    answer: "Malerkotla",
  },
  {
    question: "Haji Peer Mela is celebrated at?",
    options: ["Bathinda", "Fatehgarh Sahib", "Jalandhar", "Patiala"],
    answer: "Bathinda",
  },
  {
    question: "Gadri Babe da Mela is held at?",
    options: [
      "Desh Bhagat Yadgari Hall, Jalandhar",
      "Rang Mahal, Amritsar",
      "Kila Raipur",
      "Golden Temple, Amritsar",
    ],
    answer: "Desh Bhagat Yadgari Hall, Jalandhar",
  },
  {
    question: "Shaheedi Jorh Mela is celebrated at?",
    options: ["Fatehgarh Sahib, Sirhind", "Patiala", "Ludhiana", "Jalandhar"],
    answer: "Fatehgarh Sahib, Sirhind",
  },
  {
    question: "The Kali Mata Temple in Patiala was built by which ruler?",
    options: [
      "Raja Bhupinder Singh",
      "Maharaja Ranjit Singh",
      "Maharaja Kesar Singh",
      "Raja Gajpat Singh",
    ],
    answer: "Raja Bhupinder Singh",
  },
  {
    question: "The Punjab Police Commando Training Centre is located in?",
    options: ["Patiala", "Jalandhar", "Amritsar", "Ludhiana"],
    answer: "Patiala",
  },
  {
    question:
      "‘Tura e Marwadi’ refers to a decorative embellishment on which item?",
    options: [
      "Marwari turban (safa)",
      "Punjabi phulkari",
      "Rajasthani shawl",
      "Sindhi cap",
    ],
    answer: "Marwari turban (safa)",
  },
];
